<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Zayde a Spanish history, or, romance / originally written in French by Monsieur Segray ; done into English by P. Porter, Esq.</title>
            <title>Zaïde. English</title>
            <author>La Fayette, Madame de (Marie-Madeleine Pioche de La Vergne), 1634-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L172A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12493040</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12493040</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 638:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Zayde a Spanish history, or, romance / originally written in French by Monsieur Segray ; done into English by P. Porter, Esq.</title>
                  <title>Zaïde. English</title>
                  <author>La Fayette, Madame de (Marie-Madeleine Pioche de La Vergne), 1634-1693.</author>
                  <author>Segrais, Jean Regnauld de, 1624-1701.</author>
                  <author>Porter, P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 175 p., 1 leaf of plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Written by Comtesse de Lafayette with the assistance of Segrais.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: second part lacking in filmed copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:62420:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62420:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ZAYDE. A Spaniſh Hiſtory, OR, ROMANCE. Originally Written in
French.</p>
            <p>By Monſieur <hi>Segray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Done into Engliſh by <hi>P. Porter,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt Part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the
<hi>Popes-Head</hi> in the Lower Walk of the <hi>New-Exchange</hi> in the
<hi>Strand,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62420:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62420:2"/>
            <head>TO THE High-Born and Mighty PRINCE Henry Fits-Roy, Duke of
<hi>Grafton,</hi> Earl of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> Vicount <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> Baron
of <hi>Loeſtoffe,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Honour I had once to be Yours, gives me the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to
affix your Graces Name before this Book, made <pb facs="tcp:62420:3"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> in
your Service, at thoſe vacant hours I could borrow from the Function of my
Employment: It is a Romance, but ſo like a True Story, that your Grace may
reap by it the uſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of a true Hiſtory. It was a good
<hi>Tale</hi> in <hi>Monſieur Segrays</hi> dreſs, therefore I muſt humbly
beg your Graces par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <pb facs="tcp:62420:3"/>if I have ſpoil'd it in the Telling.</p>
            <p>The ſcope of it, is chiefly to ſhew the deformity of
Treachery, Ingratitude, the Folly and Miſchiefs of ill-grounded Jealouſies;
as alſo to puniſh Vice, and reward Vertue, though Vertue be 
<q>
                  <l>—Pulcherrima merces</l>
                  <l>ipſa ſibi—</l>
               </q> 
               <pb facs="tcp:62420:4"/>Yet if not cultivated
and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, it may be truly ſaid of her, as in this our Age is made out; 
<q>
                  <l>—Virtus Laudatur &amp; alget.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But if we may ground our Conjectures upon thoſe early Rayes of
hopeful <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> which breaks forth like a glorious Morn from your
tender Years, we may with <pb facs="tcp:62420:4"/>Aſſurance promiſe the World that
You will not ſtarve her.</p>
            <p>And that the Riches and Beauty of your Mind, will in time
out-ſhine that of your Body; in which, although the Majeſty of your
<hi>Great Sire,</hi> and the lovely features of your <hi>Mother,</hi> at once
daſle and ſurprize the eyes and the <pb facs="tcp:62420:5"/>hearts of all that ſee
you; yet the clearneſs of your Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, the quickneſs of your
Apprehenſion, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of your Memory, your Gracefulneſs and Manly
car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in performing all your <hi>Exerciſes,</hi> your Solidity in
Reaſoning, well-grounded aſſurance in Diſcourſing, even with the
greateſt and moſt <pb facs="tcp:62420:5"/>Learned men, may confirm us in our moſt
aſſured Hope (that if the Almighty be graciouſly pleaſed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
your Life) you will out-doe our juſt expectations of <hi>You.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that when you are called by the Prerogative of your Blood, to
publick <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments,</hi> you will embrace <pb facs="tcp:62420:6"/>them, not as
priſes of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Oppreſſion, Injustice,</hi> and
<hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> but as your proper Sphere wherein you will move,
moſt uſefully for the Service of <hi>God,</hi> the ſafety and honour of
your <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> nouriſhing <hi>Arts</hi> and
<hi>Vertue</hi> whereſoever you find them:</p>
            <p>And that when all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions <pb facs="tcp:62420:6"/>of the publick are at a
ſtand, you will be able moſt profitably to actuate upon your ſelf, as the
propereſt object of your Induſtry, <hi>God</hi> having made you ſo rich a
Soil, that you will be ſtill improvable, and rather chuſe to beſtow your
time in Cultivating the rich mines of your <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Princely
Soul</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:62420:7"/>(of which you give daily moſt clear demonſtrations to
all thoſe that have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Converſe with you) than to ſuffer your
ſelf to be carryed away by the ill managery of others, or by the example or
imitation of ſuch who Miſpend their times in evil <hi>Converſation</hi>
and worſe <hi>Manners,</hi> and that you will <pb facs="tcp:62420:7"/>not let ſo
hopeful a Field produce a degenerate Crop; having this Maxim ſtill in mind,
That 'tis <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue</hi> alone that can make you powerful and happy, and
that nothing but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice,</hi> and the practiſe thereof can debaſe what
was intended ſo <hi>Great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I therefore moſt humbly beſeech your Grace to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don 
<pb facs="tcp:62420:8"/>this my boldneſs, and to accept this ſmall Oblation of this
<hi>Firſt Part</hi> of <hi>Zayd,</hi> with that goodneſs which is ſo
na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to you, from one, whoſe chiefeſt Ambition has been (ſince he had
the honour to know and ſerve your Grace) to approve himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Graces moſt Obedient, and moſt Faithful Humble
Servant <hi>P. Porter.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62420:8"/>
            <head>Spaniſh Hiſtory. A NOVELL. Written in <hi>FRENCH</hi> by
<hi>MO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NSIER SEGRAIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>FIRST PART.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>PAIN</hi> began to Free it ſelf from the Dominion of the
<hi>Moors;</hi> its People, who had Retired into the <hi>Aſturies,</hi> had
laid the Foundation of the Kingdom of <hi>Leon:</hi> Thoſe who had withdrawn
themſelves into the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renean</hi> Mountains, begun the Kingdom of
<hi>Navarr.</hi> There were that raiſed themſelves to be Counts of
<hi>Barcelona,</hi> and <hi>Arragon;</hi> ſo that in a Hundred and Fifty
Years after the Invaſion of the <hi>Moors,</hi> more than half <hi>Spain</hi>
found it ſelf delivered from their Tyranny.</p>
               <p>Amongſt all the Chriſtian Princes that <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62420:9"/>then Reigned there, there was none more powerful than
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> King of <hi>Leon,</hi> Sur-named <hi>The Great:</hi> His
Predeceſſors had joyned <hi>Caſtile</hi> to their Kingdom: At firſt,
this Province was Commanded by Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, who, in proceſs of Time, had made
their Governments Hereditary; and People begun to apprehend, that they would
ſet up for the Soveraignty: They were called Counts of <hi>Caſtile;</hi>
whereof the moſt powerful were <hi>Diego Porcellos,</hi> and <hi>Nugnes
Fernando;</hi> this laſt was conſiderable for the vaſt Extent of his
Territories, and the Greatneſs of his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: And his Children were
inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental for the Preſervation not only of his Fortune, but enlarging
of its Bounds: He had a Son and a Daughter of extraordinary Beauty; His Son,
whoſe Name was <hi>Gonſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luo,</hi> whom nothing in all <hi>Spain</hi> might
equal; his Perſon and Wit had ſomething in them ſo admirable, that it
ſeem'd Heaven had made him differ from the reſt of Man-kind.</p>
               <p>Some important Reaſons had obliged him to quit the Court of
<hi>Leon;</hi> and the ſenſible Diſpleaſures he had there received,
induced him to the Deſigne of leaving <hi>Spain,</hi> and to retire into
ſome ſolitary Place. He came into the remoteſt Parts of
<hi>Catalonia,</hi> with intention to ſhip himſelf in the firſt
Veſſel he ſhould find bound for any of the <hi>Grecian</hi> 
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62420:9"/>Ilands: The careleſs Diſpoſition he was in, made him
often neglect the Roads he had been ſhewn; ſo that, inſtead of
paſſing the River <hi>Elbe</hi> at <hi>Tortoſe,</hi> as he had been
direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he followed the Courſe of the River al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to the Place where
it diſembogues it ſelf into the Sea; there he perceived he had loſt his
Way: He inquires if there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Barque there? 'Twas told him, That in
that Place, there would be none to be found; but that, if he pleaſed to go to
a little Port not far off, he might find ſome that would carry him to
<hi>Tarragone;</hi> He goes to this Port, lights off his Horſe, and asked of
ſome Fiſher-men he met with, If there were not any Shallop ready to put to
Sea?</p>
               <p>As he was talking to them, A Man, that was walking penſively
by the Shore-ſide, being ſurprized with his Beauty and good Meine, ſtood
ſtill to conſider him; and, having over-heard what he asked of thoſe
Fiſher-men, he made Anſwer, That all the Barques were ſayled for
<hi>Tarragon,</hi> and that they would not return untill the next Day; and that
he could not Embarque until the next Day after. <hi>Gonſaluo,</hi> who at
firſt did not perceive him, turning his Head towards that Voyce, was as much
ſurprized with the good Aſpect of this unknown Man, as the Stranger had
been with his. He ſaw in him <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62420:10"/>ſomething of Great and
Noble, and full of Handſomneſs; though he might eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that he
was paſſed the Prime of his Youth. Though <hi>Gonſaluo's</hi> Mind was
filled more with his own Thoughts than any thing elſe; yet, the ſight of
this Stranger in ſuch a forlorne Place, gave him ſome Attention: He thanked
him for giving him Information of what he deſired to know; and then aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
the Fiſher-men, If there were no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency in the Neighbourhood, where he
might Lodge that Night? There is no other but theſe Hutts you ſee (Replyed
the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,) where you cannot have any conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Entertainment.
Nevertheleſs (ſayes <hi>Gonſaluo</hi>) I muſt go thither to ſeek
ſome Reſt; for, I have travelled ſome Dayes without any; and I find my
Body has need of more, than my troubled Thoughts will allow it. The Stranger
was touched with the ſad manner of his pronouncing theſe Words; and was now
convinced, that it was ſome unfortunate Man. The Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity that ſeemed to
be in their Fortunes, gave him that kind of Inclination for
<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaluo,</hi> which we uſe to have for Perſons, whoſe
Diſpoſitions we believe to be like ours.</p>
               <p>You will not find here (ſayes the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) any Place worthy
of your Retreat; <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62420:10"/>but, if you pleaſe to accept of one that
I offer you hard by here, you will be Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there more commodiouſly, than
in theſe Cabanes. <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> had ſuch an Averſion for the
Society of Men, that he preſently refuſed the offer which the Stranger made
him; but at laſt, being over-come with his Importunities, and his great need
of taking ſome Reſt, he was forced to accept of it.</p>
               <p>He therefore followes him; and, after walking a little while, he
diſcovers a Houſe, ſome-what low, built with no great Coſt; yet Neat
and Regular. The Court was ſhut in only with a Row of Pomgranat Trees, and
the Garden was fenced with the like, which was ſeparated from a high Wood by
a ſmall Brook: If <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> had been capable of taking any Delight,
the agreeable Scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Dwelling, might have given him ſome
Pleaſure. He asked the Stranger, If this Place were his conſtant Abode, and
whether Chance, or his own Choyce, had led him thither? I have lived here this
four or five Years (Replyed the Stranger;) I never ſtir out but only to walk
upon the Sea-Shore; and, I can aſſure you, that ſince I have taken up my
Habitation here, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw any Rational Man in this Place, but your
ſelf: Foul Weather often caſts away Veſſels upon this Coaſt, which is
dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62420:11"/>enough: I have ſaved the Lives of ſome poor
Wretches, whom I have enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained here: But all thoſe whoſe ill For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
brought hither, were Strangers; with whom I could have no Converſation,
though I had ſought for it. You may judge by the Place of my Abode, that I
look for none; yet I muſt confeſs, I am much pleaſed to ſee a Man like
your ſelf.</p>
               <p>For my part (ſayes <hi>Gonſaluo</hi>) I ſhunn all Men; and
I have ſuch juſt Reaſons to ſhun them, that, if you knew them, you
would not think it ſtrange, that I accepted with ſo much Reluctancy, the
offer which you made me: To the contrary, you would judge, after the
Misfortunes which they have created me, that I ought for ever to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all
Humane Society. If the cauſe of your Complaint proceeds only from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men
(ſayes the Stranger,) and that you have nothing where-with to reproach your
ſelf; there are others more unhappy than you, and you are leſs unfortunate
than you imagine your ſelf to be. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of Misfortunes (cryes he)
is to have reaſon to complain of ones ſelf; This is to dig a Pit for ones
ſelf to be drowned in: This is to be unjuſt, unreaſonable: This is to
have been the Source of ones own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries. I perceive (anſwered
<hi>Gonſaluo</hi>) that <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62420:11"/>you have a ſenſible Feeling of
what you ſpeak; But, How different are they from thoſe we feel, when
without deſerving it, we are deceived, betrayed, and abandoned by all that
was moſt dear to us. Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as I can perceive (ſayes the Stranger)
you forſake your Country, to flye ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have betrayed you,
and are the cauſe of your Diſcontent: But, judgewhat torment it would be to
you, to be obliged alwayes to keep Company with thoſe that create the
Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of your Life; Believe it, this is my Condition: I have made my
own Life unhappy; and yet, I cannot ſeparate from my ſelf, for whom I have
ſo much Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and ſo juſt a cauſe of Hatred; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my own
particular Sufferings; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, for the Misfortunes of thoſe I loved
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things in this World.</p>
               <p>I ſhould never complain (ſayes <hi>Gonſaluo</hi>) if I had
none to complain of but my ſelf: You think your ſelf unhappy, becauſe you
have reaſon to hate your ſelf; but, if you had been anſwered with an
equal Flame, by the Perſon you adored, Would not you believe your ſelf
happy? You have, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, loſt her by your own Fault; but ſtill you have
the ſatisfaction, to think, that ſhe loved you; and would do ſo ſtill,
if you had not done ſomething that might have <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62420:12"/>diſpleaſed her: You are not acquainted with Love, if this Thought
alone be not capable of keeping you from believing your ſelf unhappy; and you
love your ſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than your Miſtreſs, if you had rather have cauſe
to complain of her, than of your ſelf. Doubtleſs, the little ſhare you
have in your own Misfortunes (ſayes the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) hinders you from
comprehending how great an Addition of Grief it would have been to you, to have
contributed to them; But believe it, by the Experience I have of it, that to
loſe what we love by our own Fault, is a kind of Affliction, which makes more
ſenſible Impreſſions upon us, than any other what-ever.</p>
               <p>As they made an end of theſe Words, they came into the
Houſe, which <hi>Gonſaluo,</hi> found as pritty within, as it appeared
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. He paſſed the Night with much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet; in the Morning, a
Feavour ſeized him; and, in the following Dayes it grew ſo violent, that
his Life was thought in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The Stranger was ſenſibly afflicted, and
his Affliction encreaſed by the pitty and admiration, all
<hi>Gonſaluo's</hi> Actions and his Words cauſed in him: He conceived an
earneſt deſire to know who this Man ſhould be, that appeared ſo
extraordinary to him: He asked ſeveral Queſtions of him, that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62420:12"/>him; But the Servants Ignorance of his Maſter's Name and
Quality, could not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his Curioſity: He only told him, That he
cauſed himſelf to be called <hi>Theodoric,</hi> and that he believed, that
was not his right Name. At laſt, after his Feaver had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſeveral
Dayes, the Remedies, and his Youth, drew <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> out of danger. The
Stranger ſtrove to divert him from thoſe ſad Thoughts, with which he
ſaw him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed: He ſtaid alwayes by him; and though they ſpoke but of
indifferent Things, becauſe they were not yet acquainted; yet, they
ſurprized one another by the greatneſs of their Witt.</p>
               <p>This Stranger had concealed his Name and Quality, during his
Reſidence in this ſolitary Retreat; but he was very willing
<hi>Gonſaluo</hi> ſhould know it: He told him, He was of the Kingdom of
<hi>Navarr,</hi> that his Name was <hi>Alphonſo Xymenes;</hi> and that his
bad Fortune had obliged him to find out a Retreat, where he might with more
Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, regret what he had loſt. <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> was ſurprized at
the Name of <hi>Xymenes,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be one of the moſt Illuſtrious
Names of <hi>Navarr;</hi> and was highly ſenſible of the Confidence
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> ſhewed him. What Reaſons ſoever he had to hate all
Men, he could not keep himſelf from having a Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62420:13"/>for him, beyond what he believed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf any more
capable of.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> begun to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his
Strength; and when he found himſelf pretty well to Embarque, he found he
could not leave <hi>Alphonſo</hi> without Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; he acquaints him with
their ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the deſign he had to ſeek out ſome ſolitude;
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> was much afflicted at it: He had ſo uſed himſelf to
the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Converſation, that he could not
think of the loſs of it without grief; he told him he was not yet in a
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to depart, and endeavoured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him not to look for any
other ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude then that whither chance had conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him.</p>
               <p>I dare not hope, ſayes he, to make this abode leſs tedious
to you, but me thinks that in a retreat ſo far diſtant, as that you look
for, there is ſome ſatisfaction not to be altogether alone: My misfortunes
were not capable of receiving any comfort; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, notwithſtanding I
ſhould find ſome Conſolation, if at certain times I could have ſome
body to whom I might make my moan; you ſhall find here the ſame ſolitude
you are going to look for elſe-where, and you will have the conveniency to
ſpeak when you pleaſe, to a Perſon that has an extraordinary 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62420:13"/>eſteem for your merit, and a feeling ſence of your
misfortunes, equal to that he has of his own.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s diſcourſe did not preſently
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> but by degrees it began to work upon his
reaſon, and the conſideration of a receſs remote from all Company,
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the friendſhip he had already for him, made him reſolve to
ſtay in that Houſe; the only thing that gave him trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, was his
apprehenſion of being known. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> re-aſſures him by his
own exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and tells him, that this place was ſo far diſtant from all
commerce, that for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years paſt that he had lived there, he had
never ſeen any that could know him. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> yielded to his
reaſons, and after having ſaid to one another all the obliging things that
the beſt-bred men in the World, who reſolve to live together, could ſay,
he ſent a parcel of his Jewels to a Merchant at <hi>Tarragon,</hi> who was to
return him for them, all ſuch neceſſaries as he had occaſion for. Thus
you ſee <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> eſtabliſhed in this ſolitude, whence he
reſolves never to depart: Here he is giving himſelf up to the ſad
contemplation of his misfortunes, where the only Conſolation he finds, is,
his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, that here he is at Covert from all that Malice can contrive; but
Fortune made it <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62420:14"/>appear, that ſhe can reach even in the
moſt wilde Deſerts, thoſe ſhe has reſolved to perſecute.</p>
               <p>About the latter end of <hi>Autumn,</hi> when the winds begin to
grow formidable at Sea, he went out to walk earlier than uſual, there was a
terrible Storm the night before, and the Sea that was yet agitated, gave his
ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fancy a pleaſant diverſion; he for a time conſidered the
inconſtancy of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, with the ſame reflexions he uſed to make
upon his own condition. After this, coming nearer to the Strand, he ſaw
ſeveral pieces of the Wracks of a Shallop, and caſting his eyes about, to
ſee if he could find no man that might yet want his help, he ſaw
ſomething glittering in the Sun newly riſing, that he could not preſently
diſtinguiſh what it might be, which gave him the curioſity to look a
little nearer, and coming to it, he found it was a Woman richly attired, lying
all her length upon the Sand, as if the Sea had thrown her up there; ſhe lay
ſo, that he could not ſee her face: He raiſed her up to ſee if ſhe
had any life left in her; but how great was his aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when he
perceived, even through the horrors of death, the greateſt Beauty his eyes
had ever beheld; this Beauty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed his compaſſion, and made him
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62420:14"/>that ſhe might yet be in a condition to receive
ſome relief at his hands. At that very time <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> who by
accident had followed that way, came to him, and put his helping hand to
ſuccour her; their pains were not in vain, for they found ſhe was not yet
dead, but they judged ſhe had need of more powerful aſſiſtance then
they could give her in that place; therefore, being not far off from the
Houſe, they reſolved to carry her thither: As ſoon as they had brought
her thither, <hi>Alphonſo</hi> ſent for ſome Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and Women to
aſſiſt her: As ſoon as theſe Women laid her in her Bed,
<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> came again into her Chamber, and began to contemplate this
unknown with more attention than before; he was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with the
lineaments of her Face, and the ſweetneſs of her Countenance; he view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with aſtoniſhment the delicateneſs of her Mouth, the whiteneſs of her
Neck; and he was ſo charmed with what he ſaw of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in this
Stranger, that he was ready to fancy that ſhe was not a mortal; he paſſed
a great part of the night without being able to go from her:
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> adviſed him to go take ſome reſt, but he anſwered,
that he was ſo little uſed to find any, that he was glad of an occaſion
to be kept from looking for it in vain.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62420:15"/>
               <p>Towards break of Day, they perceived that this unknown Lady
began to come to her ſelf: She opened her Eyes; and, as the Light was at
firſt troubleſome to her ſight, ſhe turned it languiſhingly towards
<hi>Gonſaluo,</hi> and gave him to ſee a pair of large black Eyes; of a
Beauty ſo particular to themſelves, that it ſhould ſeem they were made
of purpoſe to dart at once, both Reſpect and Love. A little while aftter,
they found ſhe began to recover her Senſes, and to diſtinguiſh
Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: At the firſt, ſhe was amazed at thoſe ſhe ſaw.
<hi>Gonſaluo</hi> could not by Words, expreſs his Admiration for her: He
would make <hi>Alphonſo</hi> look, and conſider her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with that kind
of Earneſtneſs which we uſe to have for what ſurprizes and charms
us.</p>
               <p>But ſtill ſhe wanted the uſe of her Speech;
<hi>Gonſaluo</hi> judging, that ſhe might yet remain for ſometime in that
Condition, with-drawes himſelf into his own Chamber. He could not forbear
making Reflexions upon this Adventure. I wonder, ſaid he, that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
ſhould offer a Woman to my ſight, in the only State wherein I could not
avoid her; wherein, on the other ſide, Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion obliges me to take
care of her: I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven admired her Beauty; but, as ſoon as ſhe is Recovered,
I will not look upon her <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62420:15"/>Charms any other way, then as I
would upon a thing of which ſhe would make uſe of to betray more Hearts,
and make more Men wretched. Great Gods! How many will ſhe ruine? And how many
has ſhe already, perhaps, undone! What Eyes! What Looks! How I pitty thoſe
that can be inflamed by them? And, How happy am I in my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs, who by
the cruel Experience I have had of Women, that I am ſufficiently fortified
againſt all their Charms? After theſe words, he had ſome difficulty to
fall aſleep; and that was but ſhort too. He goes to ſee in what State the
unknown La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was: He found her much better; but ſhe had not yet recovered
the uſe of her Speech; and that Night, and the next Day paſſed, before
ſhe could pronounce one word. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> could not forbear ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<hi>Gonſaluo</hi> to underſtand, how much he admired his great care, and
concern, for this Woman: <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> himſelf, began to wonder at it
too; but he found it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to ſtay from this fair
Creature: He believed ſtill, that ſhe ſhould have ſome conſiderable
Change in her Diſtemper, to the worſe, when he was not with her. As he
ſtood by her, ſhe pronounced ſome Words; at which, he ſelt a
Gladneſs, and a Trouble: He came nearer to underſtand <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62420:16"/>what ſhe would ſay, while ſhe was yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and was
ſurprized, to hear her ſpeak a Language, that was unknown to him: He at
firſt perceived by her Habit, that ſhe was a Forreiner; But, as it had
ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance to that of the <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Women, and that they
ſpoke the <hi>Arabian</hi> Tongue, he made no doubt, but to be able to make
himſelf to be underſtood: He ſpoke to her in that Language; and was yet
more ſurprized, to ſee ſhe did not underſtand it: He ſpoke
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> to her; but in vain: He judged by her
attentive and troubled Aire, that ſhe did not comprehend him any better: Yet
ſhe continued talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and would ſtop now and then, as if ſhe expected
to be Anſwered. <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> hearkened to all her Words, thinking that
he might underſtand ſomething of her Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. He cauſed all that would,
to come nearer to her, to find if none could under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what ſhe ſaid:
He brought a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Book, to ſee if ſhe could read that
Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; he found that ſhe knew the Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but could not underſtand
the Language. She was ſad and unquiet; and her Sadneſs added to
<hi>Gonſaluo</hi>'s Melancholly.</p>
               <p>They were in this Poſture, when <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi> came into
the Room, leading a very fair Perſon, dreſſed in the ſame kind of
Habit, <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62420:16"/>which the unknown Lady wore: As ſoon as they ſaw
one another, they embraced with great Demonſtrations of Kindneſs; ſhe
that <hi>Alphonſo</hi> brought in, pronounced very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the name of
<hi>Zayde,</hi> which gave them to underſtand that, that was the name of the
unknown Lady; and <hi>Zayde</hi> pronounced as often the name of
<hi>Felime,</hi> by which they found that to be the name of that La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that
came in laſt. After they had for ſome time diſcourſed together,
<hi>Zayde</hi> fell a weeping with all the marks of a great affliction, and
made ſignes with her hand they ſhould all go out. After they had left the
room, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> went along with <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo</hi> to be informed
where he found that other Stranger; <hi>Alphonſo</hi> told him that the
Fiſher-men of their Neighbouring Cabbins had found her the ſame day in the
like condition as he had found her Companion; they will have ſome
ſatisfaction, ſaid <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo,</hi> to be together: But
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> what think you of theſe two Ladys? if we gueſs by
their Garbe, they are of a rank above the Vulgar: But how came they to expoſe
themſelves to the hazards of the Sea in ſuch ſmall Veſſels, for it
was no great Ship they were caſt away in? She you led to <hi>Zayde,</hi> has
told her ſome News that afflicts her much; in fine, there muſt be
ſomething of <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62420:17"/>extraordinary in their fates; I believe
ſo, ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I am equally ſurprized with their adventure
and beauty: You have not perhaps obſerved that of <hi>Felime,</hi> it is
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, and you had happily been ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with it if you had not
ſeen <hi>Zayde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this diſcourſe, they ſeparate, <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi>
ſound himſelf more afflicted than uſual, and felt that the cauſe of his
ſadneſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from his not being able to make himſelf to be
underſtood by this Stranger; but ſayes to himſelf, what have I to ſay
to her? or what is it that I would know from her? Is it out of a deſign to
inform her of my misfortunes, or a deſire to learn hers? Can any Curioſity
find place in a Man as wretched as I am? What intereſt can I take in the
ſad deſtiny of a perſon I know not? Why ſhould I grieve to ſee her
ſad? Is it the evil that I have ſuffered that inſtructs me to
commiſerate thoſe of others? No doubtleſs, it is this ſtill and
ſolitary retreat wherein I am, that gives me atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſuch
extraordinary adventures, which would not long take up my thoughts, if they bad
been diverted by any other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
               <p>In ſpight of this reflection, he paſſed all that night
without ſleep, and part of the day in much diſquiet, becauſe he could not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62420:17"/>ſee <hi>Zayde.</hi> Toward the Evening, they brought him
word that ſhe was up, and gone toward the Sea-ſide; he followes her, and
finds her ſitting upon the Shore with her eyes all drowned in tears: When he
came near her, ſhe roſe and advanced to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him with much civility and
ſweetneſs; he was ſurpriſed, to find as many charmes in her Stature and
Deportment, as he had before obſerved in her Countenance: She pointed to a
little Barque ſhe ſaw upon the Sea, and named <hi>Tunis</hi> ſeveral
times, as if ſhe meant to inſinuate her deſires, to be tranſported
thither: He made ſignes to her, ſhewing her the Moon, that ſhe ſhould
be obeyed when that Planet (which then did ſhine out) had twice finiſhed
her courſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Univerſe. She ſeemed to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what he ſaid,
and then gave her ſelf up again to her tears.</p>
               <p>The next day ſhe was ill, and was not to be ſeen: He had not
felt a day ſince his Abode in this ſolitude, longer, nor more tedious to
him than this.</p>
               <p>The next day (without knowing himſelf why) he left off that
negligent dreſs which he had put on ever ſince his coming to that place;
and as he was one of the Men of the World, the beſt ſhap'd, an ordinary
plain dreſs ſet him forth more to the advantage, <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62420:18"/>than
rich and magnificent Cloaths would do others. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> met him in
the Wood, and was aſtoniſhed to find him in ſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent a garbe from
what he uſed to wear; he could not refrain ſmiling, and telling him, that
he was glad to find by his Habit, that his afflictions begun to grow leſs,
and that he found in theſe Deſaits ſome eaſe to his grief.</p>
               <p>I underſtand you <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> replied
<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo;</hi> you believe that the ſight of <hi>Zayde</hi> is that
comfort I find to my Misfortunes, but you are miſtaken; I have only for
<hi>Zayde,</hi> that compaſſion which is due to her Diſaſters, and her
Beauty: I have alſo a compaſſion for you and her, replied
<hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo;</hi> I pitty her, and would be glad to be able to comfort her;
but I am not ſo aſſiduous about her, I am not ſo obſervant of her; I
am not ſo much concerned that I do not underſtand her; I have not ſo much
mind to ſpeak to her; I have been no more afflicted yeſterday than I uſed
to be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was not to be ſeen; and I am not to day leſs
negligent in my dreſs then I have accuſtomed to be: In fine, ſince I am
as ſuſceptible of compaſſion as you are, and yet that there is ſo
much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us; it followes, that you muſt aile ſomething more
than I do.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62420:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> did not interrupt <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> but
ſeemed to examine himſelf upon theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, to find whether they
were true or no. As he was upon the point of return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Anſwer, one came
to tell him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the directions he gave, that <hi>Zayde</hi> was gone
out of her Chamber, and ſhe was walking towards the Sea-ſide; then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
conſidering that he was going to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s ſuſpicion
of him, he leaves him to go after <hi>Zayde:</hi> He ſaw her at a diſtance,
ſitting by <hi>Felime,</hi> in the ſame place where he found her two days
before; he had a particular curioſity to obſerve their actions, hoping
thereby to dive into the knowledge of their Fortunes: He obſerved that
<hi>Zayde</hi> wept, and <hi>Felime</hi> ſeemed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to comfort her;
that <hi>Zayde</hi> did not hearken to her, but looked ſtill towards the Sea,
with ſuch jeſtures, as made <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> imagine that ſhe lamented
for ſome body that might have been caſt away with her: he had formerly
found her weeping in that place; but as ſhe had done nothing that might
inſtruct him in the cauſe of her tears, he believed ſhe had only wept for
being ſo far diſtant from her Country; he then began to fancy, that thoſe
tears ſhe ſhed, were for the loſs of a Lover that might be drowned, and
that it was to follow him (perhaps) that <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62420:19"/>ſhe had
expoſed her ſelf to the dangers of the Sea. Laſtly, He fancied to know,
as ſure as if ſhe had told him, that Love was the cauſe of her tears.</p>
               <p>It is not to be expreſt what <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s thoughts
produced in his mind, and the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble which Jealouſie cauſed in a Heart
where Love had not yet declared it ſelf: He had been in Love formerly, but
had never been Jealous; this paſſion (that till then) had been unknown to
him, made him feel its firſt effects with ſo much violence, that he
believed himſelf ſtruck with a grief that no other man ever had felt or
known but himſelf. He paſſed (as he thought) through all the misfortunes
that attended Man's life, and yet now he feels ſomething more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable
than any thing he had ever indured before. He has no freedom of reaſon left,
he leaves the place where he ſtood to come nearer to <hi>Zayde,</hi> with
reſolution to ask her the cauſe of her affection; and though he was
aſſured ſhe could not Anſwer him, yet he forbears not to ask her. She
was far from comprehending what he would ſay; ſhe wipes away her tears, and
walks along with him: The pleaſure of ſeeing her, and being ſeen by her
fair eyes, did calme the agitation wherein he was; he perceived the diſorder
he was in, and ſettled his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62420:19"/>the beſt he
could. She named <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> again very often to him, and ſhew'd a great
deſire to be tranſported thither; he underſtood but too well what ſhe
demanded of him; the thought of ſeeing her depart, began already to give him
moſt ſenſible ſtrokes of grief, and it was only by the pains which Love
creates, that he perceives he is in Love, and his jealouſie and fear of her
abſence, torments him before he knows that he is fallen in Love: He would
believe that ſhe ſhould have juſt cauſe to complain of his ill Fate, if
he did but find in himſelf an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to Love; but to find himſelf at
one and the ſame time, not only in Love, but Jealous, neither to
underſtand, nor be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by her he Loved, to know nothing of her but
her Beauty, to have a proſpect of nothing elſe but of an eternal abſence,
were ſo many evils together, that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to reſiſt
them.</p>
               <p>While he made theſe ſad reflexions, <hi>Zayde</hi> continued
walking with <hi>Felime;</hi> and after, having walked a pretty while, ſhe
went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to ſit down upon the Beach, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to weep a freſh, looking
upon the Sea, and ſhewing it to <hi>Felime,</hi> as if ſhe accuſed it of
the misfortune which made her ſhed ſo many tears. <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to
divert her, ſhewed her ſome Fiſher-men which were not <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62420:20"/>far off. In ſpight of the affliction and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this new Lover,
the ſight of her he loved, gave him a ſatisfaction and joy which reſtored
him to his former Beauty; and as he was leſs careleſs of himſelf than he
uſed to be, he might deſervedly draw upon him the looks and eyes of all the
World. <hi>Zayde</hi> began to look upon him firſt with attention, then with
aſtoniſhment; and after having a good while conſidered him, ſhe turns
to her Companion, and made her obſerve, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſaying
ſomething to her. <hi>Felime</hi> looked upon him, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered her with
an action that ſhew'd ſhe approved of what <hi>Zayde</hi> ſaid to her:
<hi>Zayde</hi> eyed him again, and ſpoke ſomething to <hi>Felime;
Felime</hi> did the like; in fine, by this manner of theirs,
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> judged that he might reſemble ſome body they knew:
this, though at firſt made no impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, but found
<hi>Zayde</hi> ſo taken up with this reſemblance, that it was apparent to
him, that amidſt all her ſadneſs, ſhe took ſome content to look upon
him, that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that he was like that Lover whom ſhe
lamented.</p>
               <p>All the remainder of that Day, <hi>Zayde</hi> ſhewed divers
ſignes, that confirmed this his Suſpicion: Towards Night, <hi>Felime</hi>
and ſhe, went to ſearch amongſt the Remaines <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62420:20"/>of their
Loſs; and they looked ſo diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> obſerved
ſuch Marks of Dis-ſatisfaction in them, when they could not find what they
ſought after, that he had new Cauſes of Diſquiet. <hi>Alphonſo</hi>
took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Diſ-order he was in; and, after he had Conducted
<hi>Zayde</hi> to her Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſtaid in <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s
Chamber.</p>
               <p>You have not yet told me, ſaid he, all your paſt
Misfortunes; but, you muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thoſe that <hi>Zayde</hi> begins to
bring upon you: A Man ſo deep in Love as you ſeem to me, alwayes takes
Delight to ſpeak of his Love; and though your Evil be great, yet, perhaps, my
Help, and my Counſel, may not be unſerviceable to you. Ah my dear
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> (cryed <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) How unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py am I! How great is
my Frailty? and, How unſupportable is my Deſpair! How wiſe were you, that
could ſee <hi>Zayde,</hi> and not be in Love with her? I well perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
(Replyed <hi>Alphonſo</hi>) that you were in Love with her, though you would
not own it. I knew it not my ſelf (anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo:</hi>) It is
Jealouſie alone, that made me ſenſible I was engaged in Affection.
<hi>Zayde</hi> laments ſome loſt Lover; which makes her every Day return to
the Beach, to bemoan her Love, in the ſame Place ſhe believes he was caſt
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. It is true, I am in love with <hi>Zayde;</hi> 
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62420:21"/>and
<hi>Zayde</hi> is Enamoured of ſome other: This, of all my Misfortunes
ſeems the moſt terrible to me; which I believed my ſelf moſt free from.
I did flatter my ſelf, that, perhaps, her Grief was for no Lover; but I find
her Affliction too great, to doubt of it. I am more-over perſwaded, that what
ſhe ſo carefully looked for, was ſome thing that might come from that
happy Lover: And, what ſeems to me more Cruel than all I have told, is, That
I reſemble him for whom ſhe burns: She perceived it as we were walking: I
ſaw Joy in her Eyes, when ſhe ſaw any thing that might make her remember
him; ſhe ſhewed me twenty times to <hi>Felime,</hi> and made her take
particular Notice of all my Features. What ſhall I ſay more? She looked
upon me all the Day long; But, it was not I ſhe ſaw, nor of whom ſhe
thinks: When ſhe caſts her Eyes upon me, I put her in mind of what I would
fain have her to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get: I am, likewiſe, deprived of the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of
ſeeing her fair Eyes glancing upon me; and ſhe can no longer behold me,
without tormenting my Heart with Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſpoke all this ſo faſt, that
<hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo</hi> could not interrupt him; but he gave over ſpeaking. Is
it poſſible, ſaid he, that what you tell me, can be true; and that 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62420:21"/>the Affliction to which you have uſed your ſelf, does
not repreſent to you this <hi>Idea</hi> of ſo extraordinary a Calamity? No
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I am not deceived (ſaid <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi>)
<hi>Zayde</hi> laments a Perſon ſhe loves, and I put her in mind of him. My
Fortune will not let me fancy to my ſelf Evils beyond thoſe ſhe heaped
upon me. She out-runs what-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I could imagine: She finds our thoſe
Afflictions for me, that are unknown to the reſt of Mankind: And, if I had
told you the whole courſe of my Life, you would be obliged to acknowledge,
that I had Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to maintain, That I was more unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate than you. I dare
not tell you (ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>) that if you had not ſome
impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Reaſon to conceal your ſelf from me, you would give me all the
Joy imaginable, in acquainting me with what you are; and what thoſe
Misfortunes are, which you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be greater than mine. I know, it is not
juſt to ask you, What I do; without telling you likewiſe, what my
Misfortunes are. But, pardon an unlucky Man, who has not concealed from you
neither his Name nor Birth; nor would hide from you his Adventures, if it would
avail you to know them; or if it were in his Power to declare them, without
renewing Afflictions, which <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62420:22"/>many Years begin now with
difficulty, to blot out of his Memory.</p>
               <p>I will never preſs you (ſayes <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) to any
thing that may give you trouble; but, I muſt blame my ſelf, for not telling
you who I am; Although I had taken a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, never to diſcover my
ſelf to any Body, the extraordinary Merit I find in you, and the Gratitude I
owe you for your Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and your Care of me, obliges me to tell you that
my true Name is <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi> and, that I am the Son of <hi>Nugnes
Fernan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> Count of <hi>Caſtile;</hi> whoſe Reputation, undoubtedly,
has reached your Ear. Can it poſſible be (cryes <hi>Alphonſo</hi>) that
you ſhould be that <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> that was ſo Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, even in his
firſt Campagne, by the Defeat of ſo many <hi>Moors,</hi> and by ſuch
glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Atchievements, as has made you to be admired by all <hi>Spain?</hi> I
know the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſo Noble a Life; and when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into this
Deſert, I had already learnt, not without Aſtoniſhment, that in the
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Defeat, which the King of <hi>Leon</hi> gave <hi>Ayda,</hi> the
braveſt Captain the <hi>Moors</hi> had, you alone turned the Scale of that
Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the Chriſtians ſide: And that in mounting the firſt Man, the
Breach of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora,</hi> you were the cauſe that Town was taken; which
obliged the <hi>Moors</hi> to beg a <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62420:22"/>Peace. The Solitude in
which I have ſince that time lived, kept me ignorant of the Sequel of ſuch
Heroick and Glorious Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings; but I queſtion not, but that they agree in
all Parts. I did not believe (Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) that my Name was
known to you; and I eſteem it a Happineſs, that you are ſo
prepoſſeſſed to my Advantage, by a Reputation I have not perhaps
deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> then ſetled himſelf, with At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to
hear; and <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> begun thus:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>THE Hiſtory of <hi>GONSAL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>O.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY Father was the moſt conſiderable Man in the Court of
<hi>Leon,</hi> when he made me appear there with an Equipage ſuitable to his
Quality. My Inchnation, my Age, and my Duty, fixed me near the Prince <hi>Don
Garcia,</hi> the Kings Eldeſt Son: This Prince is Young, Handſome, and
Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious; and his good Qualities are far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than his Defects; And it
may truly be ſaid, That he has none, but what his Paſſions prompts him
to: I was ſo happy, as to be very well with him, though I did not deſerve
it: And, I did endeavour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62420:23"/>to become worthy of
his Favour, by my Services and Fidelity to him. It was my good Fortune, to be
near enough to his Perſon, in the firſt Warrs, to reſcue him out of an
eminent Danger, to which his too raſh Valour had expoſed him: This Service
added to the Kindneſs he had for me. He loved me more like a Brother, than a
Subject: He concealed nothing from me; He denyed me nothing: And, he let all
the World ſee, that to gain his Love, they muſt be beloved by
<hi>Gonſalvo:</hi> A Favour ſo great, joyned to the conſiderable Rank in
which my Father ſtood, raiſed our Houſe to ſo high a pitch, that it
began to give the King umbrage, and apprehenſion that it ſhould grow too
Great.</p>
               <p>Amongſt an infinite number of young People, that the hope of
making their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, had made my Fellows; I had a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Eſteem for
<hi>Don Ramires</hi> above all the reſt: He was one of the moſt
conſiderable of all the Court; but he was much inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or in Fortune, to me:
It was in my Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to raiſe him equal to my ſelf: I employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at all
times, both my Father's Credit, and my own, to his Advancement: I uſed all my
endeavours, to obtain him as great a ſhare as I could, in the Princes Favour:
And he of his ſide, contributed very much, by his <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62420:23"/>ſweet
and inſinuating Behaviour, to ſecond my Endeavours; inſomuch, that next
to me, he was the Man of all the Court, that <hi>Don Garcias</hi> ſhewed the
moſt Kindneſs to. I made it my whole Delight, to improve their mutual
Kindneſs; and both the one, and the other, had already felt the Power of
Love: They often made themſelves merry with my Inſenſibility; and
reproached me, with my want of Inclination, as an unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Crime.</p>
               <p>I alſo Laughed at them, becauſe their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations were not
Real: You Love, ſaid I, that kind of Gallantry, which Cuſtom has
eſtabliſhed in <hi>Spain;</hi> but you do not Love your Miſtreſſes:
You ſhall never perſwade me, that you are in Love with a Perſon, whoſe
Face you ſcarce know; and whom you would not know again, if you met her any
where elſe, than at her Window, where you uſed to ſee her.</p>
               <p>You urge the ſmall Acquaintance we have with our
Miſtreſſes (ſaid the Prince;) but we acknowledge their Beauty, which,
in Love, is the Principal Verb: We judge of their Wit, firſt, by their
Phyſiognomy; and then, by their Letters: And, when we come to ſee them
nearer hand, we are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the Delight of diſcovering what we had not
yet found out. Every Word <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62420:24"/>that falls from them, has the
Charm of a Novelty: Their manner of Delivery is ſurprizing unto us; and our
Surprize awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens and increaſes Love: When thoſe that are acquainted with
their Miſtreſſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they become enamoured of them, are ſo
accuſtomed to their Beauty, and their Witt, that they are no more
ſenſible when they are beloved again. You will never fall into this
Misfortune, quoth I; But Sir, you ſhall have my conſent to love all you do
not know; provided, you give me liberty to love a Perſon, that I know ſo
well, as to believe ſhe deſerves my Eſteem; and may give me aſſurance
to find in her, what may make me Happy when I am beloved again: I ſay,
more-over, that I could wiſh ſhe were not prepoſſeſſed in Favour of
any other. And I (interrupted) <hi>Don Ramires,</hi> ſhould take more Delight
to conquer a Heart, that were defended by a Paſſion for another, than to
vanquiſh one that never before had been ingaged. I ſhould count this a
double Victory; and I ſhould be much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly perſwaded of the
true Inclination ſhe ſhould have for me, if I ſaw it begin in the
greateſt Heat and Paſſion ſhe might have for another. In ſine, It
would be an equal ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to my Glory, and my Love, to Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh a
Miſtreſs from a Rival. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> is ſo <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62420:24"/>oppoſite to your Opinion (ſaid the Prince); and judges it ſo
bad, that he thinks it not fit to Anſwer you: And truly, I am of his ſide
againſt you: But I am againſt his ſo particular Acquaintance with his
Miſtreſs: I ſhould never fall in Love with a Perſon, that I had been
uſed to ſee: And, if I am not ſurprized at firſt ſight, I can never
be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. I am of Opinion, That natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations do make their
Impreſſions at the very firſt Moment; and, that thoſe Paſſions that
grow with time, cannot be truly called Paſſions. Why then (ſaid I) it may
be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, that you will never Love that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which you have not loved
at firſt ſight: And Sir, (added I, Laughing) I muſt bring you my
Siſter, before ſhe is come to that Perfection of Beauty, to which, in all
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, ſhe is like to arrive, to accuſtom your ſelf to ſee her;
that ſo, you may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be concerned for her. You ſear then, I ſhould
have a Kindneſs for her, ſaid <hi>Don Garcias.</hi> Never doubt it Sir,
ſaid I; Nay, I ſhould think it the greateſt Misfortune that could happen
to me, if you ſhould. What Misfortune can you find in that, Replyed <hi>Don
Ramires?</hi> That, ſaid I, of not being able to joyne with the Sentiments of
the Prince; For, if he ſhould deſire to Marry my Siſter, I ſhould never
conſent to it, by <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62420:25"/>reaſon of the Intereſt of his
Greatneſs: And if he did not intend to Marry her, and ſhe ſhould
nevertheleſs Love him, as without doubt ſhe would, I ſhould have the
Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee my Siſter the Miſtreſs of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, whom I
could not hate, though I ought to do it. Let me ſee her I pray you
(inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the Prince) before ſhe can make me in Love with her; For, I
ſhould be ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, to have Sentiments that might diſpleaſe you,
that I am impatient to ſee her, that I may aſſure my ſelf, that I
ſhall never fall in Love with her. I can no longer wonder, Replyed <hi>Don
Ramires,</hi> (addreſſing himſelf to <hi>Don Garcias</hi>) that you have
not been in Love with all thoſe fair Ladies that are Bred in the Pallace, and
to whom you have been accuſtomed from your Infancy; But I muſt confeſs, I
have been ſurprized, that none of thoſe Beauties have had any Influence
upon you hitherto: And above all, <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Don
Diego Porcellos,</hi> that ſeems to me to be ſo likely to do it. It is true
(ſaid <hi>Don Garcias,</hi>) that <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> is very Lovely: Her
Eyes are infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taking; She has a pretty Mouth; and the Aire of her Face is
Noble and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: In fine, I ſhould have been enamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of her, had I not
been uſed to ſee her, even from the firſt Moment I begun to ſee. 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62420:25"/>But, why (added the Prince) were not you in Love with her,
<hi>Don Ramires,</hi> ſince you beleive her ſo amiable? Becauſe (Reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
he) ſhe never loved any Body elſe; I ſhould find no Rival to
diſpoſſeſs her Heart of: And I have told you, that is the only thing
that is able to Charm me: You muſt ask <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> Sir, why he was
not taken with her; For I am ſure, he thinks her Fair: She has no Tye upon
her; and he has known her now a great while. Who told you, ſaid I, (Smiling,
and Bluſhing withall) that I do not love her? I know not, Replyed <hi>Don
Ramires;</hi> but by your Bluſhes, I perceive, thoſe that told me were
deceived. Can it poſſible be, cryed the Prince to me, that you are in Love?
If you are, tell it me quickly, I pray; for, I am extream glad to ſee you
ſeized with a Paſſion; of which, you make ſo little ſhew.
Seriouſly, ſaid I, I am not in Love; but, to ſatisfie you, Sir, I own,
that I might be in Love with <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> if I were a little better
acquainted with her. If there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to obſtruct your Love, but
to be better acquainted with her, aſſure your ſelf, that you are already
ſmitten. I will never go without you to the Queen my Mother; and I will
Embroile my ſelf more often with the King; that the care which ſhe alwayes
takes <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62420:26"/>to make my Peace, may oblige her to ſend for me at
particular Hours: In fine, I will furniſh you with Opportunities enough, to
ſpeak to <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> that you may be throughly in Love with her:
You will find her very Lovely; and if her Heart be as well accompliſhed as
her Underſtanding, you will have little elſe to wiſh for in this World. I
beſeech you Sir, ſaid I, do not take ſo much Pains to make me unhappy:
And, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, let your Pretexts to viſit the Queen, be any other than your
embroiling your ſelf with the King: You well know how often he accuſes me,
for your Tranſgreſſions; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, that my Father and I, to make our
ſelves more conſiderable, do inſpire that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Authority into
you, which you take upon you ſometimes, to his Diſpleaſure. In the Humour
I am in, to make <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> in love with you, I ſhall not be ſo
cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect as you would have me: I will take all opportunities, to carry
you with me to the Queens Appartment: And though I have no particular
Buſineſs, I will go thither immediately; and will ſacrifice to the
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of making you in Love, a Night, which I intended to ſpend under
thoſe Windows; where, you believe, I know no Body.</p>
               <p>I would not trouble you with the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of this
Converſation, ſayes <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> 
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:62420:26"/>to
<hi>Alphonſo;</hi> but that you might ſee by the Sequel, that it was a kind
of a Preſage of what has ſince happened.</p>
               <p>The Prince goes to the Queens ſide; he found her with-drawn
from all other Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but the Ladies of her own Family; of which number,
<hi>Nugna Bella</hi> was one: She looked ſo well that Night, that it ſhould
ſeem, that Chance favoured the Prince's Deſignes. The Diſcourſe was
genreal for a time; as the Ladies enjoyed more Freedome than at other hours,
<hi>Nugna Bella</hi> ſpoke more than ſhe uſed; and I was ſurprized to
find her to have more Wit, than I obſerved in her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The Prince prayed
the Queen to go into her Cloſſet, without acquainting us what he had to
ſay to her: While ſhe was there, I ſtayed with <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> and
ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Perſons, without. I inſenſibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged her into a
particular Converſation; and, though it was only touching indifferent things,
there appeared in it, ſomething more Gallant, than uſes to be in the
ordinary Diſcourſes: We blamed altogether, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired manner of Living,
to which the Ladies in <hi>Spain</hi> are obliged to; as finding, by our own
Experience, that we are deprived of ſome Satisfaction, in not having any
where Liberty to entertain our ſelves. If I felt from that moment, that I
begun to love <hi>Nug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <pb n="38" facs="tcp:62420:27"/>Bella,</hi> ſhe found likewiſe
(as ſhe told me after, that I was not indifferent to her; being of the humour
whereof ſhe was, her conqueſt over me could not be diſagreeable to her;
there was ſomething ſo bright in my Fortune, that a perſon leſs
ambitious than ſhe, might have been dazled with it; ſhe never neglected to
appear lovely before me, though ſhe did nothing oppoſite to her natural
haughtineſs. Directed by the inſight, a growing love inſpires, I ſoon
flattered my ſelf with the hope of pleaſing her, and this hope was as
proper to inflame me, as the thought of finding a Rival well beloved was to
cure me. The Prince was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed to find that I applyed my ſelf to
<hi>Nugna Bella;</hi> he every day gave me oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to entertain her; he
was alſo willing I ſhould tell her of the differences that were betwixt the
King and him, and to inſtruct her in the way the Queen was to uſe to bring
him to, condeſcended to what the King deſired of him: <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>
failed not to give the Queen theſe Advices, and as often as the Queen made
uſe of them, ſhe never wanted the ſucceſs ſhe deſired, ſo that
the Queen never undertook any thing in the Princes behalf, without firſt
conſulting <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> nor <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> without
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting me. Thus we had great oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities <pb n="39" facs="tcp:62420:27"/>of
converſing with one another: and in thoſe converſations, I found in her
ſo much wit, prudence and agreeableneſs; and ſhe likewiſe fancied in me
ſo much Merit, and really found ſo much Love, that it kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in us a
flame that has been ſince very violent: The Prince would needs be my
Confident, nor could I hide any thing from him: I feared only that <hi>Nugna
Bella</hi> would be offended if I had told him that ſhe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me any
demonſtrations of kindneſs; but <hi>Don Garcias</hi> aſſured me, that
of the humour ſhe was of, ſhe would be no way diſpleaſed at it: He
ſpoke to her of me; ſhe was at firſt out of countenance, and in ſome
diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at what he told her; but as he judged right, the greatneſs of the
confident, made her approve of the confidence; ſhe accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf
to ſuffer him to entertain her up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſubject of my paſſion, and
received by his hand the firſt Letters I writ to her.</p>
               <p>Love was to us an agreeable novelty, in which we found all the
ſecret charms that are no where to be had but in our firſt Love: As my
Ambition was fully ſatisfied, even before I was in Love, this laſt
paſſion was no way weakened by the former; I gave up my ſoul to this new
pleaſure, which till that time was unknown to me, and which I valued above
all that Grandure <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62420:28"/>can beſtow: <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> was
not ſo, for theſe Paſſions took their Birth in her at the ſame time,
and equally divided her heart; her natural inclination was without queſtion,
more prone to Ambition than to Love, but as the one and the other had a
reference to me, I ſtill found in her all the ardour, and all the application
I could deſire; not but that ſhe was ſometimes as much taken up with the
Princes affairs, as ſhe was with the concerns of our Love. For my part,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken up wholly by my paſſion for her, I found out to my ſorrow
that <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> was capable of other thoughts: I complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her
of it, but I found that my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints were fruitleſs, and produced nothing
but a certain conſtrained Converſation which gave me to ſee that her mind
was elſe-where ingaged. Notwithſtanding, having heard ſay that we could
not be perfectly happy in Love, no more than in other things of this life, I
ſuffered this Misfortune with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> Loved me with
an exact Faith, and I could perceive in her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but contempt for any
elſe that durſt look upon her: I was perſwaded that ſhe was free from
all thoſe imbecilities to which other Women are inclined: this thought made
my happineſs ſo compleat, that I thought I had nothing further to wiſh
for.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62420:28"/>Fortune had placed me in a rank worthy the
emulation and envy of the moſt Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious; I was Favourite to a Prince whom I
loved with a paſſionate inclination; I was beloved by the faireſt Woman
in <hi>Spain,</hi> whom I adored; and <hi>I</hi> had a Friend whom <hi>I</hi>
thought faithful, becauſe <hi>I</hi> made his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. The only thing that
troubled my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, was the Injuſtice <hi>I</hi> ſaw in <hi>Don
Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> his impatience to command, and to find my Father <hi>Nugnes
Fernando</hi> of a turbulent unquiet ſpirit, and aſpiring (as the King
ſuſpected) to raiſe himſelf above all other Authority: I was
apprehenſive to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by the Lawes of Gratitude and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to
perſons that might draw me to do things that did no way ſeem juſt to me.
In the mean time, as theſe were but uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties and imaginations, they
troubled me but ſometimes, and <hi>I</hi> eaſed my mind by communicating
them to <hi>Don Ramires,</hi> in whom <hi>I</hi> had ſo much confidence, that
<hi>I</hi> acquainted him with my very fears and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of things of
the higheſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and my ſore-ſight of dangers yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off.</p>
               <p>But the chiefeſt occupation of my mind, was the deſign
<hi>I</hi> had to Marry <hi>Nugna Bella:</hi> I had now a long time been in
Love with her without preſuming to make her that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture: 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62420:29"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> know the King would oppoſe it, becauſe
<hi>Nugna Bella</hi> was the Daughter of a Count of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> whoſe
revolt was as much feared as my Fathers, and it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rules of
pollicy to let them U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite by the tyes of a Marriage. <hi>I</hi> knew
likewiſe that my Father, although he was not averſe to my deſign, would
not conſent to have my Marriage propoſed, fearing leſt that would
increaſe the Kings ſuſpition, ſo that <hi>I</hi> was forced to wait a
more favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conjuncture; but in the mean while <hi>I</hi> did not conceal
the Inclination <hi>I</hi> had for <hi>Nugna Bella: I</hi> ſpoke to her as
often as <hi>I</hi> had opportunity, the Prince alſo ſpoke to her very
often: The King took Cogniſance of our intelligence, and took that for a
State-affair that was but a Love intreigue; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved his Son did favour my
deſign upon <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> thereby to joyn the two Counts of
<hi>Castile</hi> to his intereſt; he thought his Son meant thereby to form a
Party conſiderable enough to beget him an Authority that might ballance his:
He doubted not but that the two Counts of <hi>Castile</hi> would take his Sons
part, in hopes to get themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Soveraign Princes: Laſtly,
the Union of the two Houſes of <hi>Caſtile</hi> was ſo terrible to him,
that he declared he would not have me by any means think of <hi>Nugna 
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62420:29"/>Bella,</hi> and forbid the Prince in any wiſe to favour
our Marriage.</p>
               <p>The Counts of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> who perhaps were not innocent
of all that they were ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of by the King, but wanted power to ſhew
their intentions, commanded us to think no more of one another; this command
was moſt grievous to us: But the Prince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed us to make the King
change his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion in ſome ſhort time; he ingaged us mutually to
promiſe each other an eternal Friendſhip, and took upon him to find means
to continue our commerce, and conceal our intreigue. The Queen, who well knew,
that far from carrying the Prince to a revolt, we endeavoured with all our
might to keep him within the bounds of his Allegiance, approved her Sons
deſign for us, and favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it as much as might be.</p>
               <p>As it was no longer permitted us to ſpeak to one another in
publick, we ſought after means to entertain our ſelves in private.
<hi>I</hi> thought it to our purpoſe that <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> ſhould be
removed from her Appartment to another, whereof all the Windows looked into a
Bye-lane, and were ſo low, that a Man on Horſe-back might look in, and
conveniently diſcourſe without trouble of ſpeaking very loud: <hi>I</hi>
propoſed this project to the Prince, he commended it to <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62420:30"/>the Queen, ſhe upon ſome ſpecious pretence, cauſes it to be
done as we deſired. I came every day to this Window to wait the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in
which <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> could come to ſpeak to me; ſometimes I went away
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly charmed with the good eſteem ſhe had for me, and ſometimes I
parted in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, to ſee her ſo much taken up with the Queen: Hitherto
Fortune was conſtant to favour my deſignes, but ſhe ſoon changed her
courſe, to let me ſee that ſhe could not continue a conſtant Friend to
any Man.</p>
               <p>My Father, who was fully informed of the Kings ſuſpicion of
him, reſolved by a new Teſtimony of his Sincerity, to ſhew his Majeſty
how unjuſt his ſuſpicions were: He deſignes to place my Siſter in the
Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, notwithſtanding the reſolution he had before taken of leaving her
in <hi>Caſtilia;</hi> a vain thought puſhed him on to this reſolve; he
took a pride to ſhew to the Court a Beauty, which he believed to be one of
the moſt accompliſhed of all <hi>Spain;</hi> never was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Father more
fondly conceited of his Childrens Beauty, and drew from it a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which
might be call'd a great weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a Perſon of his quality; he brought
her therefore to Court, and ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Pallace.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:62420:30"/>
                  <hi>Don Garcias</hi> happened to be a
Hunting that day ſhe came; he came at night to viſit the Queen, without
having ſeen any body that might give him an account of her: I was alſo
there, but retired into a corner where he could not ſee me. The Queen
preſents <hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> to him (ſo was my Siſter called) he was
ſurprized with her Beauty, even to admiration; he ſaid, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before
ſaw in one perſon ſo much Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo much Majeſty, and ſo much
agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs; and that, ſo white a skin, ſo black hair, and eyes of
ſo delicate a blew was never ſeen before; that her bloming youth was
accompanyed with a becoming Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; the more he looked upon her, the more he
commended her. <hi>Don Ramires</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved his earneſtneſs in
praiſing <hi>Hermene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilde;</hi> it was not hard for him to judge, that I
had the ſame thoughts of <hi>Don Garcias</hi> his actions; and ſeeing me at
the other end of the Room, he came to me to ſpeak of my Siſters Beauty: I
wiſh there were none elſe taken with her but you, ſaid I: as I was
ſpeaking theſe words, <hi>Don Garcias</hi> by chance came near me; he
ſeemed to be ſurpriſed, ſeeing me, but he recollected himſelf, and
talked to me of <hi>Hermeneſilde,</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me that I had not deſcribed
her ſo Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful as he found her: At his going to Bed <pb n="46" facs="tcp:62420:31"/>that Night, all the diſcourſe was of her; I obſerved him with
much care, and his not commending her with the ſame aſſurance the reſt
did, confirmed my ſuſpicions of him; the following days he could not
refrain en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining of her; and the inclination he had for her, ſeemed to
me to hurry him like a torrent to what he could not reſiſt: I endeavoured
to diſcover his thoughts without any ſerious application; one night, as we
came out from the Queen, where he had entertained <hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> for a
conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time. Sir, may I be ſo bold as to ask you (ſaid I) whether
I have not been too backward to ſhew you my Siſter, and whether ſhe has
not Beauty enough to cauſe in you thoſe ſurpriſes which <hi>I</hi> was
appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of: <hi>I</hi> have been ſurpriſed with her Beauty
(anſwered the Prince) but though <hi>I</hi> believe one cannot be concerned
for her without being ſurpriſed, ſo <hi>I</hi> do not believe that any
can be ſurpriſed without being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Gracias</hi> was reſolved not to make me a more
ſerious anſwer than my Queſtion was; but as he was perplext with my
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and that he catched himſelf in it, there was a tone of diſguſt
in his anſwer by which he gave me, to underſtand that <hi>I</hi> was not
deceived in my judgment: And he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62420:31"/>found that
<hi>I</hi> had perceived his paſſion for my Siſter; yet he loved me well
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to conceive ſome grief to have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued himſelf in an affair that
he knew muſt be diſpleaſing to me; but he was too far ingaged in Love to
<hi>Hermeneſilde,</hi> to give over his deſign of creating as much Love in
her; neither did <hi>I</hi> pretend that he ſhould leave loving of her, for
the Love of me; my thoughts were only to prepoſſeſs my Siſter with what
ſhe was to do if the Prince ſhould make her a declaration of his Love. I
therefore gave her a caution in all things to follow the advice of <hi>Nugna
Bella,</hi> which ſhe promiſed to do: <hi>I</hi> therefore declared to
<hi>Nugna Bella</hi> my diſquiet about the Princes Love to my Siſter;
<hi>I</hi> told her all the unhappy conſequences which <hi>I</hi>
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended from it; ſhe had the ſame thoughts, and promiſed me that
ſhe would keep ſo cloſe to <hi>Hermeneſilde,</hi> that the Prince
ſhould find difficulty enough to ſpeak to her; whereupon they were ſo
inſeparably without the leaſt ſhew of doing of it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely, that
<hi>Don Garcias</hi> could never find <hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> without <hi>Nugna
Bella;</hi> this diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty was ſo troubleſome to him, that he was hardly
like the ſame man: As he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly uſed to acquaint me with all his
thoughts, and that he told me never a word <pb n="48" facs="tcp:62420:32"/>of what moſt
poſſeſſed then his mind, I quickly found a great alteration in his
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings towards me.</p>
               <p>Do not you admire (ſaid <hi>I</hi> to <hi>Don Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires</hi>)
the injuſtice of Man-kind? The Prince hates me becauſe he feels in his
heart a paſſion that ought to diſpleaſe me; and if he were Loved by my
Siſter, he would hate me more than he does: <hi>I</hi> well fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw the
Miſchief that would befall me, if her Beauty ſhould make any impreſſion
upon him; and if he does not change the inclination he has for her, <hi>I</hi>
ſhall not be long his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite in the eyes of the publick, ſince
<hi>I</hi> am no more ſo in his heart. <hi>Don Ramires</hi> was convinced of
the Princes Love as well as I; but to blot out of my mind a thing that gave me
pain, I know not (ſaid he) what grounds you have to believe that <hi>Don
Garcias</hi> is in Love with <hi>Hermeneſilde;</hi> it is true, he commended
her at firſt, but <hi>I</hi> ſaw nothing ever ſince in him that can make
out his being in Love: And admit he ſhould be in Love, what great miſchief
would there be in that? Why may not he Marry her? he is not the firſt Prince
that has Married one of his Subjects, neither can he find any more worthy of
him then ſhe; and if he ſhould Marry her, what an honour would it be for
your Houſe? It is for that very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62420:32"/>(ſaid
<hi>I</hi>) that the King will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent he ſhould Marry her; neither
would <hi>I</hi> have it done without his Conſent; and may be, the Prince
himſelf does not aim at it; or, if he did, that he would not purſue it
neither reſolutely enough, nor long enough, to bring it to paſs. In fine,
It is a thing that is not feaſible; nor will <hi>I</hi> ſuffer the World to
believe, That <hi>I</hi> would hazard my Siſter's Reputation, upon the
ungrounded Hope of a Greatneſs, to which we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attain. If <hi>Don
Garcias</hi> continues his purſuit of my Siſter, <hi>I</hi> will carry her
from Court. <hi>Don Ramires</hi> was aſtoniſhed at my Reſolution; He was
afraid <hi>I</hi> ſhould fall out with <hi>Don Garcias:</hi> He reſolved to
Diſcover to him my Sentiments; and fancyed, he might do it without my
Conſent, ſince his intention was to ſerve me: But, without doubt, the
Deſire he had to ingratiate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the Prince, and to creep that way
into his Confidence, was no ſmall Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Reſolution.</p>
               <p>He took his time to ſpake to him alone; He told him, He forced
to commit an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity againſt me, by revealing my Thoughts contrary to my
Intentions: But that the Zeal he had for his Service, obliged him to inform
him, That <hi>I</hi> believed he was in Love with my Siſter; and that
<hi>I</hi> was ſo <pb n="50" facs="tcp:62420:33"/>much grieved at it, that <hi>I</hi>
reſolved to carry her away from Court. <hi>Don Garcias</hi> was ſo ſtruck
with <hi>Don Ramire's</hi> Diſcourſe, and the thought of ſeeing
<hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> leave the Court, that it was impoſſible for him to
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his firſt Tranſports: And therefore, believing that <hi>Don
Ramires</hi> could no longer doubt of the Concern he had for my Siſter, he
thought beſt to acknowledge it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ingage him, to continue his
Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of my Deſignes, from time to time; but he was a while, before
he could reſolve to do this: At laſt, being confirm'd in his Intention, he
Embraces him; and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, That he was in Love with
<hi>Hermeneſilde:</hi> He told him, That he had done what he could, to defend
himſelf from being in Love with her, upon my Conſideration; But, it was
impoſſible for him to live, without being beloved by her: That he begged
his Aſſiſtance to help him, to conceal his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hinder that
<hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> ſhould be removed from Court. <hi>Don Ramires,</hi>
his Heart was not of a Temper to reſiſt the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes of a Prince,
whoſe Favourite he was in Election to be: Friendſhip and Gratitude are too
weak, to reſiſt Ambition: He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes the Prince to keep his Counſel,
and to ſerve him with <hi>Hermeneſild.</hi> The Prince Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces him the
ſecond time; and they concert <pb n="51" facs="tcp:62420:33"/>together, how they were to
demean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the purſuit of this Enterprize.</p>
               <p>The firſt Obſtacle that occurs, is <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> who
never abandoned <hi>Hermeneſild:</hi> They reſolved to win her to their
ſide; and, notwithſtanding all the ſtrict Tyes that were betwixt her and
me, <hi>Don Ramires</hi> takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, to find the Means to bring it about:
But tells him, That it was neceſſary, that he ſhould himſelf endeavour
to blot out of my Mind, the Knowledge <hi>I</hi> had of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: He
adviſed him to tell me, by way of Joke, that he was glad he had found means
to make me afraid for ſome time paſt, to Revenge himſelf of me, for the
Suſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I at firſt conceived of him: But, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this my
Apprehenſion went too far, he would no longer let me believe, that he had any
Sentiments, that <hi>I</hi> might diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Garcias</hi> approving of this Expedient, eaſily
executed it: And, as he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by <hi>Don Ramires,</hi> the things which
gave me the moſt cauſe of Suſpition, it was not hard for him to ſay, he
did them of purpoſe: And, it was almoſt impoſſible for me not to
believe him. Thus was <hi>I</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, and fancyed my ſelf
better with him, than ever I was; yet I could not but think, that he had ſome
Thoughts in <pb n="52" facs="tcp:62420:34"/>Heart, which he kept from me: Yet I fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied
this was but a ſlight Inclination, which he had over-come; for which, I
believed my ſelf obliged to him, for having done it for my ſake. In fine,
<hi>I</hi> was very well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with <hi>Don Garcia's;</hi> and <hi>Don
Ramires</hi> was not a little pleaſed, to ſee me calmed, as he deſired.
Then he began to caſt about, how he might bring <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> into the
Confidence he wiſhed of her.</p>
               <p>Having conſidered a little with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf about the Means, he
ſought an occaſion to ſpeak to her; which ſhe often gave him;
becauſe, ſhe knew I concealed nothing from him, and that ſhe might
Diſcourſe with him about our Concerns: He began to entertain her with his
Joy, that the Prince and I were made Friends. She told him, She was as glad of
it as he: For, that I found (ſaid ſhe) <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſo nice upon
the Concern of his Siſter, that I apprehended he might em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broile himſelf
with <hi>Don Garcia.</hi> If I thought Madam (ſaid he) that you were of
thoſe, that were capable of concealing any thing from their Lovers, when it
is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for their Intereſt, it would be a great Comfort to me, to
ſpeak to a Perſon as concerned as your ſelf, in what regards
<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo:</hi> I fore-ſee things that gives great Diſquiet; and you
are the only Perſon to <pb n="53" facs="tcp:62420:34"/>whom <hi>I</hi> may impart them:
But, Madam, it is upon Condition, that you will not ſpeak of them even to
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> himſelf. <hi>I</hi> do promiſe it you, ſaid ſhe;
and you ſhall find me as ſecret, as you can deſire: <hi>I</hi> know, that
as it is dangerous to conceal ſome things from our Friends; ſo it is as
dangerous never to conceal any thing from them. You ſhall ſee, Madam,
(ſaid he) of what Importance it is to conceal what <hi>I</hi> am going about
to tell you: <hi>Don Garcias</hi> has lately given <hi>Don Gonſalvo</hi> new
Aſſurances of his Friendſhip; and has aſſured him, that he has no
more Thoughts of his Siſter; But <hi>I</hi> am very much miſtaken, if he
does not love her moſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately: Of the Humour this Prince is of, he
cannot long conceal his Paſſion; and, of the Humour <hi>Don Gonſalvo</hi>
is of, he will never ſuffer it ſhould continue: He will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly anger
the Prince, and quite loſe his Favour. <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs (ſaid
<hi>Nugna</hi>) that <hi>I</hi> had the ſame Suſpitions: And, by what
<hi>I</hi> have ſeen, and by certain things that <hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> has
told me, which <hi>I</hi> would not let her acquaint her Brother with, I could
not induce my Thoughts to believe, that what <hi>Don Garcias</hi> has, was but
an Affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a deſigne, only to fright <hi>Don Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo.</hi> You
did very diſcreetly (ſaid <hi>Don Ramires;</hi>) and <hi>I</hi> believe,
Madam, you will <pb n="54" facs="tcp:62420:35"/>do well for the ſuture, to keep
<hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> from telling her Brother any thing of what paſſes
betwixt her and the Prince, for it is both dangerous, and to no purpoſe to
ſpeak to him of it: If the Prince has but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate paſſion for her, he
will eaſily hide it, and by your conduct <hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> will
eaſily cure him of it; <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> will know nothing, and ſo you
will keep out of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal apprehenſions, and preſerve him in the favour of
the Prince: But if Don <hi>Garcias</hi> his paſſion be violent and
ſtrong, do you think it impoſſible for him to Marry
<hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneſilde?</hi> and would you believe that we ſhould do
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ill Service, if what we keep from his knowledge, ſhould
be a means to make his Prince his Brother-in-Law? Aſſuredly Madam, you
muſt well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether Don <hi>Garcias</hi> his Love to
<hi>Herme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſilde</hi> muſt be broke off; and it concerns you more than
any, by the intereſt you may have to ſee one day a perſon, your
<hi>Queen,</hi> which in all appearance will be your Siſter-in-Law.</p>
               <p>Theſe laſt words made <hi>Nugna</hi> ſee what ſhe had
not till then thought of; the hopes of being Siſter-in Law to the
<hi>Queen,</hi> made her believe there was more weight in Don <hi>Ramires</hi>
his reaſons than in truth there was: At laſt be managed her ſo well, that
it <pb n="55" facs="tcp:62420:35"/>was agreed betwixt them, that I ſhould know nothing of
their intreigne, that they would make an exact ſcrutiny into the Prince's
Thoughts; and that, from what they ſhould be able to diſcover of them, they
would take their Meaſures according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Ramires,</hi> Tranſported with Joy, to have ſo well
begun his Negotiation, gives the Prince an Account of what he had done: The
Prince was over-joyed at it, and gave <hi>Don Ramires</hi> full power to ſay
what he pleaſed of his Inclinations. <hi>Don Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires</hi> now,
plenipotentiary of the Princes Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, returns immediately to <hi>Nugna
Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la:</hi> He makes to her a long Narrative of his manner of bringing the
Prince to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his Paſſion for my Siſter: He adds, That he never
ſaw Man ſo tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Love: That he admired the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence the
Prince uſed to himſelf, for fear of diſpleaſing me: That all things
might be hoped from a Man ſo paſſionately in Love; But that it was
neceſſary to give him ſome Hope, that his Love would ſucceed.
<hi>Nug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> gave full Credit to all <hi>Don Ramires</hi> had ſaid; and
promiſed him to ſerve <hi>Don Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias,</hi> and employ all her Intereſt
with my Siſter, for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:62420:36"/>
                  <hi>Don Ramires</hi> runs to the Prince with
this Newes; which he receives with incredible Joy, and Embraced him a
thouſand times over: He could not forbear ſpeaking to him; and wiſhed, he
might not be obliged to ſpeak to any Body elſe: But that, he ſaw he could
not in Prudence change his Conduct, nor his manner of Living with me. <hi>Don
Ramires</hi> himſelf, took great care to conceal his new acquired Favour; and
the Remorſe of his Treachery, made him ſtill believe that <hi>I</hi>
ſuſpected it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Garcias</hi> ſoon found Opportunity to ſpeak to
<hi>Hermeneſilde;</hi> He declared to her his Paſſion for her, with all
the Zeal he could: And, as he was really in Love, he found no great difficulty
to perſwade her, that he was ſo. She was diſpoſed to Entertain him
kindly: But, after what <hi>I</hi> had ſaid to her, ſhe was afraid to
follow the Dictates of her own Heart. She acquaints <hi>Nugna</hi> with all
that paſſed betwixt the Prince and her. <hi>Nugna,</hi> for thoſe very
Reaſons <hi>Don Ramires</hi> had alleadged to her, adviſed her to let me
know nothing; and ſo to manage the Prince, as to inflame him more, and
preſerve his Eſteem for her: She told her further, That what-ever
Repugnance I might ſhew againſt the Princes Love to her; yet ſhe might
well believe, that I ſhould be very glad of <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62420:36"/>what was like
to be ſo advantagious to me, but that for certain reaſons I was unwilling
to take any Cogniſance of things until they were more advanced.
<hi>Hermeneſilde,</hi> who had an entire deferrence to all that <hi>Nugna
Bella</hi> deſired, was eaſily drawn to follow her conduct, and her
inclination for Don <hi>Garcias</hi> was ſtrongly ſupported with the hopes
of a Crown.</p>
               <p>This intrigue betwixt my Siſter and the Prince was carried on
with ſo much art and dexterity, that except the firſt day or two that
notice was taken of his commending her Beauty, none ever ſuſpected that he
had any inclination for her: He never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained her publickly, for
<hi>Nugna</hi> gave him opportunities of converſing with her in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate: I
perceived a decay in the Princes Friendſhip to me, but I did attribute it to
the inequality and levity which is uſual in young people.</p>
               <p>Things were in this poſture when <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dala,</hi> King of
<hi>Cordona</hi> (betwixt whom and the King of <hi>Leon</hi> there had been a
long Truce, begun the War again. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Army belonged to
<hi>Nugnes Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando</hi> by the right of his place; and though the King were
unwilling to place him at the head of his Troops, yet could he not take the
command of them from him, without <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62420:37"/>charging him with ſome
great Crime, or cauſing him to be clapt up: It's true, he might have given
Don <hi>Garcias</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over him, but the King apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him more
than he did the Count of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile,</hi> and was affraid to ſee them
both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a great power in their hands.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide <hi>Biſcay</hi> began to revolt, wherefore
he reſolves to ſend the Prince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rebels, and <hi>Nugnes
Fernando</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Moores:</hi> I ſhould have been glad to
ſerve under my Father, but the Prince would have me along with him into
<hi>Biſcay;</hi> and the King was more inclined to have me with his Son than
with the Count of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile,</hi> ſo that I was fain to ſubmit to what
was deſired, and to ſee my Father part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us. He was much troubled
that I was not permitted to attend him, and beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other
conſiderable reaſons that made him deſire my being in his Army, his
pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Love was none of the leaſt: The af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection he bore to my Siſter
and me was infinitely tender; he carryed along with him our Pictures, that he
might have the ſatisfaction of ſeeing us always, and of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the
beauty of his Children, of which I believe I told you that he was very much
enamoured. He marched againſt <hi>Abdala</hi> with a very conſiderable
Army, but much <pb n="59" facs="tcp:62420:37"/>inferiour to that of the <hi>Moores;</hi>
and inſtead of endeavouring only to hinder their paſſage in a place
whereof the very Scituation made his Army inacceſſible; the deſire of
doing ſomething extraordinary, made him hazard a Battle in open Campagne,
where he could have no manner of advantage; his men was ſo totally routed,
that he had much difficulty to ſave himſelf; all his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was cut in
pieces, all his Baggage loſt, and the <hi>Moors</hi> perhaps never gained
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo ſignal a Victory againſt the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
               <p>They received the news of this overthrow with much regret,
laying all the blame up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Father, and not without reaſon; but as he was
glad to humble him, he laid hold of this occaſion; and when my Father
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to come to juſtifie himſelf, he ſent him word he would never
ſee him more, and that he deprived him of all his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that he might
thank God that his head was not taken off; he had orders to retire to his own
Eſtate. My Father obeyed him, and with-drawes into <hi>Caſtilia</hi> as
full of rage and deſpair as an ambitious man, whoſe fortune and reputation
had received ſo great a breach, could be capable of.</p>
               <p>The Prince (by reaſon of a dangerous fit of Sickneſs) was
not yet departed for <hi>Biſcay;</hi> 
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:62420:38"/>the King Marches in
perſon againſt the <hi>Moores</hi> with all the force he could bring
together: I beg'd leave to wait upon him, which he granted, but unwillingly; he
would have heaped upon me all my Fathers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces, but as I had no ſhare
in his fault, and that the Prince ſtill ſhewed much kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for me, the
King durſt not Baniſh me into <hi>Castile,</hi> therefore I followed him,
and Don <hi>Ramires</hi> ſtaid with the Prince. <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> ſeemed
to be neerly concerned for my Misfortune and our ſeparation: I parted with
the Conſolation at leaſt of believing my ſelf beloved of the perſon of
the World I moſt eſteemed and loved.</p>
               <p>The Prince being not in a condition to command, his Brother Don
<hi>Ordogno</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto <hi>Biſcay;</hi> he was as unfortunate in his
enterpriſe as the King was ſucceſsful: Don <hi>Ordogno</hi> was defeated,
and eſcaped nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly with his Life. They overthrew the <hi>Moores,</hi> and
forced them to beg Peace. It was my good fortune to do ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Services, but I was never the better uſed by the King; the reputation I had
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, did not free me from the Contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ayre, with which Diſgrace had
blaſted me: When I came to <hi>Leon,</hi> I eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that Glory
does not confer the ſame luſtre as Favour does.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62420:38"/>Don <hi>Garcias</hi> (during my abſence)
had the advantage of ſeeing <hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> very often, but with that
caution, that none per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived or took notice of his addreſſes; he ſought
all means imaginable to pleaſe her; he gave her hopes that he would one day
place her upon the Throne of <hi>Leon;</hi> he had, In fine, ſhewed ſo much
affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, that ſhe wholly abandoned her heart to him.</p>
               <p>As Don <hi>Ramires</hi> and <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> were obliged to
ſee one another often, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to mannage this intelligence, and the
Beauty of <hi>Nugna</hi> was of thoſe kinds that are not often ſeen without
danger; ſo the admiration which Don <hi>Ramires</hi> had for her, augmented
every day, and ſhe likewiſe was not a little taken with his Wit, which, to
ſay the truth, was very agreeable. The particular commerce that paſſed
betwixt them, and the continual occupation which the affairs of the Prince and
<hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> gave her, made her leſs ſenſible of my ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
than ſhe could have promis'd her ſelf at our ſeparation.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the King was returned, he beſtowed all the places
which <hi>Nugna Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando</hi> had, upon Don <hi>Ramires</hi> his Father. I did
upon that occaſion beyond what could be expected from a ſincere Friend; for
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, <pb n="62" facs="tcp:62420:39"/>after the Services I had rendered the King in
theſe two laſt Wars, I might have pretended to thoſe employments which
were taken from my Father, yet I did no way oppoſe my pretenſions to the
Kings diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of them.</p>
               <p>I went to Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> and told him that the only
conſolation I had, after the loſs of ſo many advantagious
eſtabliſhments taken from my Family, was the joy I had to ſee them
confer'd upon his Houſe; though Don <hi>Ramires</hi> wanted no wit, yet he
could make me no anſwer; he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded to receive ſuch marks of a
Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which he knew he did not deſerve; but I gave ſo favourable a
conſtruction to his Confuſion, that his words could not be more
perſwaſive to me. My Fathers em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments being transfer'd to another
Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, made the <hi>Court</hi> believe that his diſgrace was for ever
without remedy; and Don <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires</hi> was now almoſt in my ſtead by the
new Dignities his Father had received, and by the Princes favour towards
himſelf: This favour appeared very plainly, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the care
they both took to conceal it; and every body inſenſibly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to follow
this new Favourite, and by degrees to leave me. <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>'s
affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not ſo firmly ſetled, but that theſe <pb n="63" facs="tcp:62420:39"/>alterations cauſed ſome change in it; my Fortune as much as my
Perſon had laid the foundation of her Love for me: I was in diſgrace, and
ſhe held for me, by the bare tyes of a Love, that was too weak long to hold a
heart like hers. I found ſoon after a ſenſible decay in her affection
towards me; I complained of it to Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> I ſpoke of it
likewiſe to <hi>Nugna Bella;</hi> ſhe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured me, that ſhe was
ſtill the ſame for me as ſhe had been; and as I had no preciſe cauſe
of complaint, and that my ſuſpicions took their riſe from a certain ayre
of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, which I imagined in all her actions: It was not hard for her to
juſtifie her ſelf, which ſhe did with ſo much cunning and addreſs,
that ſhe re-aſſured me for ſome time.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Ramires</hi> entertained her upon the ſubject of my
ſuſpicions of her change, and ſpoke to her with deſign to find out
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe were ſo or not; without doubt, with a deſire to know that I
was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in my opinion. I am not changed, ſaid ſhe; I Love as well
as I ever did; but if I loved him leſs, it were injuſtice in him to
complain; are we Maſters of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings or end of our paſſions? She
ſpoke theſe words with an ayre, that aſſured him that ſhe no longer
loved me: This aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <pb n="64" facs="tcp:62420:40"/>which gave Don
<hi>Ramires</hi> ſome hope, made him open his eyes to contemplate the Beauty
of this unfaithful Woman, of which he was ſo enamoured, that being no longer
Maſter of himſelf, told her, ſhe was in the right. We have no power,
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, over our paſſions, for I feel one that draws me ſo forceably,
that it is not in my power to reſiſt it; but remember, it is your opinion,
that it does not depend on us to oppoſe it. <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> eaſily
comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his meaning; at which ſhe ſeemed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle concern'd as well
as he: As he had ſaid it with premeditation, he was ſurpriſed at the
effect it had; the remembrance of the Obligations he owed me, fill'd all his
thoughts, and put him into ſome diſorder, he caſt down his eyes, and
remained a while in a profound ſilence, and <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> for
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the like nature, was ſilent likewiſe; they parted without any
further diſcourſe: Don <hi>Ramires</hi> repented him of what he had ſaid,
and <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> that ſhe did not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him: Don
<hi>Ramires</hi> went away ſo much troubled, and ſo out of order, that he
was not himſelf; after recollecting himſelf a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, he began to reflect
upon his own thoughts, but the more he examined them, the farther he found his
heart ingaged; he then begun to conſider the danger he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed 
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62420:40"/>himſelf to, by ſo often ſeeing <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi>
he knew the delight he had taken in her Converſation, was of another nature
than he had imagined. Laſtly, he found he was in Love, and that it was too
late to endeavour to ſuppreſs it.</p>
               <p>The aſſurance he had that <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> loved me
leſs, left him no force to reſiſt his paſſion; he thought he had
excuſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to engage himſelf to her, when he knew her diſingaged from
me; he found ſome pleaſure in undertaking to conquer a heart, of which I
was no longer ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely poſſeſſor, but that he might conceive
ſome hopes to gain it; but withall, that I had power enough over it to
acquire him the glory of diſpoſſeſſing me: However, when he came to
conſider that it was <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> that muſt be removed from this
heart, that <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to whom he owed ſo true a Friendſhip; his
thoughts made him bluſh, and oppoſed them ſo, that he believed he had
conquered them, he reſolved to ſay no more of his Love to <hi>Nugna
Bella,</hi> and to avoid the occaſions of ſpeaking to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> who had no other trouble, but for not
anſwering Don <hi>Ramires</hi> as ſhe ought to have done, made not ſo
many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections; ſhe thought ſhe had no reaſon to ſeem to
underſtand what he ſaid to her, <pb n="66" facs="tcp:62420:41"/>ſhe believed ſhe
ought to have ſome kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for a man, with whom ſhe had ſuch tyes:
She ſaid to her ſelf, that he had not ſpoken to her with any deſign,
though ſhe had for a long time perceived the Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he had for her; but
leaſt ſhe ſhould repent her, or be obliged to uſe Don <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires</hi>
ill, ſhe undertook not to believe what ſhe could no way doubt of.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Ramires</hi> followed the deſign he had taken for a
while, but in vain, for he faw every day <hi>Nugna Bella:</hi> She was
hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, ſhe no longer loved me; ſhe uſed him kindly: It was
impoſſible to reſiſt ſo many allurements, he reſolves therefore to
follow the inclinations of his heart: He had no ſooner taken this
reſolution, but all his former remorſe vaniſhed; the firſt Treachery he
committed againſt me, made the ſecond more eaſie; he had uſed himſelf
to deceive me, and to conceal from me what he ſaid to <hi>Nugna Bella:</hi>
He tells her at laſt that he loved her, and he told it her with all the marks
of an unfeigned paſſion, exagerating to her his grief for
tranſgreſſing againſt out Friendſhip; he inforces that he is hurried
on by the moſt violent paſſion that ever man had; he aſſures her he
does not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be loved again, that he well knew the advantages I had
over him, and the <pb n="67" facs="tcp:62420:41"/>impoſſibility of removing me out of
her heart, but that he only begg'd the favour of her to hear him, and to help
him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover himſelf, and to conceal his weakneſs from me.
<hi>Nugna</hi> promiſes the laſt, as a thing ſhe thought her ſelf
obliged to, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leaſt ſome miſchief might happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, and
told him with a great deal of ſweetneſs, that ſhe could not grant him the
reſt. Believing ſhe ſhould be a complice to his crime if ſhe ſhould
ſuffer the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it; yet for all that ſhe did ſuffer it; the
Love he bore her, and the Friendſhip ſhe had for him, drew her wholly to
his ſide: I appeared leſs agreeable in her eye; ſhe could ſee no great
advantage in my For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, being threatned daily with an aſſured
Baniſhment into <hi>Caſtile:</hi> She knew the King had always a mind to
ſend me thither, and that the Prince oppoſed it only out of a point of
Honour; ſhe ſaw no likelihood of his Marrying <hi>Hermeneſild;</hi> ſhe
was ſtill his Confident in the Love he had for her; and by this and Don
<hi>Ramire</hi>'s Love towards her, ſhe ſtill kept her Credit with Don
<hi>Garcias,</hi> ſhe believed the King was leſs diſpoſed than ever, to
conſent to our Marriage; he had no reaſon to oppoſe her Marriage with Don
<hi>Ramires,</hi> ſhe found in him the ſame advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages that recommended my
Love to her: <pb n="68" facs="tcp:62420:42"/>and laſtly, ſhe concluded that reaſon as
well as prudence did Authoriſe her change, and that ſhe ought to abandon a
man that was never like to be her Husband, for one that in all probability
might Marry her; there needs not always ſo many reaſons to warrant a Womans
Levity. <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> therefore determins to engage in Affection with
Don <hi>Ramires;</hi> though when ſhe made that reſolution, ſhe was
already engaged to him both in her inclination and her words; yet whatever her
reſolutions were, ſhe had not force enough to let me ſee that ſhe
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted me in the time of my diſgrace.</p>
               <p>Neither could Don <hi>Ramires</hi> reſolve to declare his
Treachery; it was agreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, that <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> ſhould
conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to live with me after the ſame rate ſhe had been uſed to do;
and they believed that I could not eaſily diſcover her change, becauſe as
I told Don <hi>Ramires</hi> ſtill the leaſt of my thoughts, ſhe being
always told of them by Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> might eaſily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any
cauſe of ſuſpicion: They reſolved alſo to tell Don <hi>Garcias</hi>
how things ſtood betwixt them, thereby to engage him to their intereſt; Don
<hi>Ramires</hi> took upon him to do it, though he could not reſolve it
without trouble, for the ſhame, and the fear of being diſcountenanced
embaraſhed him. But <pb n="69" facs="tcp:62420:42"/>the Confidence Don <hi>Garcias</hi>
put in him, and the power he gave him to mannage his Love, gave him ſome
aſſurance: The truth is, that he managed the Prince as he pleaſed; he
engages him, even to ſpeak a good word for him to <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> ſo
that this new Favourite had his Maſter for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident; as he was his
Maſters, <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> who apprehended that the Prince would condemn
her Inconſtancy, was raviſhed to find him rather a promoter of it; they
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled their Bonds of mutual fidelity to one another; they then take their
meaſures how to conceal this intelligence; ſhe reſolved that, ſeeing
the particular Whiſperings of Don <hi>Ramires</hi> and the Prince might give
me ſome Jealouſie, becauſe in appearance they ought to keep no ſecret
from me, that Don <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires</hi> ſhould come to the Prince by a back
Stair, at ſuch times as he had none with him, and that they ſhould never
ſpeak any thing before me of their intreigue: Thus was I betrayed and
forſaken by all thoſe I loved beſt, without being able to ſuſpect
them in the leaſt.</p>
               <p>All I was in pain for, was only becauſe I fancied ſome
change in <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>'s heart; if I complained to Don
<hi>Ramires,</hi> Don <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires</hi> gave her notice of it, that ſhe might
counterfeit better; but when I ſeemed at <pb n="70" facs="tcp:62420:43"/>eaſe, he was
unquiet, he feared ſtill I had regained <hi>Nugna Bella;</hi> then he would
not have her act her part ſo well in Cheating me; ſhe obeyed him, and
neglected me more than ever: Thus he had his Rival complaining to him of the
hard uſage he received by his order. Sometimes he was very glad when he had
deſired her to put a conſtraint upon her ſelf, to learn by my complaints
that ſhe had not conſtrained her ſelf as much as he deſired her. It was
ſuch a charm for his glory and his love to have ruined ſuch a Rival as I
appeared to him, and to ſee my quiet depend upon the leaſt word of his
mouth, that were it not for his extream Jealouſie, he would be the
happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt man in the world.</p>
               <p>While I was taken up with my Amour, my Father was buſied by
his Ambition; he had made ſo many Cabals, and ſo many intregues in the time
of his Exile, that he believed himſelf in a condition to revolt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly; but
before all, I was to be drawn from Court, I was too dear, and too
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a pledge to him to leave me in the Kings hands, when he
intended to declare War againſt him: He was not ſo apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of my
Siſter, becauſe her Sex and her Beauty would protect her againſt all
events. He ſent me a perſon known in all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, 
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62420:43"/>to inform me how matters ſtood, and to command me to quie
the Court in that very inſtant, without taking leave either of the King or
Prince. This Meſſenger was ſtrangely ſurpriſed to find me quite of
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opinion than my Father: I told him that I would never give my
conſent to ſo unjuſt a revolt; that it was true, the King had dealt ill
with <hi>Nugnes Ferrando,</hi> in taking away his employments; but that this
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front was to be endured, becauſe he had in ſome meaſure deſerved it;
that for my part I was reſolved not to leave the Court, nor ever to take Arms
againſt my King: This Meſſenger carryed back my Anſwer to my Father, he
was outragiouſly mad to ſee ſo many great deſignes quaſhed to
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by my diſobedience alone: He ſent me back word, that (though he
never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it) he would purſue his enterpriſe; and that ſince I had
ſo little obedience for his will, he would not change his reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
though the King of <hi>Leon</hi> were to cut off my head.</p>
               <p>In the mean time Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for
<hi>Nugna Bella</hi> grew ſtill, and he could no longer indure the manner of
her conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with me, though he ſaw it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Well Madam,
ſays he to her one day, after ſhe had entertained me a pretty while, 
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62420:44"/>you look upon him ſtill with the ſame kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that
you uſed to do, you ſpeak to him after the ſame manner, you write to him
the ſame kind things; who ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure me, that it is no more with the
ſame heart? He once pleaſed you, and that's enough to find the way of doing
it again. But you know (ſaid ſhe) I do but what you would have me; that is
true, replyed he, and that is it which renders my misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune inſupportable,
that I muſt in prudence adviſe you to do thoſe things, which when you do
them, puts me into deſpair; it is unheard, that a Lover ever gave his
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that his Rival ſhould be kindly treated. Madam, I can no longer
endure that you ſhould look upon <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi> there is nothing I
would not attempt to ruine him, rather than live in the condition I am in; for
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having rob'd him of your heart, I ought not much to ſcruple cutting
his Throat: Your Paſſion (anſwered <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>) is too violent
to hold; you will firſt conſider how many important ſecrets you will
diſcover before you fall out with Don <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> and to what
Reproaches you will expoſe your ſelf. I ſee all that is to be ſeen
Madam, ſaid he; I ſee likewiſe, that if I muſt have but little
ſenſe to do what I propoſe, I muſt have none at all, to ſuffer a man
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <pb n="73" facs="tcp:62420:44"/>way lovely, that once has pleaſed you, to ſpake
to you every day in private; if I knew nothing of it, I ſhould have the cruel
delight of being deceived: But I know it, I ſee you ſpeaking to him; it is
I that brings you Letters, it is I that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſures him when he doubts of
your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: Ah Madam, it is impoſſible I ſhould hold out any longer,
uſing ſo much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt my ſelf: If you would contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to my
quiet, contrive it ſo that <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> may leave the Court; and the
Prince would conſent to ſend him into <hi>Caſtile,</hi> as his Majeſty
preſſes him every day. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I beſeech you, replyed <hi>Nugna
Bella,</hi> what an action you would have me do? Yes Madam, returned Don
<hi>Ramires,</hi> I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered it; but after all that you have done, it
is no longer time to ſtand upon Niceties: and if you conſent not to the
Baniſhment of Don <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> I ſhall believe I have more reaſon
to endeavour his abſence from you than I thought: Once more, Madam, by what
arguments ſhall I be convinced that you love him no more? you ſee him, you
ſpeak to him, you know he Loves; your heart, you ſay, is changed, but your
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings are not: In fine, Madam, nothing can re-aſſure me, but your
endeavours to get him Baniſhed, and as long as you ſhall 
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62420:45"/>appear averſe to it, I ſhall believe you uſe but
little conſtraint when you tell him you Love him. Well then, ſaid <hi>Nugna
Bella,</hi> I have already committed many Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for the Love of you, and
I will add this too; but give me the means, the Prince every day refuſes the
King to let him be Baniſhed, and there is little likelihood that he ſhould
grant it to ſo unreaſonable a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt as mine: I'le take upon me (ſaid
Don <hi>Ramires</hi>) to make the Propoſition to the Prince, and provided you
make it appear to him that you are conſenting to it, I am ſure to bring it
about: <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> agrees to it, and that very night Don
<hi>Ramires</hi> (under pretence of their common intereſt) propoſes to the
Prince to let me be ſent away, and to make the King believe he did it in
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his commands: The Prince made no difficulty of aſſenting; he
was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſo aſhamed of what he had done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, that my
preſence was a continual reproach to him of his weakneſs. <hi>Nugna
Bella</hi> ſpoke to him as ſhe had promiſed Don <hi>Ramires;</hi> they
reſolved that upon the firſt occaſion the Prince ſhould ſend his
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word that he would no longer oppoſe my Baniſhment from Court,
provided it ſhould be given out that it was done againſt his will.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:62420:45"/>An occaſion ſoon offer'd it ſelf; the
King was in paſſion againſt the Prince, for doing ſomething againſt
his order, and accuſed me for adviſing him to it: The Prince not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to
come into the Kings preſence, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be Sick, and kept his Bed for
ſome dayes; the Queen (according to her cuſtom) endeavoured a
reconciliation, ſhe came to her Sons Appartment to acquaint him with the
King's complaints againſt him. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, theſe are not the true cauſes of
the King's Anger, I know the reaſon, he has a ſtrange averſion againſt
<hi>Gonſabvo,</hi> he accuſes him of all that diſpleaſes him, he
deſires to ſend him away; He will never be well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with me, as
long as I oppoſe his abſence. I love <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> dearly, but I
ſee I muſt be forced even againſt my will to conſent to his
Baniſhment, and to deprive my ſelf of him, ſince I can purchaſe the
Kings good will at no other rate. Tell him then Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, if you pleaſe, that I
conſent he ſhould be Baniſhed, but upon condition that none know I have
conſented to it. The Queen was ſurpriſed at her Sons diſcourſe: It
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes not me (ſaid ſhe) to think it ſtrange that you ſhould have a
deferrence to the King's will, but I muſt confeſs I wonder how you can
conſent to <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the Prince alleadged ſome
bad rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <pb n="76" facs="tcp:62420:46"/>in his own defence, and turned his
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to another ſubject. Whilſt they were ſpeaking, one of the
Queens Maids that was my Friend, and <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>'s Woman, was by
chance ſo near the Bed, that ſhe over-heard all that the Queen and Prince
ſaid about me: She was ſo ſurpriſed, and ſo penſive to find out
what might be the cauſe of ſo great a change in the Prince, that I came
into the Room, and began to ſpeak to her before ſhe perceived me: I Laughed
at her for her thoughtfulneſs: You ought to thank me for it, ſaid ſhe, I
heard juſt now a thing that amazes me ſo much, that I cannot well
comprehend it: <hi>Elvire,</hi> (for that was her name) then told me what ſhe
had heard, and amazed me much more than ſhe had been; I made her tell it me
over once more: As ſhe made an end, the Queen went out and interrupted our
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; I went out with her, and being not in a condition to remain
with the Prince, I walked by my ſelf in the Garden of the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, to make
reflections upon ſo ſtrange an adventure.</p>
               <p>It could not enter into my imagination, that a Prince that
always uſed me ſo well, would cauſe me to be Baniſhed without ſome
cauſe; I could not comprehend what ſhould induce him to wiſh my
abſence; I could <pb n="77" facs="tcp:62420:46"/>not gueſs what ſhould make him
profeſs a kindneſs for me, when he had none; nor could I believe that what
I was told could be true, nor that Don <hi>Garcias</hi> could be ſo weak as
to conſent to my Baniſhment: As I loved him paſſionately, his change
pierced me unto the very ſoul; and being not able to endure what I
ſuffered, I went to look out Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> to have the ſatisfaction
to make my complaint to him.</p>
               <p>As I was going towards the Pallace, I met one of the Officers of
Don <hi>Garcias</hi>'s Chamber, whom I had placed with the Prince, and who was
nearer to his perſon than any other. I bid him to go ſee if Don
<hi>Ramires</hi> was not with the Prince, and to pray him to come to me
preſently; this Officer made anſwer that he was not there, and that,
without doubt, he would not come thither until his accuſtomed hour, when
every body elſe was retired. I was extreamly aſtoniſhed at theſe words;
I thought at firſt I had not well underſtood them, yet I was ſenſible
enough of them: Many things came into my mind, that made me ſuſpect, that
Don <hi>Ramires</hi> had ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with the Prince, more than he
ever told me; at another ſeaſon I ſhould not have ſuch a thought, but
what I had heard of Don <hi>Garcias</hi>'s diſloyalty, obliged me to 
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62420:47"/>believe that all the world might be falſe: I asked this
Officer, if Don <hi>Ramires</hi> came often to Don <hi>Garcias,</hi> when none
elſe was there: He told me, he wondered I ſhould ask him ſuch a
queſtion, and that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved I knew well enough both their meetings and
the ſubject of their private diſcourſe; I replyed I knew neither, and
that I found it ſtrange he would not before then give me notice of it: He
thought I did but counterfeit my ignorance of all things, to diſcover whether
he told me truth or no; and to let me ſee that he could conceal nothing from
me, he told me the Princes Love for my Siſter, and what ſhare Don
<hi>Ramires</hi> had in the carrying it on; he told me he had often heard them
ſpeak of it when they thought none was in hearing; and they learnt all the
reſt from him that was intruſted to carry the Princeſs Letters to
<hi>Hermeneſilde;</hi> thus I underſtood all that paſſed, except what
concerned <hi>Nugna Bella.</hi> I need ſeek no more, cryed I, (tranſported
with rage) whence proceeds Don <hi>Garcias</hi>'s change; the Treachery he
commits againſt me, makes my preſence inſupportable to him. How! Don
<hi>Garcias</hi> Love my Siſter, my Siſter ſuffers it, and Don
<hi>Ramires</hi> is their Confident: At theſe words I ſtop'd, being
unwilling this Officer ſhould take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice <pb n="79" facs="tcp:62420:47"/>of my
reſentment, and forbid him to tell any body what he had informed me. I went
home ſo full of trouble, that I was beſide my ſelf: When I found my
ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, I abandoned my ſelf to my rage and deſpair; I was fifty
times in the mind to Stab the Prince and Don <hi>Ramires;</hi> I had all the
tranſports of Fury and Vengeance that the exceſs of rage can ſuggeſt:
At laſt, after recollecting my thoughts, to give my ſelf the time to
chooſe the fitteſt courſe for my revenge, I reſolved to fight Don
<hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires,</hi> and to perſwade <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> to go with me into
<hi>Caſtile,</hi> to obtain leave of her Father to Marry her; and as he had
the ſame deſign of revolting, as I had, to joyn with them and incourage
them to declare War againſt the King of <hi>Leon,</hi> and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow that
throne which Don <hi>Garcias</hi> was to aſcend; I fixed my reſolve upon
this determination, though it was contrary to all my thoughts untill that hour,
but my deſpair hurried me to it.</p>
               <p>I was to have waited upon <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> that very Night;
<hi>I</hi> expected the hour of going with great impatience, and the hope of
finding her ſenſible of my Misfortune, was the only thing that could give
me all the ſolace <hi>I</hi> was capable of: As <hi>I</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to
go out, a Man that ſhe uſed to <pb n="80" facs="tcp:62420:48"/>keep, and often brought
me her Letters, came to me with one from her, and told me, that ſhe was very
ſorry ſhe could not ſee me that Night, for reaſons, <hi>I</hi> ſhould
read in her Letter: <hi>I</hi> told him it was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary
that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſpeak to her that Night, that <hi>I</hi> was going
to write her an Anſwer, and prayed him to ſtay; with that <hi>I</hi> went
into my Cloſet, opened <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>'s Letter, where <hi>I</hi> found
theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Letter.</head>
                     <p>I know not whether I ſhould return you thanks for the leave
you give, to ſhew Don <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſome regret for his departure; I
ſhould rather have been glad that you had forbid it me, that I might have a
reaſon not to do a thing that will give me ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint; though
you have ſuffered through the manner I was oblidged to uſe in entertaining
him ſince his return, I have ſuffered more than you; nor would you doubt of
it, if you knew how hard it is for me to tell a man, that I Love no more, that
I love him ſtill; when I am out of my Witts, that I ever Loved, and that I
would redeem with my Blood, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have pronounced, but for you, all thoſe
words which I muſt ſay to him: You will <pb n="81" facs="tcp:62420:48"/>know when he is
further off, all the injuſtice you do me, and the joy you ſhall ſee me to
have at his departure, will better perſwade you than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing. I can ſay.
<hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> is angry with the Prince, becauſe he yeſterday did
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain a perſon for a great while, for whom ſhe had already ſhewed
ſome Jealouſie, which was the reaſon ſhe went not along with the Queen
when ſhe had been at his Appartment, he muſt not tell her he knows any
thing of this, for I promiſed her to ſay nothing of it; ſhe ſo truly
Loves him, that my Letter was interrupted in this place by a thing that puts me
into a mortal fright. One of my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to day, heard all the Prince
ſaid to the Queen about <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> and told it him at that very
inſtant: She juſt now told me of it as a thing that doth both ſurpriſe
and afflict me: It is impoſſible but that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>
ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects that you have known ſomething of the Princes deſignes, and
will find out a great part of the truth; conſider what miſchief that may
do; this accident troubles me to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree that I know not what I do: I am
go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to write to him that I cannot ſee him to Night, for I cannot expoſe
my ſelf to ſpeak to him, before you have ſeen him, and I know from you
what I muſt ſay to him; fare-well, Judge of my trouble.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:62420:49"/>I was in ſuch a paſſion after the
reading of this Letter, that I knew not what <hi>I</hi> ſaid, nor what
<hi>I</hi> did; my Anger was raiſed to the utmoſt pitch of rage and fury at
the diſcovery <hi>I</hi> had before made of ſo many Treacheries, but they
were weak and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderble to what chance had laid before me. <hi>I</hi>
ſtood without ſpeech or motion, and remained ſo for a long time; my
thoughts were confuſed; my underſtanding was oppreſſed with weight of
grief.</p>
               <p>You are then Unfaithful <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> cryed <hi>I</hi>
of a ſuddain; you joyn to your inconſtancy the injury of deceiving me, and
you conſent <hi>I</hi> ſhould be betray'd by thoſe <hi>I</hi> loved above
all the World, next your ſelf; it is too much Cruelty at one time; my
misfortunes are of the nature, that it were leſs ſhame to be overwhelmed by
them, than to reſiſt them. <hi>I</hi> yield to the Cruelty of the moſt
unfortunate chance that ever perſecuted man; <hi>I</hi> had both the force
and the deſign to be revenged of an Ungrateful Prince, and an unfaithful
Friend; but <hi>I</hi> have neither againſt <hi>Nugna Bella, I</hi> thought
my ſelf more happy in her than in all the World beſides: But ſince ſhe
forſakes me, <hi>I</hi> am indifferent to all things elſe, and <hi>I</hi>
renounce all thoughts of a revenge that can bring me no ſatisfaction:
<hi>I</hi> was not <pb n="83" facs="tcp:62420:49"/>long ſince, the firſt man of all the
King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by my Fathers and my own proper Grandeur, and by the favours of the
Prinde, believed my ſelf well beloved by thoſe whom <hi>I</hi> moſt
eſteemed: Fortune forſakes me, <hi>I</hi> am abandoned by my Maſter,
<hi>I</hi> am deceived by my Siſter, <hi>I</hi> am betray'd by my Friend,
<hi>I</hi> loſe my Miſtreſs, and <hi>I</hi> loſe her by the contrivance
of that Friend? Is it poſſible, <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> that you ſhould
leave me for Don <hi>Ramires?</hi> Is it poſſible that Don <hi>Ramires</hi>
ſhould deſire to take you from a man that loved you ſo paſſionately,
and had ſo great a kindneſs for him? Muſt you two joyn to rob me of one
another, and not leave me the poor conſolation of one of you, to whom
<hi>I</hi> might make my moan.</p>
               <p>Such cruel reflections took from me the uſe of my reaſon,
the leaſt of thoſe misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes that fell upon me in that one day, was able
to torment me mortally: This great number of ſad accidents, put me out of my
ſenſes, <hi>I</hi> knew not which of them <hi>I</hi> ſhould complain of
moſt: He that brought the Letter from <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> ſent to tell me
that he ſtaid for my Anſwer; <hi>I</hi> waked as it were out of a Dream at
this meſſage, and ſent him word <hi>I</hi> would ſend an Anſwer the
next day, and gave order none ſhould come to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:62420:50"/>I again began to reflect upon my former
condition, ſo cruel an experience had <hi>I</hi> of the inconſtancy of
Fortune, and the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of Men, inſpired me with the deſign of
renouncing for ever to all worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and go to end my Life in ſome
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more Deſart; my grief ſuggeſted to me, that <hi>I</hi> had no other
choyce to make: <hi>I</hi> had no where to go but to my Father; <hi>I</hi> knew
the deſign he had of taking Arms, but for all my deſpairs, <hi>I</hi> could
not reſolve to revolt againſt a King that had never done me wrong: If
<hi>I</hi> had only been forſaken by Fortune, <hi>I</hi> ſhould take a
delight to reſiſt her, and to make it appear <hi>I</hi> deſerved what
ſhe had given me. But after having been deceived by ſo many perſons whom
<hi>I</hi> ſo paſſionately loved, and of whom <hi>I</hi> thought my
ſelf ſo aſſured, what was there left me? Could <hi>I</hi> ever ſerve
a Maſter better, or more faithful than <hi>I</hi> did Don <hi>Garcias?</hi>
Could <hi>I</hi> ever love a Friend better than <hi>I</hi> did Don
<hi>Ramires?</hi> Or could <hi>I</hi> be more in love with a Miſtreſs than
<hi>I</hi> was with <hi>Nugna Bella?</hi> and yet they have all betrayed me,
<hi>I</hi> have nothing left but a reſolute retreat to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw my ſelf
from the deceit of men, and the dangerous charms of Women.</p>
               <p>As <hi>I</hi> was reſolving upon this courſe, <hi>I</hi>
ſaw coming unto my Cloſet Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> 
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:62420:50"/>a
perſon of quality and worth, who always applyed himſelf to me; he was
Brother to that <hi>Elvire,</hi> who gave me notice of the Princes betraying
me, and had learnt from her juſt then what the Prince had ſaid to the
Queen; he was much ſurpriſed to read in my face the marks of ſo great an
agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and extream trouble of mind; he knew me too well to think that
Fortune alone could ſo much diſcompoſe me; nevertheleſs, he believed
that <hi>I</hi> was grieved at the Princes infidelity, and began to uſe
Arguments to alienate my trouble: <hi>I</hi> alway had an eſteem for Don
<hi>Olmond,</hi> and ſerved him upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral occaſions, although
<hi>I</hi> always prefer'd Don <hi>Ramires</hi> before him. The ingratitude of
this latter, made me ſenſible of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice <hi>I</hi> did therein to
Don <hi>Olmond:</hi> To make him amends, or rather to have the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
of complaining of my Misfortunes, <hi>I</hi> told him the condition <hi>I</hi>
was in, and all the Treacheries that had been committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: He could
not chuſe but be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at it, but not ſo much as <hi>I</hi> expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of
<hi>Nugna Bell</hi>'s infidelity; for he told me that his Siſter, when ſhe
had informed him of the Princes Infidelity towards me, that <hi>Nugna
Bella</hi> was without doubt chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that ſhe concealed many things
from me: Behold, Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> ſaid <hi>I,</hi> ſhewing 
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62420:51"/>him <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>'s Letter, her change, and ſee
what ſhe has conceal'd from me; ſhe ſent me this inſtead of that ſhe
intended for me, and it is eaſie to judge that this was meant for Don
<hi>Ramires.</hi> Don <hi>Olmond</hi> was ſo concern'd to ſee me in that
condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and my Misfortunes ſeemed to him ſo great, that he would not
undertake to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole with me, but thought it beſt to leave me to eaſe my
ſorrow by my complaints. Had not <hi>I</hi> reaſon, ſaid I, to deſire
to know <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> well, before I ſhould ingage my heart to love
her; but I find I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to an impoſſibility, there is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving into
a Womans heart, they are ever Strangers to themſelves; it is opportunity
alone that can decide the controverſie of their diſagreeing thoughts.
<hi>Nugna Bella</hi> believed ſhe Loved me, but it was my Fortune and not me
ſhe loved; and perhaps ſhe loves only that in Don <hi>Ramires:</hi>
Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs (cryed I) ſhe has ſaid nothing to me this great while, but
what he gave her leave to ſay, it was to my Rival I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the change
he cauſed in her; he ſpoke to her for himſelf, when I believed he ſpoke
for me: Is it poſſible they ſhould make me the object of their deceit?
How have I deſerved this from them? That per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious Man betray'd me with
<hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> 
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:62420:51"/>as he did with Don <hi>Garcias:</hi>
I confided my Siſter to their care, and they betray'd her to the Prince; this
conſent and union <hi>I</hi> found in them, which gave me much
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, was but a blind to deceive me. O God (cryed <hi>I</hi>) for
whom do you reſerve your Thunder-bolts, unleſs it be for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo
unworthy to live?</p>
               <p>After this violent tranſport of my grief, the Idea of
<hi>Nugna Bella</hi> unfaithful, which left me nothing but indifference for all
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther misfortunes, put me into a ſadneſs full of diſpair; I acquainted
Don <hi>Olmond</hi> with my reſolution of leaving all things; he was
ſurpriſed at it, he did what he could to diſwade me from it; but
<hi>I</hi> let him ſee that my reſolutions were ſo fixt, that he thought
it to no purpoſe to oppoſe them, at leaſt in their firſt impetuoſity.
<hi>I</hi> took all my Jewels, and we got on Horſeback, that we might get out
of my Houſe; before the King's Order for my departure could reach me; we rid
untill Sun-riſing: Don <hi>Olmond</hi> lead me to a Houſe of one of his
Servants, in whom he had great confidence; <hi>I</hi> pray'd him to leave me in
that place, until Night, that <hi>I</hi> might take my Journey to the place
whither <hi>I</hi> reſolved to go: After along con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt he promiſed to
leave me, provided <hi>I</hi> would not quit that place until he returned; 
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62420:52"/>that in the mean time he would go to <hi>Leon,</hi> to know
what effects my departure had wrought, that perhaps ſome alteration might
have happened that might divert me from my ſad reſolution: He earneſtly
beſought me to expect his coming, <hi>I</hi> conſented, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition he
ſhould tell none that he ſaw me, nor knew where <hi>I</hi> was: Yet though
<hi>I</hi> conſented, it was rather out of an unvoluntary Curioſity, to
know after what manner <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> ſpoke of me, then that there
could happen any thing that might leſſen my Misfortunes.</p>
               <p>Go my dear <hi>Olmond</hi> (ſaid <hi>I</hi>) ſee <hi>Nagna
Bella,</hi> and if it be poſſible, know from your Siſter what her
thoughts are; endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to learn, ſince what time ſhe ceaſed to Love me,
and if ſhe has abandoned me only becauſe Fortune forſook me; Don
<hi>Olmond</hi> aſſured me that he would do what I deſired. Two days
after he returned with a ſadneſs, that gave me to underſtand he had
nothing to ſay to me that might oblige me to change my deſign.</p>
               <p>He told me all were ignorant of the cauſe of my departure,
that the Prince as well as Don <hi>Ramires</hi> ſeemed to be much afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
at it; that the King believed I was gone, with his Sons private conſent, and
of intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence with him: He told me he ſaw his <pb n="89" facs="tcp:62420:52"/>Siſter, that all I believed was true; that the recital of the
particulars would but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my grief, and therefore deſired to be
excuſed from the telling it. I was not in a condition to fear the increaſe
of my Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes; and what he would have conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was the only thing that
could give me ſome curioſity; I prayed him therefore to hide nothing from
me; I will not repeat all he told me, becauſe I have already told you the
moſt part, to put my Narrative in ſome order: It was from him I learnt all
thoſe things (of which I was ignorant) while they were tranſacting, as you
might judge. I will only tell you that his Siſter informed him that the Night
before my departure, as ſhe came back from the Queen, where <hi>Nugna
Bella</hi> had not appeared that Night, ſhe went to <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>'s
Chamber, where ſhe found her all bathed in her tears, with a Letter in her
hand, that they were both ſurpriſed but for different reaſons, that In
fine, <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> after a long ſilence, ſhut the Door, and told
her that ſhe would truſt her with all the ſecrets of her Life, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
her to pitty her, and comfort her in the ſaddeſt condition that ever poor
Maid was reduced to; that then ſhe diſcovered to her all that had
paſſed betwixt the Prince Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> my Siſter, and her,
juſt as I <pb n="90" facs="tcp:62420:53"/>told you; and that Don <hi>Ramires</hi> had
juſt then ſent her back this Letter which ſhe held in her hand, becauſe
it was not for him, but intended for me, and that I had received that Letter
ſhe meant for Don <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires,</hi> that by that Letter I had found out all
that ſhe had concealed from me for ſo long time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elvire</hi> told her Brother that ſhe never ſaw any
perſon ſo afflicted and troubled as <hi>Nugna Bella:</hi> She apprehended
that I ſhould acquaint the King with the intregue that was betwixt the Prince
and my Siſter, and that I would cauſe Don <hi>Ramires</hi> and her to be
Baniſhed from the Court, that above all things ſhe feared the ſhame of my
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and that the Treacheries ſhe had committed againſt me, made
her hate me mortally.</p>
               <p>You may well think, that what I came to learn of Don
<hi>Olmond,</hi> would no way leſſen my diſpleaſures, nor make me
change my intention. He preſſed me with all the earneſtneſs imaginable,
and all the marks of an extraordinary Friendſhip, to let him go along with me
to the Deſert I intended to go to: I oppoſed it ſo ſtrongly, that at
laſt we ſeparated; he left me upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that in what part of the
World ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I ſhould be, I ſhould oblige my ſelf to write to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:62420:53"/>He returned to <hi>Leon,</hi> and I parted
with deſign to Embarque my ſelf at the firſt Port I ſhould come to. But
when I was alone, left to the reflections of my Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, the remainder of
my days appeared ſo tedious to me, that I reſolved to go ſeek my Death in
the Wars that the King of <hi>Navar</hi> had againſt the <hi>Moores; I</hi>
would be known by no other name but by that of <hi>Theodirick,</hi> and I was
unhappy enough to acquire ſome glory which I did not look for, inſtead of
that death which <hi>I</hi> ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: The Peace was concluded,
<hi>I</hi> reaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed my former deſign, and your re-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter made me
change that diſmal Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, whither <hi>I</hi> intended to go, into a
moſt pleaſant retreat. There <hi>I</hi> began to find that quiet and
tranquility which <hi>I</hi> had loſt, not but that Ambition has been buſie
ſometimes to tempt my heart, but what <hi>I</hi> had already taſted of the
inſtability of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, render'd it contemptible to me; and the Love
<hi>I</hi> had born <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> was ſo totally blotted out of my
heart by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt <hi>I</hi> conceived for her, that <hi>I</hi> might
juſtly ſay, <hi>I</hi> had no Paſſion for any kind of thing, although
<hi>I</hi> had yet a great deal of Sadneſs left in me; the ſight of
<hi>Zayde</hi> has raviſhed from me that ſad tranquility which <hi>I</hi>
enjoyed, &amp; hurryes me into new Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, <pb n="92" facs="tcp:62420:54"/>much more
cruel than thoſe <hi>I</hi> have already experimented.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſo</hi> remained both Surpriſed and Charm'd with
Don <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s ſtory; <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs (ſaid he) that
<hi>I</hi> had conceived a large Idea of your Merits and Virtues, but
<hi>I</hi> muſt acknowledge that what I have now heard, ſurpaſſes my
former thoughts: <hi>I</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought to fear (replyed Don
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) that <hi>I</hi> have leſſened the good opinion you had
of me, by letting you ſee how eaſie <hi>I</hi> was to be deceived; but
<hi>I</hi> was young, <hi>I</hi> was ignorant of the Court-Artifices,
<hi>I</hi> was incapable of practiſing to them: <hi>I</hi> never Loved any
but <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> and the Love <hi>I</hi> had for her would not let me
imagine that that kind of Paſſion could ever have an end, ſo that nothing
could lead me to a diffidence neither of Friendſhip nor of Love. You could
not defend your ſelf, replyed Don <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> from deceit, unleſs
you had been of a ſuſpicious Nature, and yet your ſuſpicions (though
never ſo well grounded) would ſeem to your ſelf unjuſt, ſince you had
not until then any cauſe given you of diffidence againſt any that might
deceive you; and their deceit was carryed on with ſo much Art, that there was
no appearance in reaſon of a fallacy: Let us ſpeak no more of my paſt
Misfortune (replyed <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi>) <pb n="93" facs="tcp:62420:54"/>ſince I am no
longer ſenſible of them. <hi>Zayde</hi> has taken from me, even the
remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, and I wonder how I could call them to mind: But I could
never believe that Beauty alone could make me in Love, nor be ſmitten by one
that had other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingagements; and yet I adore <hi>Zayde,</hi> to whom I am
ſo much a Stranger, that I know nothing of her, but that ſhe is
hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and that her heart bleeds for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Since I was deceived
in the opinion I had of <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> whom I knew, what can I expect
from <hi>Zayde,</hi> whom I do not know? But what ſhould I expect, or what
pretenſions can I have upon <hi>Zayde?</hi> She is utterly unknown to me;
Chance threw her upon this Coaſt; ſhe is impatient to be gone; I cannot
keep her againſt her Will, without being both unjuſt and unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. Though I
ſhould detain her, what ſhould I be the better for it, I ſhould ſee her
every day bewailing the abſence of a Man that ſhe Loves, and remembring him
as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as ſhe looks upon me. Ah, <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> what a miſchief is
Jealouſie? Ah, Don <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> you had reaſon, that is the only
paſſion that ſurpriſes us, and ſtrikes us of a ſuddain; all the
other Paſſions are but Chains, by which we ſuffer our hearts willingly to
be drawn away; all true inclinations plucks it <pb n="94" facs="tcp:62420:55"/>from us in
ſpight of us, and the Love I have for <hi>Zayde</hi> is a torrent that draggs
me, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaving me the leaſt power of reſiſting. But
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I make you ſpend the Night here in entertaining you with
my ſorrowes, it is but reaſon I ſhould let you now take your reſt.</p>
               <p>After theſe words Don <hi>Alphonſo</hi> went to his Chamber,
and Don <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> paſſed the reſt of the Night without
ſleeping one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The next day <hi>Zayde</hi> ſeemed to be taken up
with the deſire of finding out what ſhe had already ſought after, but all
her endeavours were to no purpoſe; <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> never parted from
her, he forgot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every moment that ſhe could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand him;
he asked her the cauſe of her grief, with the ſame reſpect and
cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, and fear of diſpleaſing her, as if ſhe had
underſtood what he ſaid: When he recollected himſelf, and had the
diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſeeing ſhe could return him no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he thought to
comfort himſelf by ſaying to her all that his Paſſion could
ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Love you fair <hi>Zayde</hi> (ſaid he) looking
ſtedfaſtly upon her; <hi>I</hi> Adore you; <hi>I</hi> have at leaſt, the
ſatisfaction to tell you ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offending you; all your actions tell
me that none durſt declare it without incurring <pb n="95" facs="tcp:62420:55"/>your
diſpleaſure, but that Lover, for whom you weep, has ſpoken to you
(without doubt of his Love, and you have uſed your ſelf to hear him: How
many doubts might you reſolve me, fair <hi>Zayde,</hi> in one word?</p>
               <p>When he ſpoke to her in this manner, ſhe turned her ſelf
ſometimes toward <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime</hi> with aſtoniſhment, as it were to make
her take notice of a reſemblance, which always ſurpriſed her: This was
ſo piercing a ſmart for Don <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to imagine that he put her
in mind of his Rival, that he would with all his heart renounce the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages
of his Beauty and good mean, to be rid of ſuch a reſemblance: This trouble
was ſo inſupportable to him, that he could hardly reſolve with himſelf
ever to ſee <hi>Zayde</hi> more, he had rather deprive himſelf of her
ſight, than to repreſent to her the Image of him ſhe Loved; and her looks
ſeemed ſo favovrable to him, he could not indure them, he was ſo
perſwaded that they were not addreſſed to him; he would leave her, and
ſpend whole Afternoons in the Woods, When he returned to her, he found her
more angry than ſhe uſed to be; he fancied conſequently, that he ſaw
ſome inequality in her behaviour towards him; but as he could not gueſs at
the cauſe, he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined <pb n="96" facs="tcp:62420:56"/>that the diſpleaſure of being
in an unknown place, cauſed the alterations that appeared in her humour;
nevertheleſs he perceived that the Affliction ſhe was in the firſt dayes
of her abode there, begun to leſſen. <hi>Felime</hi> was more Afflicted
than <hi>Zayde,</hi> but her ſadneſs was always alike; ſhe ſeemed to be
over-whelmed with grief, and endeavoured to be alone, to entertain her ſelf
with her ſad thoughts. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> took notice of it ſometimes to
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> with amazement, and he wondered that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of her
Melancholly did not tarniſh her Beauty. In the mean time all Don
<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi>'s ſtudy was to pleaſe <hi>Zayde,</hi> and to give her
all the Divertiſements that Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Hunting, and Fiſhing could furniſh;
and ſhe buſied her ſelf in all that could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert her; ſhe ſpent her
time, for ſome dayes, in making a Bracelet of her Hair, and when ſhe had
finiſhed it, ſhe faſtened it about her Arm with that eagerneſs which
people have for a thing they have finiſhed: The ſame day that ſhe put it
on, ſhe let it fall by chance in the Wood: <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſeeing her
go out, went to follow her, and going along, he found this Bracelet, which he
eaſily knew again: He was extream glad to have found it, and his gladneſs
had been more compleat if he had received it <pb n="97" facs="tcp:62420:56"/>from the hands
of <hi>Zayde;</hi> but as he had no hopes of it, he thought himſelf happy to
owe it to Fortune. <hi>Zayde</hi> having miſſed it, was comeing back to
look for it in the places ſhe had paſſed; ſhe made ſignes to Don
<hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> what ſhe had loſt, and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be much afflicted
at it: Though he was in pain to cauſe her diſquiet, he could not reſolve
to part with a thing that was ſo precious to him; he made as if he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
for it too, and at laſt obliged her to leave off her unneceſſary
ſearch. As ſoon as he was gotten into his Chamber, he kiſſed this
Bracelet a thouſand times, and faſtened to it a buckle of Diamonds of great
value: Sometimes he went out to walk before <hi>Zayde</hi> was up, and when he
found himſelf in a place where he believed no body could ſee him, he would
untye this Bracelet the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to conſider it.</p>
               <p>One Morning, as he was thus buſie, ſitting upon a Beach that
ſomewhat advanced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea, he heard ſome body behind him; he turn'd
about on a ſuddain, and was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed to ſee it was <hi>Zayde:</hi>
All he could do was to hide the Bracelet, but not ſo cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verly, but that
<hi>Zayde</hi> perceived he had hid ſomething; he fancied ſhe ſaw what he
had hid, he obſerved ſo much coldneſs and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content in her looks,
that he did no longer <pb n="98" facs="tcp:62420:57"/>doubt, but that ſhe was angry with
him for not reſtoring her Bracelet; he durſt not look upon her, feating
leaſt he ſhould ſee her make ſignes to reſtore it her again, which he
could not reſolve to do: She ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſad and out of order, and without
look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> ſhe ſet her down, and turned her face
towards the Sea; the wind blew away a Vail ſhe had in her hand, unknown to
her; <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> roſe to take it up, but in riſing, he let fall the
Bracelet, which he could not tye again for fear of diſcovering it.
<hi>Zayde</hi> turned her head at the noyſe <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> made, ſhe
ſaw her Bracelet, and picked it up before <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> could turn that
way; but he was infinitely troubled when he ſaw it in her hand, both for his
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of loſing it, and for fear of her anger; nevertheleſs he took
courage, ſeeing no more anger nor diſcontent in her Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, he rather
fancied he ſaw ſomething of ſweet and pleaſant: He was no leſs moved
by the hope he conceived from <hi>Zayde</hi>'s countenance, than he was a
moment before, by his fear of having diſpleaſed her. She conſidered, with
attention, the luſtre of the Diamond Buckles that were faſtened to the
Bracelet; and after looking upon it a while, ſhe undid it, and gave it to
<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo,</hi> and put the Bracelet into her Pocket. <pb n="99" facs="tcp:62420:57"/>When <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſaw that <hi>Zayde</hi> returned him only
his Buckles, he turned himſelf to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sea, and threw them in with a
careleſs and melancholly ayre, as if he had let them fall in by chance.
<hi>Zayde</hi> cryed out, and advanced her body, to ſee if there were no
poſſibility of retrieving them, but he told her it was in vain to look
after them; and becauſe ſhe ſhould make no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reflection upon what
he had done, he offered her his hand, to lead her further from that place: They
walked without ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing to one another, inſenſibly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s Houſe, both of them ſo full of thoughts, that they
ſeemed to deſire to ſeparate.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> had conducted her to her
Chamber, he left her to think of his Adventure. Though <hi>Zayde</hi> did not
ſeem to him as Angry as he had apprehended, he believed that the joy of
finding her Bracelet had baniſhed her diſcontent; ſo that his
diſpleaſure was nothing leſs, though he had a great mind to have the
Bracelet; yet the fear of diſpleaſing <hi>Zayde</hi> kept him from asking
it, and left him oppreſſed with that kind of grief, which Love without
hope, gives; all his Conſolation was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Grievances to
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> and to blame himſelf for his weakneſs in being in Love
with <hi>Zayde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:62420:58"/>You are unjuſt (in your Accuſations)
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſelf, <hi>Alphonſo</hi> would ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to him. It
is not eaſie to defend ones ſelf in the middle of a Deſert, againſt the
force of ſuch a charming Beauty as <hi>Zayde:</hi> It is all you could be
able to do in a great Court, where other Beauties might make a diverſion, or
where Ambition, at leaſt, would claim a ſhare in your heart: But did any
Man ever Love without hope? Said <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> And how can I hope to be
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, ſince I cannot ſo much as ſay I Love? How ſhall I be able to
perſwade it, ſince I cannot utter it? which of my actions ſhall be
convincing enough to induce <hi>Zayde</hi> to believe I Love her in a place
where I ſee none but her ſelf, and where I cannot make her ſenſible I
prefer her before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? How ſhall I baniſh out of her mind what
ſhe Loves? by no other means but by her good liking of my Perſon: But my
Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune has contrived it ſo, that the ſight of my face preſerves in
her the memory of her Lover. Ah my dear <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> flatter me not;
nothing but meet folly could make me in Love with <hi>Zayde;</hi> and ſo much
in Love, as to make me even forget that I was once before in Love, and was
abuſed in it. I am of opinion (replyed <hi>Alphonſo</hi>) that you were
never in Love before now, ſince you <pb n="101" facs="tcp:62420:58"/>knew not what
Jealouſie was, but ſince you Loved her. I had no cauſe of being Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
of <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> ſo well ſhe knew
how to deceive me. When a Man is ſeriouſly in Love, ſaid
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> he is Jealous without cauſe; you ſee it by experience
in your ſelf: make but a little reflections upon the diſquiet that
<hi>Zayde</hi>'s tears does create you, and mark how Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie has put it
into your head, that ſhe laments the loſs of a Lover, and not that of a
Brother. I am but over-perſwaded, (replyed <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) that I Love
<hi>Zayde</hi> much more than ever I did <hi>Nugna Bella;</hi> the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of
this laſt, and her Application to the Princes intereſt, often abated of my
Love. All that I find in <hi>Zayde,</hi> oppoſite to my Love, for example to
believe, that ſhe Loves another, and neither to know her heart nor her
thoughts, cannot leſſen my Paſſion for her. But <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> am
not I a Mad-man to Love <hi>Zayde</hi> much more than ever I did <hi>Nugna
Bella;</hi> the ſucceſs of the Love I bore <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> was, I
muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, too cruel; yet every Man that is in Love, may have the like:
There was no folly in Loving her; I knew her, &amp; ſhe was in Love with no
body elſe; I was acceptable to her, I might have Marryed her. But <hi>Zayde,
Alphonſo.</hi> But <hi>Zayde,</hi> Who is ſhe? <pb n="102" facs="tcp:62420:59"/>What
can I pretend in her? Does not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry circumſtance elſe but her
incomparable Beauty, condemn me of madneſs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> did often entertain <hi>Alphonſo</hi> with
ſuch like diſcourſes: In the mean time his Love increaſed daily; he
could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain letting his eyes ſpeak after ſuch a charming manner,
that he believed he ſaw by thoſe of <hi>Zayde,</hi> that their Language was
underſtood; he ſound her ſometimes in a kind of ſurpriſe that
confirmed him in this belief: She could not make her ſelf to be underſtood
by her words, it was generally by her looks that ſhe made <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend part of what ſhe would ſay; but there was ſomething ſo
paſſionate and ſo charming in her looks, that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was all
inflamed by them. Fair <hi>Zayde,</hi> he would ſay ſometimes, If thus you
look upon thoſe you do not Love, What do you reſerve for that happy Lover,
of whom, I am ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy as to put you in mind? If he had not been
poſſeſſed with theſe thoughts, he would not believe himſelf ſo
unfortunate, not would the actions of <hi>Zayde</hi> perſwade him that he was
indifferent to her.</p>
               <p>One day, having left her for a while, be went to walk upon the
Beach, and came back again to a Fountain that was in a pleaſant part of the
Wood, where ſhe uſed <pb n="103" facs="tcp:62420:59"/>to go very often: As he came near
it, he heard ſome noiſe, and he ſaw through the Boughs, <hi>Zayde</hi>
ſitting by <hi>Felime;</hi> the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, occaſioned by this
rencounter gave <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> as much joy, as if Fortune had brought him
again to the ſight of <hi>Zayde</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a whole years abſence: He
approaches to the place where they were, and although he made a noiſe in
walking, they talked with ſo much attention, that they did not hear him. When
he was come before her, ſhe ſeemed no leſs concerned than a perſon that
had ſpoken aloud in a place where ſhe was affraid to be over heard, and
forgotten that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> could not underſtand her: The agitation
this ſurpriſe had put her in, had in ſome meaſure added to the luſtre
of her Beauty: <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> having ſeated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf near her (being
no longer able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelf) threw himſelf of a ſuddain at her
feet, and ſpoke to her of his Love, in ſo paſſionate a manner, that
ſhe might eaſily know what he ſaid without underſtanding his Language;
and it was clearly ſeen by <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> that ſhe underſtood him
well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; ſhe Bluſhed, and having made a ſign with her hand, as if
ſhe would puſh him away, ſhe roſe with a cold kind of Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as if
ſhe would have him riſe from a place where he might be incommoded.
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> 
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:62420:60"/>happened to walk by in that very
inſtant; and ſhe went towards him, without ſo much as looking upon
<hi>Gonſalvo:</hi> He remained in that place without being able to riſe
from thence.</p>
               <p>Thus, ſaid he to himſelf, am I treated, when I am not looked
on as the picture of my Rival; but you turn your eyes towards me, fair
<hi>Zayde,</hi> after ſuch a manner as would charm and enflame the whole
World, when my Countenance puts you in mind of his. But if I do but preſume
to let you ſee that I Love you, you will not daigne to caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſo much
as an angry look upon me; for you think me unworthy of the leaſt glance of
your eye. If I could but make you ſenſible that I know you bewail a Lover,
I ſhould think my ſelf happy, and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my Jealouſie would be
ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged by the diſpleaſure you ſhould have to hear it.
Is it not for this, that I ſeem to you to be perſwaded that you love
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that I may have the ſatisfaction to be aſſured by your
ſelf, that you love no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Ah <hi>Zayde,</hi> my Revenge is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd,
and had rather give you opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſatisfie my Curioſity, than in the
leaſt give cauſe of offence.</p>
               <p>Being taken up with theſe thought, he ſteeres his courſe
towards the Houſe, to <pb n="105" facs="tcp:62420:60"/>leave the place where
<hi>Zayd</hi> was, and that he might be alone in a Gallery, where he uſed to
walk. He thought a long time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the means how to make <hi>Zayde</hi>
under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that he ſuſpected ſhe was in Love with ſome body elſe;
but it was not eaſie to find a way, nor could it be well brought about,
without the help of ſpeech. After he had wearied himſelf with thinking and
walking, he was going out of the <hi>Gallery,</hi> when a Painter, whom
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> employed to draw ſome Pictures, earneſtly begged of him
to view his work; <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> would have been glad to be excuſed; but
being unwilling to anger the Painter, he ſtood ſtill to look upon what he
was drawing. It was a large piece, wherein <hi>Alphonſo</hi> gave him order
to paint the Sea, as it appeared from his Windows, and to make it the more
pleaſant, he repreſented therein, a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; there appeared of one
ſide, Ships foundring in the mid'ſt of the Sea; and on the other ſide,
Ships daſhed againſt the Rocks: Men were ſeen, endeavouring to ſave
their Lives by Swiming; others alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy drowned, whoſe Bodyes were caſt
upon the Shore. This Tempeſt put <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> in mind of
<hi>Zayde</hi>'s Ship-wrack, and made him bethink him of a way to let her
underſtand what he thought of her Affliction: He told <pb n="106" facs="tcp:62420:61"/>the Painter, he muſt add ſome more Figures to thoſe that he had
already drawn; that he muſt in the firſt place, draw upon one of thoſe
Rocks (in the Picture) a young fair Lady, with her Body bending forward, over
the body of a Man ſtretched our dead upon the Shore; that he muſt paint the
La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy weeping as ſhe looked upon this dead body; that there muſt be another
Man drawn proſtrate at her feet, endeavouring to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her to remove
from this dead body; that this fair Perſon (without turning her eyes towards
him that ſpoke to her) puſhed him away from her with one hand, and with the
other wiped her Tears. The Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter undertook to draw <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s
fancy, and began preſently to deſign it: <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was well
pleaſed, and prayed him to work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it with all ſpeed, and ſo went out
of the Gallery; he went to find out <hi>Zayde,</hi> not being any longer able
(notwithſtanding his late diſpleaſure) to be ſeparated from her: But he
was informed, that at her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from walking, ſhe was gone to her Chamber;
and ſo he could get no ſight of her all the reſt of the day, for which,
he was much Afflicted, and apprehended that ſhe had deprived him of her
ſight on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to puniſh him, for preſuming to make her underſtand
what he had done. The <pb n="107" facs="tcp:62420:61"/>next day ſhe ſeemed to him more
ſerious than ſhe uſed to be; but the following dayes, he found her as
ſhe was accuſtomed to be.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the Painter went on to finiſh
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s deſign, which he with impatience expected: As ſoon as
it was made an end on, he led <hi>Zayde</hi> into the Gallery, as it were to
divert her, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her the Painter at work; he at firſt ſhewed her
all the places which were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy finiſhed; after, he made her conſider
with more attention that Sea-piece, upon which the Painter was yet at work; he
made her look upon that young Lady that lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the dead Man; and when he
ſaw that her eyes were fixed upon it, and that ſhe ſeemed to know that
Rock, whereon ſhe uſed to ſit ſo often; he took the Penſil out of the
Painter's hand, and writ the name of <hi>Zayde</hi> over the young Lady, and
that of <hi>Theodoric</hi> over the young Man that was upon his knees.
<hi>Zayd,</hi> at the reading of what he writ, Bluſhed; and having looked
upon him with eyes full of anger, ſhe took a Penſil and quite blotted out
that dead Man's Figure, of whom ſhe thought <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> believed to
be the ſubject of her Tears. Though he were ſenſible of the offence he
had given <hi>Zayde,</hi> yet he was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed <pb n="108" facs="tcp:62420:62"/>to ſee
her blot out the Man he thought ſo much beloved. Although this action of
<hi>Zayde</hi>'s might be judged rather an effect of her diſdain, than a
proof that ſhe lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no body; yet he found, that after the Love he had
profeſſed for her, ſhe did him the favour not to let him believe that
ſhe Loved any other; but the ſmall hope this belief gave him, could not
deſtroy ſo many cauſes of fear which he believed he had reaſon to
have.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that was no way prepoſſeſſed with
any Paſſion, made very different re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the actions of this fair
Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, from what <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s were. I find (ſaid he) that you
have no reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your ſelf unhappy; you are, without doubt,
Wretched, to have placed your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection upon a Perſon which in all
likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood you cannot Marry, but not in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you fancy your ſelf to
be; and all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances are deceitful, if you be not truly beloved of
<hi>Zayde:</hi> It is true (replyed <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi>) that if I ſhould
judge of her thoughts by her looks, I might flatter my ſelf with ſome hope:
But as I have told you, ſhe never looks upon me, but for that reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance,
which creates me ſo much Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. I know not, Anſwered
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all that you think, be true or no; but 
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62420:62"/>if I were in the place of him, you think ſhe laments, I
ſhould not be very well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that my reſemblance ſhould make her
look ſo kindly upon any man elſe, and it is impoſſible, that the Idea
of another man ſhould produce thoſe ſentiments which <hi>Zayde</hi> has
for you: It is very natural for Lovers to hope, if any of <hi>Zayde</hi>'s
actions did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready make him conceive any, <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s diſcourſe
confirm'd him in it; he begun to think that <hi>Zayde</hi> did not hate him,
for which, he was extream glad; but this glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was of no long
continuance, for he imagin'd, if ſhe were a little inclined towards him, he
ow'd it all to his Rivals; he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied, that having already loſt the Man
ſhe Loved moſt, ſhe had a favourable diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards another
that might be like him: His Love, his Jealouſie, and his Glory, could not be
ſatisfied with an Inclination which he did not firſt create, but it
proceeded only from that ſhe formerly had for another: He believed, that
although <hi>Zayde</hi> ſhould Love him, ſhe would only Love his Rival in
him: In fine, he ſaw he ſhould be wretched, though he ſhould be ſure to
be beloved: Notwithſtanding, he could not avoid being well pleaſed to ſee
in this fair Strangers manner of proceedings, an ayre very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that
ſhe had at firſt; and his <pb n="110" facs="tcp:62420:63"/>Paſſion for her was ſo
ſtrong, that let the marks of her Inclination proceed from what cauſes
ſoever, he could not chuſe but receive them with great tranſports.</p>
               <p>One day, it being very fair weather, ſeeing ſhe came not out
of her Chamber, he went in to know if ſhe would walk: She was writing; and
though he made a noiſe as he entred the Chamber, yet he came near her without
being perceived by her, and ſtood looking upon her as ſhe writ; ſhe
turned her head by chance, and ſeeing <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> ſhe Bluſhed,
and hid what ſhe had writ, with ſo much haſt, that it cauſed no ſmall
trouble in <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi> for he believed ſhe could not have ſo much
application, and be ſo much ſurpriſed for a Letter which had not
ſomething of miſtery in it: This thought put him upon the wrack; he
retires, and goes to find out <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> to reaſon with him an
adventure which gave him imaginations very different from thoſe he hitherto
had: Having ſought him a great while in vain, of a ſuddain, an impulſe of
Jealouſie made him return to <hi>Zadye</hi>'s Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; he enters, but found
her not there; ſhe was gone into a Cloſet where <hi>Felime</hi> uſed to
ſit: <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſaw a piece of writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten paper half folded, upon
the Table, he could not refrain taking it up; and opening <pb n="111" facs="tcp:62420:63"/>it, he made no queſtion, but that it was the ſame paper he had
ſeen <hi>Zayde</hi> write a little before; he found in it the Bracelet of
hair which ſhe had formerly taken from him; ſhe enters as he held the Paper
and Bracelet; ſhe advances towards him, as if ſhe meant to take them from
him: <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> retires a ſtep or two back, as it were, to view
them; but with a ſubmiſſive action, that ſeemed to beg her
permiſſion: <hi>Zayde</hi> made ſignes that ſhe would have them, but
with an ayre ſo full of authority, that it was impoſſible for a Man (as
much in Love as he) not to obey; he returned them into the hands of
<hi>Zayde,</hi> but with the greateſt regret imaginable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he
believed them deſigned for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: He was not able to command his
Paſſion, he goes abruptly out of her Room to his own, where he found
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> who came to him, having been told that he had been looking
for him. So ſoon as they were ſeated; I am far more unhappy my dear
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> (ſayes he) than I thought; that Rival, of whom I was ſo
Jealous, as dead as I believed him, certainly is not dead; juſt now I found
<hi>Zayde</hi> writing to him, and ſending him that Bracelet which ſhe took
from me; ſhe muſt needs have heard from him. There is certainly ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body
hid here, that muſt carry her Letters <pb n="112" facs="tcp:62420:64"/>to him. In fine,
all thoſe hopes of felicity, which I had are but imaginary, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
only from explicating <hi>Zayde</hi>'s actions wrong. She had reaſon to blot
out that dead Man, for whom I made her conceive that ſhe grieved: She knew
too well, that he (for whom ſhe wept) was not dead; ſhe was in the right,
to be angry to ſee that Bracelet in my hands, and to be over-joy'd when ſhe
got it again, ſince ſhe had made it for another. Ah <hi>Zayde!</hi> it is
cruelty to let me conceive any hope; for you have given me leave to hope, and
your fair eyes did no way forbid it me. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s grief was ſo
great, that he could hardly end theſe words. When <hi>Alphonſo</hi> had
given him time to recollect himſelf, he pray'd him to tell him how he came to
know all this; and whether <hi>Zayde</hi> had in a moment found out ways to
make her ſelf to be underſtood. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> told him what he had
ſeen, how <hi>Zayde</hi> was diſcompoſed when he had catched her Writing;
how he found the Bracelet in the ſame Letter ſhe had been writing, and how
ſhe took it from him; In fine, <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> added he, none can be
ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for an indifferent Letter: <hi>Zayde</hi> has no Commerce nor
affair here, ſhe can write of nothing with ſo much attention, but what
paſſes in her own heart, nor was it <pb n="113" facs="tcp:62420:64"/>to me that ſhe
was writing; and now what would you have me think of what I ſaw? I would not
(ſaid <hi>Alphonſo</hi>) have you think things, ſo unlikely, which
cauſes your ſo much diſquiet: Becauſe <hi>Zayde</hi> bluſhed when you
ſurpriſed her a writing, you believe ſhe writ to your Rival: For my part
I believe ſhe Loves you well enough, to bluſh eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time ſhe is
ſurpriſed with ſeeing you near her; perhaps ſhe writ what you ſaw,
only to divert her ſelf; ſhe would not let you have it, becauſe it would
availe you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſince you cannot underſtand it; and I declare, I am
not at all ſurpriſed that ſhe took her Bracelet from you; for though I am
perſwaded ſhe Loves you, I do believe her too diſcreet to give a Bracelet
of her hair to a man that is a mere Stranger to her.</p>
               <p>Nor can I comprehend what grounds you can have to believe that
ſhe intends to ſend them to another; we have ſcarce been from her ſince
her coming hither, no body has ſpoke to her, and even thoſe that might
ſpeak to her, underſtand her not; how then would you have it, that ſhe
has heard from that Lover which creates you ſo much Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, or ſend
to him? I confeſs to you, ſaid <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> that I do torment my
ſelf more than I need, but the incertainty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <pb n="114" facs="tcp:62420:65"/>I am
is inſupportable to me; the incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties of others are but ſmall, they
believe themſelves more or leſs beloved, and I paſs from the hope of
being beloved of <hi>Zayde,</hi> to the belief that ſhe loves another; not am
I ſure one moment, whether what I perceive by her, ought to make me hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py or
wretched: <hi>Alphonſo</hi> (ſaid he) you take a pleaſure in deceiving
me; ſay what you will, ſhe could write to no body but a Lover, and I
ſhould think my ſelf happy, if (after what I have ſeen) I had that
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, of which I complain, as of the greateſt of all evils.
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> gave him ſo many reaſons that his diſquiet was
ill-grounded, that at laſt he brought him in ſome meaſure to himſelf,
and <hi>Zayde,</hi> whom they found walking, fully confirmed him: She ſaw him
at a diſtance, and came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them with ſo much ſweetneſs, and with
ſuch obliging looks for <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> that ſhe diſſipated a part
of thoſe troubles which ſhe a little before gave him. The time which he
ſet to this fair Stranger for her departute, which was the ſame that the
great Veſſels uſed to part from <hi>Tarragona</hi> for <hi>Africk,</hi>
began to approach, which gave him mortal afflictions; he could not reſolve to
be inſtrumental in depriving himſelf of <hi>Zayde;</hi> and though he ſaw
it a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice <pb n="115" facs="tcp:62420:65"/>to detain her, he had need of all
his reaſon &amp; his vertue to keep him from it: How (ſaid he) to
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> ſhall I for ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive my ſelf of <hi>Zayde?</hi>
this will be a fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well without hopes of returning: I ſhall never know in
what part of the Earth to find her; ſhe is reſolved to go into
<hi>Africk,</hi> but ſhe is no <hi>African,</hi> and I know not in what part
of the world ſhe was Born.</p>
               <p>I will follow her <hi>Alphonſo</hi> (continued he); though in
following her, I do not hope for the happineſs of ſeeing her any more.
Though I know that neither her Vertue nor the Laws of <hi>Africa</hi> will
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to live with her, yet I am reſolved to go to end my ſad dayes in
the places of her abode; it will be at leaſt ſome comfort to me to breath
the ſame ayre ſhe does; happen what will, I am wretched, I have no certain
Country, Chance ſtaid me in this place, and Love will oblige me to leave it.
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſtill confirmed himſelf in this reſolution,
notwithſtanding all the pains <hi>Alphonſo</hi> took to diſſwade him
from it; he was more perplexed than ever, for not being able to underſtand
<hi>Zayde,</hi> nor be underſtood by her: He reflected upon the Letter he
ſaw her writing, and he fancied it was written in Greek Characters, though he
was not very certain of it: The deſire <pb n="116" facs="tcp:62420:66"/>he had to be
ſatisfied, made him think of going to <hi>Tarragon</hi> to find out
ſomebody that might underſtand the Greek tongue; he had already ſent
ſeveral times to find Strangers that might be his Interpreters, but as he was
ignorant what Language <hi>Zayde</hi> ſpoke, it was not eaſie to know of
what Nation he deſired to have; therefore the Journeys of all thoſe he had
ſent, proving ineffectual, he reſolves to go himſelf; and yet it was not
eaſie for him to take this reſolution, for he muſt have expoſed
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a great Town, to the hazard of being knovvn; and vvhat vvas more
irkſome, he muſt leave <hi>Zayde;</hi> but the deſire he had to be able
to explain himſelf to her, made him paſs over all difficulties; He
indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make her underſtand that he was going to fetch an
Interpreter, and ſo parted for <hi>Tarragon.</hi> He diſguiſed himſelf
as well as he could, he went into thoſe places which Strangers frequented; he
found a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but their Language was different from that which
<hi>Zayde</hi> ſpoke: At laſt he inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red if there were none that
underſtood the Greek tongue; he that he ſpoke to, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in
<hi>Spaniſh,</hi> that he was of one of the Iſles of <hi>Greece.
Gonſalvo</hi> pray'd him to ſpeak his Language, he did, and
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> knew that was <hi>Zayde</hi>'s Language: <hi>By</hi> good 
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:62420:66"/>fortune this Stranger had no great buſineſs to ſtay
him at <hi>Tarragon,</hi> he very willingly followed <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> who
gave him a greater reward than he durſt ask or hope for. They began their
Journey the next day very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> thought himſelf
more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in his Interpreter, than if he had the Crown of <hi>Leon</hi> upon
his head.</p>
               <p>As they went along, he begun to learn the Greek; the firſt
thing he learnt, was, <hi>I love you:</hi> When he thought that he could ſay
it to <hi>Zayde,</hi> and that ſhe ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him, he believed he
could be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger unhappy; he arrived betimes at <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe</hi>'s
Houſe, he found him walking, he made him partaker of his joy, and asked him
where <hi>Zayde</hi> was; <hi>Alphonſo</hi> told him that ſhe had been gone
out a good while to walk towards the Sea ſide: He haſtens thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his
Interpreter, he went ſtraight to the Beach where ſhe uſed to be; he was
ſurpriſed not to find her there, but he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected nothing; he walked
after her as far as the Port, whither ſhe was ſometimes uſed to go; he
came back to the Houſe; he went into the Wood, but all in vain; he ſent to
all the places where he thought ſhe might be; but when ſhe could not be
found, he began to have ſome fore-thoughts of his Misfortune: Night came on
without <pb n="118" facs="tcp:62420:67"/>any tidings of her, he was in diſpair to have
loſt her, he was afraid ſome ill accident had befallen her, he blamed
himſelf to have left her; in a word, there was no grief comparable to his, he
was all the Night with Flambeaus up and down the Fields, and even when he was
out of hopes to find her, he would not give over looking for her; he had been
already ſeveral times at the Fiſher-mens Hutts to know if none of them had
ſeen her, but could learn no news of her. About break of day, two Women that
were coming from a place where they lay all Night, told him, that as they came
out of their Cabbins, they ſaw <hi>Zayde</hi> and <hi>Felime</hi> walking by
the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, that the mean while a Shallop had put into the Shore, that
ſome Men Landed out of the Shallop; that <hi>Zayde</hi> and <hi>Felime</hi>
went back at the ſight of theſe Men; but being called by theſe men, they
came back to them, and that after having talked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a great while, and
ſhewed by their geſtures that they were glad to ſee them, they went all
into the Shallop together, and put to Sea.</p>
               <p>At this relation, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> looked upon
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> with an ayre that expreſſed his grief far better than
he could do with all his Eloquence. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> knew not what 
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:62420:67"/>ſay to him that might moderate his ſorrow; when all
thoſe that attended upon them were withdrawn, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> broke
ſilence, I loſe <hi>Zayde,</hi> ſaid he, and I loſt her in the very
inſtant that I was able to make my ſelf to be underſtood by her! I loſe
her <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> and it is her Lover that takes her from me, as may
eaſily be conjectured by what theſe Women ſay; cruel Fortune, thou
would'ſt not let me be ignorant of the only thing that could increaſe my
ſorrow for loſing <hi>Zayde!</hi> I have loſt her then for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhe
is now in the Armes of a Rival ſhe loves: It was to him, without queſtion,
ſhe was writing that Letter which I ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed; and it was to inform him
of the place where he ſhould find her. It is too much, cryed he of a
ſuddain, it is too much, my Afflictions are great enough to make thouſands
wretched at once; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I am too weak to bear them all; and after having
forſaken all things, I cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to be more tormented in the mid'ſt of
a Deſart, than I have been in the mid'ſt of a flouriſhing Court: It is
ſo <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> added he, the only loſs of <hi>Zayde</hi> has
poured down a thouſand Misfortunes upon me, far greater than any I have ever
yet felt; is it poſſible that I muſt never more hope to ſee
<hi>Zayde?</hi> If I knew, at leaſt, whether I <pb n="120" facs="tcp:62420:68"/>was
acceptable, or whether I was indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to her, my miſery would not be ſo
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable to me, and I ſhould know to what kind of Melancholly I
ſhould abandon my ſelf. If I was pleaſing to <hi>Zayde,</hi> how can I
think of forgetting her? ought not I to ſpend my dayes in running over all
the parts of the Earth until I find her; but if ſhe loves another, ought not
I to uſe all my endeavours to forget her for ever? <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> take
pitty of me, endeavour to make me believe that <hi>Zayde</hi> loved me, or
perſwade me that I am indifferent to her: How, ſaid he, ſhould I be
beloved of <hi>Zayde,</hi> and not endeavour to ſee her for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, that
Misfortune would be greater than being hated by her: But, no, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be
unhappy if <hi>Zayde</hi> loved me, Alas! I ſhould have found that out in
that very moment in which I loſt her; what-ever precaution ſhe had taken, I
ſhould have dived into her thoughts, I ſhould have known the cauſe of her
Tears, her Country, her Fortune, her Adventures, and I ſhould know now
whether I ought to follow her or no, and where to find her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſo</hi> knew not what to anſwer to
<hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> ſo hard it was to reſolve what to ſay that might
calme the violence of his ſorrow: At laſt, having repreſented to him, 
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62420:68"/>that he was not in a condition to determine any thing at
that inſtant, and that he muſt make uſe of his reaſon to ſupport his
Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, he obliged him to go along with him home. So ſoon as
<hi>Ganſalvo</hi> was in his Chamber, he cauſed his Interpreter to be
called to expound ſome words that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred to have heard <hi>Zayde</hi>
ſpeak; the Interpreter told him the meaning of many words, and among others,
thoſe which <hi>Zayde</hi> uſed to ſpeak to <hi>Felime</hi> when ſhe
looked upon him; he interpreted them ſo, as <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was ſure
that he was not miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; when he believed ſhe ſpoke of a
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, and he no longer doubted but that it was the Lover of
<hi>Zayde</hi> whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled. Upon this he ſends for thoſe Women
that had ſeen <hi>Zayde</hi> go away, to know of them, if among thoſe Men
that carryed her away, they had not obſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that was like him; there
was no ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his Curioſity, for theſe Women were at too great a
diſtance from them to mark any ſuch reſemblance; they told him only there
was one whom <hi>Zayde</hi> embraced. <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> was ſtruck to the
heart at theſe words, in ſo much, that he was upon the point of
precipitating himſelf into the deſign of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Zayde</hi> to kill
her Lover before her face. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> told him, that his deſign 
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:62420:69"/>was as unjuſt, and it was impoſſible, that he had no
juriſdiction over <hi>Zayde,</hi> that ſhe was engaged to this Lover before
ſhe had ſeen him; that he might be perhaps her Husband; that he knew not in
what part of the world to look for her; that if by chance he ſhould find her,
it was likely it muſt be in ſome Country where this Lover would have power
enough to hinder him from executing the enterpriſe which his rage prompted
him to. What would you have me do then, replyed <hi>Gonſalvo?</hi> can you
imagine it is poſſible for me to continue in the ſtate I am in? I could
wiſh you would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ear this
Misfortune which regards only your paſſion, as you have already ſupported
that which concerned your Love and your Fortune: I have ſuffered too much
already, Anſwer'd <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to be able to ſuffer any more; I
will go in queſt of <hi>Zayde,</hi> to ſee her, to know from her own mouth
that ſhe is in Love with another, and to dye at h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> feet; and yet I will not, for I
ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerve all my
Misfortunes, if I went to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> after
<hi>Zayde,</hi> after having left me as ſhe did, the reſpects and
ſubmiſſions I had for her, might have ingaged her at leaſt to ſend me
word ſhe was going to leave me, ſhe was bound in gratitude to have done it;
and ſince ſhe did not do it, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <pb n="123" facs="tcp:62420:69"/>that
ſhe adds contempt to her indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for me; I have flatter'd my ſelf too
much, when I fancied that ſhe did not hate me; I muſt never think of
following or looking after her; no <hi>Zayde,</hi> I will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you.
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I ſubmit to your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; I ſee I muſt pretend to
nothing elſe, but to end as ſoon as I can the remainder of a wretched
life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſeemed fixed in this reſolution, and his
mind was more calme; he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs in ſuch a deep Melancholly as
would draw pitty from all that ſaw him; he would ſpend whole dayes in the
places where <hi>Zayde</hi> uſed to be, and ſeemed to look for her there
ſtill: He kept his Interpreter with him to learn the Greek Tongue; and though
he was perſwaded he ſhould never more ſee <hi>Zayde,</hi> yet he took
delight in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring himſelf, that if ever it ſhould be his fortune to
ſee her, he ſhould be able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand her; he learnt in few days what
others are many years a learning; but when he had no longer this occupation,
which ſeemed to have ſome relation to <hi>Zayde,</hi> he fell into a deeper
Melancholly than ever.</p>
               <p>He made frequent reflexions upon the ſeverity of his
deſtiny, which after having over-whelmed him at <hi>Leon</hi> with ſo many
Misfortunes, made him now ſenſible of one <pb n="124" facs="tcp:62420:70"/>far greater
than all the reſt, in depriving him of the only perſon of the World, which
alone was dearer to him than the Fortune, the Friend, and the Miſtreſs
which he had loſt. In making this ſad difference betwixt his preſent and
his paſt unhappineſſes, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred him of a promiſe he made to Don
<hi>Olmond</hi> to write to him, and whatever dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty he found to think of
any thing but <hi>Zayde,</hi> he judged he owed this mark of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement
to a man that had ſhewed him ſo much Friendſhip; he would not let him
know preſently the place where he was, he only deſired him to write to him
to <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon,</hi> that his abode was not far from thence, that he found
himſelf void of all Ambition, that he bore no Anger againſt Don
<hi>Garcias,</hi> nor hatred for Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> nor love for <hi>Nugna
Bella,</hi> and yet he was more unfortunate than when he parted from
<hi>Leon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſo</hi> was very ſenſible of
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s condition, he ſeldom parted from him, and endeavor'd
all that he could to allienate his Affliction. You have loſt <hi>Zayde,</hi>
ſaid he to him one day, but you were no way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to her loſs; and
as unhappy as you are, there is one kind of unhappineſs which your Deſtiny
has kept you a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to, to be the occaſion of your own 
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:62420:70"/>wretchedneſs, is that evil which is yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to you,
and which for ever ſhall be my puniſhment. If you can find any
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation (continued he) to learn by my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that you might be more
unhappy than you are, I am willing to inform you of the accidents of my life,
whatever grief ſo ſad a Narrative may cauſe me. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> could
not chuſe but ſhew a great earneſtneſs to know the reaſons that had
obliged him to confine himſelf to a Deſert: Thereupon <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>
to ſatisfie his Curioſity, and to let him underſtand that he was leſs
wretched than himſelf, thus began the Hiſtory of his diſpleaſures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:62420:71"/>
               <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Alphonſo</hi> and
<hi>Bellaſire.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY Lord, you know my name is <hi>Alphonſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Xymenes,</hi> and that my Family is of ſome eſteem
in <hi>Spain,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of the firſt Kings of <hi>Navarre;</hi>
my deſign being only to acquaint you with the Hiſtory of my laſt
Misfortunes, I will not trouble you with that of my whole life, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there
be many remarkable paſſages in it; but ſince, from that time I intend to
ſpeak of, I have been unfortunate only by the fault of other people, and not
by my own, I will paſs it over in ſilence; you ſhall only know that I
have experimented all that the Infidelity, and the Unconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Women can
inflict of vexatious and troubleſome, in ſo much, that I had no ſtomack
to be in Love with any of the Sex; the commerce of Love ſeemed to me the
greateſt puniſhment, and though there were many handſome Women in the
Court, who might have a kindneſs for me, I had none for them, but only
thoſe ſentiments of reſpect which are due to their Sex. My Father, who
was yet alive, and had a great deſire to ſee me Marryed out of that 
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:62420:71"/>
                  <hi>Chimera,</hi> ſo ordinary to all man-kind to
propagate their name. I was not utterly averſe to Marriage, but the knowledge
I had of Women, made me reſolve never to Marry a handſome one; and having
been ſo much perplexed by Jealouſie, I was not willing to expoſe my
ſelf to the hazard of being plagued with that of a Lover and a Husband
together. I was in this diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when one day my Father told me that
<hi>Belaſire,</hi> the Daughter of the Count of <hi>Gueuarre</hi> was come to
Court, that ſhe was a conſiderable Match both by Birth and Fortune, and he
did heartily wiſh to have her for his Daughter-in-Law: I told him, his wiſh
was vain; that I had already heard ſpeak of <hi>Belaſire,</hi> and that I
knew none could ever pleaſe her yet; that I knew like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that ſhe was
very handſome, and that was enough to take from me all inclination to Marry
her. He asked me if I had ſeen her: I anſwered him, that every time ſhe
had been at Court, it was my Fortune to be in the Army, that I knew her only by
hear-ſay. Very well (replyed my Father) if I were as ſure that you would be
accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to her, as I am perſwaded that ſhe will make you change your
reſolution of never Marrying a handſome Woman, I ſhould not doubt of your
Marriage. Some <pb n="128" facs="tcp:62420:72"/>few dayes after, I found
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> with the Queen; <hi>I</hi> asked her name, ſuſpecting
it might be ſhe; and ſhe asked my name, believing alſo me to be
<hi>Alphonſo.</hi> We both gueſſed what we inquired after, and we told
one another ſo; we ſpoke to one another with more freedom than we ſhould
have done, or then is uſual in the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: I found the
perſon of <hi>Bellaſire</hi> very charming, and her Witt far beyond what I
thought it. I told her I was out of Countenance not to be better acquainted
with her, and for all that, that I ſhould be glad to know her no more than I
did; that I was not ignorant how vain it was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to pleaſe her, and
how hard a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was not to deſire it. I added, that as difficult a
thing as it was to make her ſenſible, I could not refrain from forming the
deſign; if ſhe ceaſed to be leſs hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but that while ſhe was
as I then ſaw her, I would never think more of her; nay more, I prayed her to
aſſure me that it was impoſſible to pleaſe her, fearing leaſt a
vain expectation ſhould make me change the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution I had taken, never
to ingage my ſelf in affection to any handſome Woman. This Converſation
that was ſomething ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, pleaſed <hi>Bellaſire;</hi> ſhe
ſpoke fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably enough of me, and I ſpoke of her <pb n="129" facs="tcp:62420:72"/>as
of a perſon in whom I found ſo much me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſo much agreeableneſs
above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Women: I made ſtricter inquiry after all thoſe that had
made their addreſſes to her, with more application than ordinary: I learnt
that the Count of <hi>Lare</hi> was deſperatly in Love with her, and that his
paſſion to her laſted a long time; that he was kill'd in the Army; that
he run headlong into dangers when he had loſt all hope of Marrying her: I was
told moreover, that many other perſons had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to win her favour,
but to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and that all people had given her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, becauſe they
thought it an impoſſible thing to thrive in their purſuit. I took no
ſmall delight in thinking of overcoming this impoſſibility; and for all
that I had no deſign to endeavour it. But I ſaw <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> as
often as I could poſſible; and as the Court of <hi>Navar</hi> is not ſo
ſtrict as that of <hi>Leon,</hi> it was not hard for me to find occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
of ſeeing her, and yet there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of ſeriouſneſs betwixt her
and me: I ſpoke to her, laughing at the diſtance that we were at, and of
the joy I ſhould have, if ſhe would change her face and her opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I
imagined that my Converſation was not unpleaſant to her, and that ſhe was
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with my Wit, becauſe ſhe found I knew the depth of hers:
Finding ſhe had a <pb n="130" facs="tcp:62420:73"/>Confidence in me, that gave me full
liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſpeak to her; I prayed her to tell me the reaſons why ſhe did
ſo obſtinately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject all thoſe that made their addreſſes to her. I
will tell you ſincerely (ſaid ſhe): I was born with a natural averſion
againſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, the tyes whereof have alwayes ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me very
harſh, and I believed that nothing but a paſſion ſtrong enough to blind
me, could make me tread underfoot all thoſe reaſons that ſeem to oppoſe
that engagement. You will not Marry for Love (ſaid ſhe) and for my part, I
cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend how any can reſolve to Marry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Love, and that a
very violent one; far from having a paſſion, I never had the leaſt
inclination for any Man. So that, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> if I am not Marryed, it
is becauſe I never Loved any Man well enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage me to it. How Madam
(Anſwered I) no man ever pleaſed you? Your heart has never received any
impreſſion, it has never been diſcompoſed at the ſight or mention of
thoſe that adored you? No (ſaid ſhe) I am utterly a Stranger to all the
impulſes of Love: How! And of Jealouſie too, ſaid I? I, and of
Jealouſie too, replyed ſhe. Ah Madam (ſaid I) if that be, I am
perſwaded that you never had any inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for any Man. It is true (ſaid
ſhe) that <pb n="131" facs="tcp:62420:73"/>no man ever pleaſed me; no, I never found
any bodyes humour agreeable, or any way like my own: I know not what effects
the words of <hi>Bellaſire</hi> wrought upon me; I know not whether
<hi>I</hi> was already in Love without knowing it: But the Idea of a heart like
hers, that never received any impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeemed ſo wonderful, and
ſo new to me, that <hi>I</hi> was in that very inſtant ſtruck with a
deſire to pleaſe her, to gain the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of touching a heart that all the
world believed inſenſible. <hi>I</hi> was no longer that Man that begun to
ſpeak without deſign: <hi>I</hi> ruminated upon all that ſhe had ſaid,
and believed that at the ſame time ſhe told me ſhe never found Man that
could pleaſe her; ſhe excepted me. In fine, <hi>I</hi> had hope e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to
compleat my intanglement, and from that moment <hi>I</hi> became more in Love
with <hi>Bellaſire</hi> than ever <hi>I</hi> had been with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny before:
<hi>I</hi> will not repeat to you how <hi>I</hi> took the freedom to declare my
paſſion to her; <hi>I</hi> began to ſpeak to her by a kind of Rallery,
for it was hard to talk ſeriouſly to her; and this Rallery gave me
occaſion to tell her things that <hi>I</hi> ſhould not have durſt to tell
of a long time, ſo that <hi>I</hi> was in Love with <hi>Bellaſire,</hi> and
was happy enough to touch her heart, though not ſo happy as to be able to
perſwade her that <hi>I</hi> Lov'd <pb n="132" facs="tcp:62420:74"/>her: She was
naturally diffident of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, though ſhe conſidered me far above all
thoſe that ſhe had ever ſeen, and by conſequence, more than I
deſerved, yet ſhe would not give credit to my words; but her manner of
proceeding with me, was different from that of all other Women, and I found
ſomething ſo noble and ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in her ways, that I was altogether
ſurpriſed at it: It was not long e're ſhe confeſſed to me the
inclination ſhe had for me; ſhe would tell me from time to time what
progreſs I made in her heart; and as ſhe concealed nothing from me that was
for my advange, ſo likewiſe ſhe told me what was againſt me; ſhe
would ſay, that ſhe could not believe that I Loved Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and that
ſhe would never conſent to Marry me untill ſhe was better ſatisfied of
my Love: I cannot expreſs the pleaſure I took in finding that I had made an
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon a heart that never was ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any before; and to
ſee the confuſion ſhe was in, to find her ſelf ingaged in a
paſſion, which till then, was altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to her: how charming it
was to me to know the aſtoniſhment <hi>Bellaſire</hi> was in being no
longer Miſtreſs of her ſelf, nor having any more power over her own
thoughts. I taſted in theſe beginnings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights <pb n="133" facs="tcp:62420:74"/>beyond my hope or imagination; and he that has not known the delight
of making a perſon violently in Love with him, that has never been
ſenſible of Love, may ſay ſhe never knew the true pleaſures of Love.
If I had great tranſports of pleaſure to find out the inclination
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> had for me, I was alſo in terrible anxieties for the
doubt ſhe was in of my paſſion for her, and the impoſſibility I ſaw
of perſwading her to believe it.</p>
               <p>When theſe thoughts diſturbed me, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call'd to mind the
opinion I had of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, I found I was going to precipitate my ſelf into
the misfortunes which I ſo much apprehended: I thought I ſhould have the
affliction of not being capable of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Bellaſire</hi> of the
paſſion I had for her, or that if I did convince her, and that ſhe
ſhould be truly in Love with me, I ſhould be expoſed to the Misfortune of
being no more beloved paſſionately. I ſaid to my ſelf, that Wedlock
would diminiſh the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhe had for me, and that ſhe would love
me no more than as far as duty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and that perhaps ſhe would Love
ſome body elſe: The horror of being Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous was ſo impetuous upon me,
that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the eſteem and paſſion I had for her, I had
almoſt reſolved to quit the <pb n="134" facs="tcp:62420:75"/>reſolution I had taken;
and I preferr'd the Misfortune of living without <hi>Bellaſire</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
that of enjoying her without being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of her. <hi>Bellaſire's</hi>
thoughts were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as diſtracted as mine, ſhe concealed nothing from
me, no more than I did from her; we debated the reaſons we had, not to engage
one anothers Affections; we ſeveral times reſolved to break off, and we
took leave of one another, with intention to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute our reſolutions, but
our <hi>Adieus</hi> were ſo tender, and our inclinations ſo ſtrong, that
we were no ſooner out of one anothers ſight, but we were contriving how to
ſee one another again. In fine, after many ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolutions on both ſides,
I at laſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all <hi>Bellaſires</hi> doubts, and ſhe clear'd all
mine; ſhe promis'd to conſent to our Marriage as ſoon as our Friends had
agreed upon all things that was requiſite for the conſummating thereof: Her
Father was forc'd to leave the Court before all things were concluded, for the
King commanded him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the Frontires to ſign a Treaty with the
<hi>Mores,</hi> and we were forc'd to wait his coming back: I was in the mean
time the happieſt Man in the World; the Love I bore <hi>Bellaſire,</hi>
took up all my thoughts, and ſhe loved me as paſſionately: I eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
her beyond all the Women in the world, <pb n="135" facs="tcp:62420:75"/>and believed my
ſelf upon the point of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing her.</p>
               <p>I enjoyed all the freedom that a Man that was ſoon to Marry
her could take. One day it was my Misfortune to pray her to tell me all that
her Lovers had done for her: I took delight to obſerve the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
betwixt her manner of proceeding with them, and that ſhe uſed with me. She
named me all thoſe that Loved her, ſhe told me what they had done to
pleaſe her; ſhe ſaid that thoſe that were moſt conſtant in their
purſuit, were thoſe ſhe leaſt cared for; and that the Count of
<hi>Lare,</hi> who Loved her to his death, was never accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to her. After
what ſhe had told me, (I know not for what reaſon) but I had a greater
curioſity to know what concern'd the Count <hi>de Lare</hi> than all the
reſt; his long perſeverance touch'd my imagination: I pray'd her once more
to repeat what paſſed betwixt them; ſhe did ſo, and though ſhe ſaid
nothing that could diſpleaſe me, I was ſeized with a Jealouſie; I
found, that although ſhe had ſhewed no inclination, ſhe had ſhewed a
great deal of eſteem for him; a ſuſpicion took me in the head, that ſhe
did not tell me all the ſentiments ſhe had for him; I would not let her
know what I thought, but retired home in a worſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour <pb n="136" facs="tcp:62420:76"/>than I uſed to be; I ſlept little, I could not reſt untill I
ſaw her again the next day, and made her tell over again all ſhe had told
me the day before, it was not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for her to tell me in an inſtant
all the circumſtances of a Paſſion that had laſted many years; ſhe
told me ſome things that ſhe had not thought on before, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
ſhe did it out of deſign of concealing them from me: I asked her a
thouſand queſtions, and I beg'd of her upon my knees to anſwer me with
ſincerity; but when, what ſhe anſwered was as I would have it, I thought
ſhe ſaid it only to pleaſe me; if ſhe ſaid any thing that was
advantagious for the Count of <hi>Lare,</hi> I thought ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed more
than ſhe would tell of him: In ſine, Jealouſie, with all the horrors that
accompany it, ſeized upon my underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; I afforded her no reſt, I
could no longer ſhew her either love or kindneſs; I could ſpeak of
nothing to her, but of the Count of <hi>Lare,</hi> and yet <hi>I</hi> was out
of my Wits for making her remember him, and recall to mind what he had done for
her ſake; I reſolved never more to ſpeak to her of him, but I alwayes
found that I had forgotten to make her explain her ſelf upon ſome
circumſtance or other. As ſoon as I had begun this diſcourſe, I was as
it were <pb n="137" facs="tcp:62420:76"/>in a maze, I could never get out of it, and my
affliction was equally great in ſpeaking of the Count <hi>de Lare,</hi> or
not ſpeaking of him.</p>
               <p>I paſſed whole Nights without ſleep, <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſire</hi>
was no more to me the ſame perſon: How, ſaid <hi>I,</hi> what was the
charm of my paſſion? Was it not the belief I had that <hi>Bellaſire</hi>
never lov'd any thing, nor never had Inclination for any body? And yet by what
ſhe tells me her ſelf, ſhe had no aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the Count <hi>de
Lare,</hi> ſhe had too much eſteem for him, and ſhe uſed him with too
much reſpect: If ſhe had not been in Love with him, ſhe would have hated
him for the long Perſecutions that he and his Friends raiſed againſt her.
No <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> you have deceived me, you were not ſuch as I
believed you; <hi>I</hi> adored you as one that had never loved any thing, that
was the foundation of my Love. <hi>I</hi> find no ſuch thing, it is juſt
therefore <hi>I</hi> recall all the Love <hi>I</hi> had for you: But, ſaid
<hi>I</hi> to my ſelf again, If ſhe had told me truth, what a notorious
injuſtice do <hi>I</hi> do her? And how much <hi>I</hi> plague my ſelf in
robbing my ſelf of all the happineſs <hi>I</hi> enjoyed in her Love.</p>
               <p>While <hi>I</hi> was in theſe thoughts, <hi>I</hi> reſolved
to ſpeak once more to <hi>Bellaſire; I</hi> believed <hi>I</hi> ſhould
tell her better what grieved me, and <pb n="138" facs="tcp:62420:77"/>ſhould ſatisfie
my ſelf in all doubts more clearly than ever: I did what I reſolv'd; I
ſpoke to her, but it was not for the laſt time, and the next day I took up
the ſame diſcourſe with more heat than I had done the day before: But
<hi>Bellaſire,</hi> who thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, with a moſt unwearied patience, and
wonderful ſweetneſs, had endured all my ſuſpicions, and had endeavoured
to clear them, begun to be tired with the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a Jealouſie ſo
violent and ſo ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſo</hi> (ſaid ſhe, one day to me) I perceive you
have got a Capricio in your head that will deſtroy the paſſion you had
for me; but know, at the ſame time that it will inevitably ruine the Love I
had for you. Conſider, I beſeech you, about what it is that you torment me
and your ſelf too about a dead Man whom you cannot fancy that I Lov'd ſince
I did not Marry him; for if I had had but the leaſt inclination for him, my
Parents would have Marryed me to him, for there was nothing elſe that could
hinder it. It is true Madam, that I am Jealous of a dead Man, and that is it
that breaks my heart: If the Count of <hi>Lare</hi> were yet living, I ſhould
judge by your manner of uſage to him, how you did uſe him formerly; and
what you do for me <pb n="139" facs="tcp:62420:77"/>would convince me that you did not Love
him; I ſhould have the pleaſure in Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, to deprive him of the
hopes you have given him, notwithſtanding all you can tell me; but he is
dead, and dyed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in an opinion, that if he had lived, you might have
loved him. Ah Madam, I cannot but be unhappy every time I ſhall think that
any other but my ſelf could fancy that you could Love him. But
<hi>Alphonſo</hi> (ſaid ſhe) if I had Lov'd, why did not I Marry then?
Becauſe (anſwered I) you did not love him enough, and that the averſion
you had for Marriage, could not be overcome by a weak Inclination. I know you
love me much better than ever you loved the Count of <hi>Lare;</hi> but let
your love for him have been never ſo little, it has deſtroyed all my
happineſs, ſince I am no more the only Man that has pleaſed you, nor am
not the firſt that has made you ſenſible of Love; your heart has been
fill'd with other thoughts than thoſe I ſupplyed: In a word, Madam, it is
no more what made me the happieſt Man in the World, neither are you to me of
that value I firſt ſet upon you. Pray tell me, <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> how you
could live at eaſe with thoſe you formerly were in Love with all? I would
fain know whether you found in them a heart that never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:62420:78"/>had felt any paſſion: I never ſought for any ſuch,
Madam, ſaid I, nor did I ever hope to find any; I never looked upon them as
Women that could love nothing elſe but me; I was ſatisfied to believe that
they loved me far beyond all others that they had had any Inclination for: But
for you, Madam, it is not the ſame, I always look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon you as one that was
above the reach of Love, and who would never have known what it was, had it not
been for me. I thought my ſelf not only happy, but proud to have been able to
make ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary a Conqueſt: For pitty ſake leave me not in the
uncertainty in which I am; if you have concealed any thing from me concerning
the Count <hi>de Lare,</hi> confeſs it; the owning it, and your ſincerity
will perhaps, leſſen the trouble which I may conceive for it: Clear my
ſuſpicions, and do not let me ſet a higher value upon you than I ought,
or a leſs than you deſerve. <hi>Bellaſire</hi> made anſwer, If you had
not loſt your ſenſes, you would eaſily judge that ſince I did not
perſwade you, I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go about it; but if I could add any thing to
what I have already told you, it would be an infallible ſign that I never had
any inclination for the Count of <hi>Lare,</hi> being I ſay I had not. If I
had loved him, <pb n="141" facs="tcp:62420:78"/>nothing ſhould make me deny it; I
ſhould believe my ſelf guilty of a hainous Crime if I ſhould renounce any
kindneſs I might have for a dead man who had deſerved it; ſo that you may
be aſſured, <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that I never had any that may
diſpleaſe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me then of it, Madam, cryed I, tell it me a thouſand
times over, write it to me; In fine, reſtore me again to the pleaſure of
loving you as I did, and above all, pardon me the vexation I give you;
<hi>I</hi> torment my ſelf more than <hi>I</hi> do you, and if <hi>I</hi>
could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem my ſelf out of the ſtate <hi>I</hi> am in, <hi>I</hi> would
do it at the hazard of my life.</p>
               <p>Theſe laſt words made an impreſſion upon
<hi>Bellaſire,</hi> ſhe clearly ſaw <hi>I</hi> was not Maſter of my
ſenſes; ſhe promiſed me to write down all that ever ſhe thought or
did for the Count <hi>de Lare;</hi> and though they were things that ſhe had
already told me a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, yet <hi>I</hi> felt a certain pleaſure
to think that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſee them written with her own hand. The
next day ſhe ſent me what ſhe promis'd, <hi>I</hi> found an exact
Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of all that the Count of <hi>Lare</hi> had done for her, and all
ſhe did to cure him of his paſſion, with all the reaſons that might
perſwade me to believe what ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be true. This Narrative was
made after a manner that ought to have <pb n="142" facs="tcp:62420:79"/>cur'd me of all my
Caprichio's, but is wrought a contrary effect upon me: <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun with
being angry with my ſelf, for having forced <hi>Bellaſire</hi> to ſpend
ſo much time in thinking of the Count <hi>de Lare:</hi> Thoſe parts of her
Narrative, where ſhe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulariſed his actions, were inſupportable to
me; <hi>I</hi> thought ſhe had too good a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the actions of a man
that was indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to her; thoſe which ſhe related cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorily,
perſwaded me that there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more behind which ſhe durſt not
own to me. In fine, <hi>I</hi> made a bad conſtruction of all, and came to
ſee <hi>Bellaſire</hi> more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and more deſperate than ever: She,
that well knew <hi>I</hi> ought to be very well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, was much offended
to ſee me ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, which ſhe made me underſtand with more force
than ſhe uſed to do. <hi>I,</hi> on the other ſide (as angry as
<hi>I</hi> was) began to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my ſelf as well as <hi>I</hi> could;
<hi>I</hi> ſaw <hi>I</hi> was in the wrong, but it was not in my power to be
in a right ſenſe: <hi>I</hi> told her that my extream nicety in what ſhe
might have thought of the Count <hi>de Lare</hi> was a true mark of the great
paſſion and eſteem <hi>I</hi> had for her, and that the great value
<hi>I</hi> ſet upon her heart, made me ſo apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of any body
elſe having a ſhare in it; <hi>I</hi> ſaid all <hi>I</hi> could think of
to make my Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie <pb n="143" facs="tcp:62420:79"/>more excuſable.
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> would not admit of my reaſons; ſhe told me that
ſlight doubts might ariſe from what <hi>I</hi> had told her, but ſuch a
long and obſtinate Jealouſie could be produced from nothing elſe, but
from an ill humour, inſomuch that ſhe began to be apprehenſive of living
with me, and that if <hi>I</hi> continued in this manner, ſhe ſhould be
forced to change her opinion. Theſe Words made me tremble, <hi>I</hi> threw
my ſelf at her feet, <hi>I</hi> aſſured her <hi>I</hi> would never more
ſpeak to her of my ſuſpicions; and <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved within my ſelf,
that <hi>I</hi> ſhould be able to be as good as my promiſe; but it was for
a few dayes only, <hi>I</hi> quickly begun again to vex her, <hi>I</hi> often
ask'd her pardon, and as often made her think that I ſtill believed ſhe had
loved the Count of <hi>Lare,</hi> and that this thought would render me
eternally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy.</p>
               <p>I had a long Friendſhip with a man of quality, called <hi>Don
Mauriques,</hi> he was a Man of extraordinary merit; the tyes that were betwixt
us, had created a great confidence betwixt <hi>Bellaſire</hi> and him, their
amity was never diſpleaſing to me, nay, <hi>I</hi> took plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in
making it greater; he took notice ſeveral times of the ill humour <hi>I</hi>
had been in of late. Though <hi>I</hi> concealed nothing from him, <hi>I</hi>
was ſo much aſhamed of my <pb n="144" facs="tcp:62420:80"/>Caprichio, that <hi>I</hi>
durſt not own it to him: He came one day to viſit <hi>Bellaſire,</hi>
where <hi>I</hi> was more unreaſonable than ever, and ſhe more weary of my
Jealouſie than ſhe uſed. <hi>Don Mauriques</hi> knew by the changing of
our Countenances, that we had ſome little qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel. <hi>I</hi> always begged
of <hi>Bellaſire</hi> never to tell him of my weakneſs, and pray'd her
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as <hi>I</hi> ſaw him enter, to ſay nothing of it; but ſhe was
reſolved to put me out of Countenance, and without giving me time to oppoſe
her, ſhe told Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> all the cauſe of my diſquiet; he
ſeemed to be ſo aſtoniſhed at it, he found it ſo ill groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and he
handled me ſo ſeverely for it, that he put me quite beſides my ſelf:
You ſhall be Judge Sir, whether <hi>I</hi> was not mad, and how prone
<hi>I</hi> was to Jealouſie; for it ſeemed to me that Don
<hi>Mauriques,</hi> after the manner he condemned me, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs'd
by <hi>Bellaſire: I</hi> perceived well enough, that <hi>I</hi> paſſed
the limits of reaſon; but <hi>I</hi> could not believe that he would be ſo
ſevere in his Condemnation, unleſs he were in Love with <hi>Bellaſire.
I</hi> fancied then that Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> had been ſo a great while,
and that <hi>I</hi> ſeemed too happy to him for being beloved by her, that he
did not think <hi>I</hi> ought to complain, though ſhe had loved another.
<hi>I</hi> believed likewiſe that <pb n="145" facs="tcp:62420:80"/>
                  <hi>Bellaſire</hi>
her ſelf perceived that Don <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> had more than an ordinary
Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for her. I fancied ſhe was glad to be adored (as all Women for
the moſt part are) and without ſuſpecting her of Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; I was
Jealous of the Friendſhip which ſhe had for a Man whom ſhe believed her
Lover. <hi>Bellaſire</hi> and Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> ſeeing me thus
diſtracted, were far from imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what cauſed the diſorder of my mind;
they endeavonred with all the induſtry they could, to bring me to my ſelf
again, but their diſcourſes rather aggravated my vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I left them,
and when I was alone I repreſented to my ſelf this new Misfortune, which I
fancy'd far beyond the other; I found then my want of reaſon in appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending
danger from a Man that was no more in a condition to do me any harm. I found
Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> every way a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Man, he was handſome;
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> had a great eſteem and frienſhip for him, ſhe uſed
to ſee him often; ſhe was weary of my ill humours and Caprichios, and me
thought ſhe was glad to make her ſelf mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with him upon my ſcore; that
ſhe would inſenſibly give him the place which I held in her Love; to
ſay all, I was now more Jealous of Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> than I had been 
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:62420:81"/>before of the Count of <hi>Lare.</hi> I knew he had been
in Love with another Lady a great while; but this Lady was in all things ſo
far inferiour to <hi>Bellaſire,</hi> that his paſſion for her was no
ſecurity to me. However, as my genious would not utterly abandon me ſo to
my Caprice, but that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained to me ſtill, Witt enough to keep me in
ſuſpence; I was not ſo unjuſt, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Don
<hi>Mauriques</hi> endeavoured in any wiſe to defeat me of
<hi>Bellaſire:</hi> I fanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he fell in Love with her unknown to himſelf,
and without deſiring to be ſo, and that he ſtrove to reſiſt his
paſſion, becauſe of the friendſhip that was betwixt us, and that
although he ſaid nothing of it to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſire,</hi> yet he gave her to
underſtand that he Loved her without hoping a return. <hi>I</hi> thought I
had no reaſon to complain of Don <hi>Mauriques,</hi> ſince I believed it
was for my ſake he forbore to declare his paſſion. In fine, as <hi>I</hi>
was Jealous of a dead Man without knowing why, ſo likewiſe <hi>I</hi> was
Jealous of my Friend, and believed him my Rival, without thinking that
<hi>I</hi> had cauſe to be angry with him. It were in vain to tell you what
<hi>I</hi> ſuffer'd by ſuch extravagant thoughts, being it is eaſie to
imagine it: When <hi>I</hi> met Don <hi>Mauriques, I</hi> excuſed my 
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:62420:81"/>ſelf for concealing from him the diſquiet the
buſineſs of the Count of <hi>Lare</hi> had cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated me, but told him
nothing of my new Jealouſie; nor to <hi>Bellaſire,</hi> fearing leaſt, if
ſhe knew it, ſhe ſhould utterly forſake me. Being alwayes perſwaded
that ſhe ſtill Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me very much, <hi>I</hi> believed if <hi>I</hi> could
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my paſſion, and keep my ſelf within the bounds of Reaſon,
ſhe would not leave me for Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> ſo that the intereſt of
my Jealouſie oblig'd me to conceal it: <hi>I</hi> begged
<hi>Bellaſires</hi> pardon, and aſſured her that I had perfectly
recover'd my right ſenſes; ſhe was glad to ſee me in that opinion at
leaſt, though the perfect knowledge ſhe had of my humour, made her eaſily
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that I was not ſo calme within as <hi>I</hi> outwardly ſeemed to
be.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> continued his viſits to her as he
uſed to do, and ſomewhat more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, by reaſon of the freedom they
uſed to one another in diſcourſing of my Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> having taken notice that I was offended at her for telling
him of it, took care to ſpeak no more of it in my preſence; but if ſhe
ſaw me in an ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, ſhe would complain to him, and pray him to help
her to cure me. It was my ill Fate to take notice two or three times that ſhe
broke off her diſcourſe with Don <pb n="148" facs="tcp:62420:82"/>
                  <hi>Mauriques,</hi>
at my coming into the Room; you may judge what ſuch a thing would produce in
a head as jealous as mine: For all this, I found <hi>Bellaſire</hi> ſo kind
to me, and ſeemed ſo glad as often as ſhe ſaw me in a good humour, that
<hi>I</hi> could not believe that ſhe loved Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> ſo
paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to hold a correſpondence with him; neither could
<hi>I</hi> fancy that Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> ever had a deſign to engage her
to him, ſince <hi>I</hi> ſaw all his care was to hinder us from falling
out; ſo that <hi>I</hi> could not well find out what their thoughts were for
one another; many times <hi>I</hi> did not know my own; ſo in a word,
<hi>I</hi> was the wretchedeſt of all Man-kind. Upon a time, as <hi>I</hi>
came into the Room, ſhe was whiſpering ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Don
<hi>Mauriques,</hi> but ſo, as if ſhe would not have me percieve that ſhe
ſpoke to him. <hi>I</hi> remembred then that ſhe threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me ſeveral
times, when <hi>I</hi> perſecuted her about the Count of <hi>Lare,</hi> to
make me jealous of a living Man, to cure me of that <hi>I</hi> had of the dead;
<hi>I</hi> believed it was to make good that promiſe, that ſhe uſed Don
<hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> ſo kindly; and let me take notice, that there was a
ſecret correſpondence betwixt them. This opinion leſſen'd my trouble,
and made me forbear for ſome dayes to <pb n="149" facs="tcp:62420:82"/>ſpeak to her of
it; but at laſt, <hi>I</hi> reſolv'd to declare my mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> went to ſee her with this reſolution, and
caſting my ſelf down at her feet, I ſaid to her, <hi>I</hi> confeſs
Madam that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign you had to afflict me, has had the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs you
expected: you have given me all the diſquiet you can wiſh; you have made me
feel, as you have promis'd, that the jealouſie which is conceived of the
living, is much more cruel than any we can have of the dead. <hi>I</hi>
deſerved to be puniſhed for my ſolly, and you have done it
ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently: If you did but know how <hi>I</hi> have been tormented for
thoſe very things which <hi>I</hi> believed you did of purpoſe, you would
quickly ſee that you may make me unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py when you pleaſe to go about it:
What would you ſay, <hi>Alphonſo</hi> ſaid ſhe? You fancy, <hi>I</hi>
deſign'd to make you Jealous; do not you know that I have been too much
afflicted for that you had againſt my will, to deſire you ſhould be any
more ſo? Ah! Madam (ſaid <hi>I</hi>) leave tormenting me, once more
<hi>I</hi> tell you, <hi>I</hi> have ſuffer'd enough; and though <hi>I</hi>
ſaw that your manner of converſing with Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> was only to
execute the promiſe you made me, for all that, it was to me a moſt
ſenſible affliction: <pb n="150" facs="tcp:62420:83"/>
                  <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> replyed
<hi>Bellaſire,</hi> either you are out of your Wits, or elſe you have a
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to torment me; you ſhall never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me that <hi>I</hi> ever
intended to create you the leaſt Jealouſie, nor ſhall you convince me
that you could have any. <hi>I</hi> would have you, added ſhe, looking upon
me, after having been Jealous of a dead Man whom <hi>I</hi> never loved, to be
Jealous of a living Man that does not love me. How, Madam, ſaid <hi>I,</hi>
you had no intention to make me Jealous of Don <hi>Mauriques;</hi> you only
plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow your inclination in doing what you do; was it not to give me
cauſe of ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, your leaving of whiſpering to him, or changing
your diſcourſe when <hi>I</hi> come into the Room? Ah Madam, if that be
ſo, <hi>I</hi> am more unhappy than <hi>I</hi> thought my ſelf; nay,
<hi>I</hi> am the moſt unfortunate of all Man-kind. You are not the moſt
unhappy (replyed <hi>Bellaſire</hi>) but the moſt unreaſonable of all
Man-kind; and if <hi>I</hi> ſhould follow the dictates of reaſon,
<hi>I</hi> ſhould break off with you this very moment, and never ſee you
more: But is it poſſible, <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> added ſhe, that you can be
Jealous of Don <hi>Mauriques?</hi> How can I be otherwiſe, Madam, ſaid I,
when you keep a correſpondence with him which I muſt not know. I conceal it
from you, <pb n="151" facs="tcp:62420:83"/>ſaid ſhe, becauſe you were angry when I
ſpoke to him of your ſtrange imaginations; and that I had no mind you
ſhould know that I ſpoke to him ſtill of your ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and of the
diſſatisfaction I receive from them. How Madam (ſaid I) you complain of
my humours to my Rival, and you think ill of me for being troubled at it? I
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to your Friend (ſaid ſhe) and not to your Rival. Don
<hi>Mauriques</hi> is my Rival (replyed I) and I cannot think that you can
avoid acknowledging it; and I (ſaid ſhe) cannot believe you dare tell me he
is ſo, knowing as you do, that he ſpends whole dayes in praiſing you to
me. It is very true (ſaid I) that I do not ſuſpect that Don
<hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> does any way endeavour to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine me; but that does not
hinder but he may be in Love with you; nay more, I do believe he never yet
ſpoke to you of his Love; but after the manner you uſe him, he will not be
long before he ſpeaks to you of it, and the hopes that your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings give
him, will make him without ſcruple of Conſcience paſs over all the tyes
and obligations of the Friendſhip that was betwixt us. Can any Man be ſo
void of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as you are, anſwer'd <hi>Bellaſire?</hi> Mark well your
own words, you tell me Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> 
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:62420:84"/>ſpeaks for
you to me, that he is in Love with me, and that he does not ſpeak to me for
himſelf; where will you find things ſo contradictory? Is it not true, that
you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I love you, and that you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced Don <hi>Mauriques</hi>
does ſo too? It is very true, anſwered I, that I believe both the one and
the other. If you believe it, cryed ſhe, how can you imagin that I can love
you and love Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> too? Or that Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> can be
in love with me, and love you ſtill? <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I am infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
troubled to find the diſorders of your mind to be ſo exorbitant; I now
perceive your diſeaſe is incurable, and that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to Marry you,
I muſt at the ſame time reſolve to be the moſt miſerable Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of
the world. Aſſuredly I love you very much, but not ſo much as to
purchaſe you at ſo dear a rate; the Jealouſie of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers is
troubleſome, but the Jealouſie of Husbands is inſupportable; you make me
ſo plainly ſee what I am like to ſuffer, that I believe I ſhall never
be Marryed to you: I love you too well not to be ſenſibly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted to
ſee that I ſhall not (as I hoped) ſpend my dayes with you. Leave me alone
I conjure you, your words and your ſight do but increaſe my ſorrow.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:62420:84"/>At theſe words ſhe roſe without
giving me time to anſwer, and went to her Cloſet, and lockt the door, which
ſhe would not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen upon no intreaty. I was forced to go home ſo
deſperate, and ſo irreſolved in my own thoughts, that I wonder I did not
run out of the little wit I had left me: I came next day to ſee
<hi>Bellaſire,</hi> whom I found ſad and afflicted; ſhe ſpoke to me
without any manner of ſharpneſs, nay, with great ſweetneſs, but without
ſaying any thing that might make me apprehend that ſhe would abandon me; I
thought ſhe ſtudyed whether ſhe ſhould or no, as we eaſily flatter
our ſelves, I believed ſhe would not remain long in the mind ſhe was in:
I asked her pardon for my folly as I had done a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times before; I prayed
her to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Don <hi>Mauriques;</hi> I Conjured her upon my knees
to change her conduct with him, and not to treat him for the future ſo well
as to give me diſquiet of mind. I will not tell Don <hi>Mauriques</hi>
(ſaid ſhe) any thing of your folly, but I will alter nothing of my way of
living with him; if I thought he Lov'd me, I would never ſee him more, though
you had never been concerned at it, but he has only a Friendſhip for me; nay
more, you know he loves elſe-where; I eſteem him, I love him, you have
conſented <pb n="154" facs="tcp:62420:85"/>I ſhould; therefore the diſquiet you
receive upon his ſcore, proceeds from your folly and diſorder of mind: If I
ſhould ſatisfie you, you would quickly pick a quarrel with me upon ſome
other Mans account, as you do upon his; therefore do not vex your ſelf about
my conduct with him; for aſſuredly, <hi>I</hi> ſhall not change it.
<hi>I</hi> am willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve (ſaid <hi>I</hi>) that all you ſay is
true, and that you do not believe that Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> loves you; but
<hi>I</hi> believe it Madam, and that's enough; <hi>I</hi> know you have only a
Friendſhip for him, but it is a Friendſhip ſo tender, ſo full of
confidence, eſteem and liking, that although it ſhould never riſe to the
heighth of a paſſion, yet I have reaſon to be jealous of it, and to
apprehend that it may too much affect your heart: The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal you make of
altering your way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding with him, gives me to underſtand that
<hi>I</hi> do not fear him without cauſe. To ſhew you (ſaid ſhe) that
the refuſal I make you, does not concern Don <hi>Mauriques,</hi> but your
Caprice only; if you deſired me not to ſee the Man of the world which is
moſt deſpicable to me, I would deny it you, as I do, to leave off having a
Friendſhip for Don <hi>Mauriques.</hi> I believe you Madam (ſaid I) but I
am not Jealous of the Man of the world you deſpiſe moſt; it is of a Man, 
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:62420:85"/>whom you love well enough to prefer him before my quiet; I
neither ſuſpect you of weakneſs or change, but I muſt confeſs I
cannot ſuffer that your heart ſhould enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any kindneſs for any man
but my ſelf; I am grieved alſo that you do not hate Don <hi>Mauriques,</hi>
though you know he loves you, and I think it belongs to me alone to have the
advantage over all others to love you without being hated, ſo that you muſt
grant my requeſt without being offended at my Jealouſie. I ſaid all I
could think of, to induce her to grant what I deſire, but all to no
purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Though I had been a long time Jealous of Don <hi>Mauriques,</hi>
yet I had ſo much power over my paſſion, as to hide it from him; and
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> was ſo diſcreet, as to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to him of it;
but made him believe that my Chagrin was ſtill cauſed by the Jealouſie I
had of the Count of <hi>Lare;</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, ſhe held on in her old
way of entertaining Don <hi>Mauriques;</hi> and he being ignorant of my
thoughts of him, converſed ſtill with her as he uſed to do, ſo that my
Jealouſie increaſed daily, and was grown to that height, that I
perſecuted <hi>Bellaſire</hi> without intermiſſion.</p>
               <p>After I had thus perſecuted her a long time, and that this
fair Creature had in <pb n="156" facs="tcp:62420:86"/>vain tryed all wayes to cure me of my
Caprice: She fell ſick, and was ſo ill, that for two dayes I could not be
admitted to ſee her; the third day ſhe ſent for me, I found her much
alter'd, but I thought that was cauſed by her indiſpoſition: She made me
ſit down near a pallet Bed on which ſhe lay; and having been ſilent for a
good while, <hi>Alponſo</hi> (ſaid ſhe) I believe you have perceived
eaſily this good while, that I have been endeavouring to reſolve
abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to break off with you; yet for all I had many convincing
reaſons to induce me to it, I do not believe I ſhould be able ever to do
it, if you had not given me ſtrength by the ſtrange extravagancies of your
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. If this extravagancy were not ſo great, and that I could
believe it were poſſible to cure you of it by a diſcreet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, or
the auſtereſt way of living, my for you was ſtrong enough to make me
embrace it with joy; but ſince I ſee that this diſorder of your
underſtanding is incurable, and that although you have no cauſe of being
troubled, you fancy things that never were, nor ever will be, I am forced for
your peace and mine, to let you know that I abſolutely reſolved to break
off with you, and never to Marry you. I do tell you moreover, this time, which
ſhall be <pb n="157" facs="tcp:62420:86"/>the laſt that we ſhall have any particular
converſe together, that I never had any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination for any man but for your
ſelf, and you alone were capable of making me in Love. But ſince you have
confirmed me in the opinion <hi>I</hi> have, that none can be happy that is in
Love with any man: You, whom <hi>I</hi> thought the only man worthy of Love,
may be aſſured, that <hi>I</hi> will never be in Love with any Man more;
and that thoſe impreſſions which you have made in my heart, have been the
only, and ſhall be the laſt it ſhall ever receive; nor would <hi>I</hi>
have you believe that <hi>I</hi> have too much Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for Don
<hi>Mauriques, I</hi> refuſed to change my conduct with him, to ſee if you
would not recover your right ſenſes again, and to give my ſelf room to
beſtow my ſelf upon you once more, being once aſſured that your
diſtemper was capable of being cured; but <hi>I</hi> was not ſo happy, and
this was the only reaſon that kept me from giving you that ſatisfaction:
This reaſon being no more, <hi>I</hi> do ſacrifice Don <hi>Mauriques</hi>
to your deſire, and therefore have prayed him never to ſee me more:
<hi>I</hi> ask you pardon for telling him of your Jealouſie, for <hi>I</hi>
could not avoid it, and he would have found it out himſelf by the rupture
betwixt us. My Father ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived laſt night, <hi>I</hi> acquainted him with my 
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:62420:87"/>reſolution, he is gone at my requeſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your
Father of it; ſo that, <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> you muſt think no more of
making me change this reſolve: <hi>I</hi> have told Don <hi>Mauriques,</hi>
what was requiſite to ſtrengthen my reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution before <hi>I</hi> told
you of it; <hi>I</hi> have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd it as much as <hi>I</hi> could, more
perhaps for the love of my ſelf, than for the love of you; and believe it,
none ſhall ever be ſo abſolutely, nor ſo faithfully beloved as you have
been.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> know not whether <hi>Bellaſire</hi> continued her
diſcourſe, but as my ſurpriſe was ſo great from the time ſhe begun,
that <hi>I</hi> had not power to interrupt her; ſo all my ſtrength left me
at thoſe laſt words which <hi>I</hi> told you, and ſwooned away:
<hi>I</hi> know not what <hi>Bellaſire</hi> or her Servants did, but when
<hi>I</hi> came to my ſelf, I found my ſelf in my Bed, and Don
<hi>Mauriques</hi> by me, as much in deſpair as I was.</p>
               <p>When all the Servants were with-drawn, he omitted nothing that
might juſtifie him againſt all the ſuſpicions <hi>I</hi> had of him,
and that might ſhow me how much he was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted for being the innocent
cauſe of my Misfortune: As he had a great Love for me, ſo likewiſe he had
a great feeling of my condition; <hi>I</hi> fell deſperately ill; <hi>I</hi>
then, (but too late) found out the injuries <hi>I</hi> did <pb n="159" facs="tcp:62420:87"/>my Friend; <hi>I</hi> conjured him to pardon me, and to viſit
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> to beg for pardon for me, and to endeavour to pacifie her.
Don <hi>Mauriques</hi> went to her Houſe, but was told ſhe was not to be
ſeen; he went every day while my ſickneſs laſted, but to no purpoſe;
as ſoon as <hi>I</hi> was able, <hi>I</hi> went thither my ſelf, but
<hi>I</hi> had the ſame anſwer: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time <hi>I</hi> came, one of
her Women came and told me from her, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould come no more
thither, for ſhe would not ſee me. <hi>I</hi> was in deſpair when I ſaw
no more hopes of ſeeing <hi>Bellaſire;</hi> yet <hi>I</hi> alwayes believed
that the ſtrong paſſion which ſhe had for me, would make her return
again if ever <hi>I</hi> had but the opportunity to ſpeak to her once more:
But ſeeing ſhe would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſpeak to me, <hi>I</hi> loſt all
hope; <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs, that to hope no more to poſſeſs
<hi>Bellaſire,</hi> was a moſt cruel pain to one that was ſo near it, and
lov'd her ſo paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>I</hi> ſought all wayes to ſee her,
ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided me as carefully, and lived ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, that it was altogether
impoſſible for me to ſee her.</p>
               <p>All the content <hi>I</hi> had, was to go and paſs whole
Nights under her Window, but <hi>I</hi> could not obtain ſo much as the
ſatisfaction of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them open. <hi>I</hi> believed one night, as I came
there to hear them open, the next Night <pb n="160" facs="tcp:62420:88"/>I fancied the
ſame thing. In fine, I flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my ſelf with the thought that
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> had a Curioſity to ſee me, without being ſeen; and
that ſhe came to her Window when ſhe heard me going away. I reſolved to
feign as if <hi>I</hi> were going away, and to return abru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tly again, to ſee if ſhe would not appear; I did
ſo: I went to the end of the Street, as if I were going away, and I heard the
Window open diſtinctly: I came back again preſently; I thought I perceived
<hi>Bellaſire:</hi> but in coming nearer ſaw, a Man creeping cloſe to the
Wall under her Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, as if he would hide himſelf: I thought, I knew not
how, in ſpight of the Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that it was Don <hi>Mauriques;</hi> this
thought put me quite out of frame, I preſently Imagined that
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> lov'd him; that he was there to ſpeak to her, that ſhe
open'd her Windows for him; to be ſhort, I believed Don <hi>Mauriques</hi>
had gained <hi>Bellaſire</hi> from me: In the fury I was in, I drew my Sword,
and we began to fight with a great deal of heat. I found I had wounded him in
two places, but he ſtill defended himſelf; at the Noiſe we made, or
elſe by <hi>Bellaſire</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, people came out to ſeparate us. Don
<hi>Mauriques</hi> knew me by the light of the flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus, he went back two or
three ſtepps, I ſteppt forward to take his Sword from him; 
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:62420:88"/>but he let fall the point, and told me with a feeble
Voice, is it you <hi>Alphonſo?</hi> And is it poſſible that <hi>I</hi>
have been ſo unfortunate as to fight againſt you? Yes Traytor, ſaid
<hi>I,</hi> and it is <hi>I</hi> that will pluck out this Heart, for Robbing me
of <hi>Bellaſire,</hi> you paſs the Nights at her Window, while they are
kept ſhut for me. Don <hi>Mauriques,</hi> who was lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the Wall
(ſupported by ſome that ſtood about him) being he could not well ſtand,
looking upon me with Eyes full of Tears, ſaid, <hi>I</hi> am unfortunate
allways in Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your diſcontent; the cruelty of my Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is ſome
conſolation to me for the Death you give. I die ſaid he, and the condition
<hi>I</hi> am in, ought to perſwade the Truth of my laſt words; <hi>I</hi>
ſwear unto you, that <hi>I</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had a thought for <hi>Bellaſire</hi>
that could diſpleaſe you; the love <hi>I</hi> have for another, and which I
have not concealed from you, carried me abroad this Night; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved I was
watched and dog'd; I walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very faſt, I run through ſeveral ſtreets,
till at laſt I ſtopt in the place where you found me without knowing that
it was <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſire's</hi> Houſe: This is the Truth, my dear
<hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I conjure you not to be troubled at my Death; I forgive
you with all my heart, he continued ſtretching out his Arms to embrace me: at
this he loſt his Sence, <pb n="162" facs="tcp:62420:89"/>and fell dead upon thoſe that
held him up.</p>
               <p>I want words, my Lord, to expreſs the ſtate I was in, and
the Rage I had againſt my ſelf; I was twenty times upon the point of
running my ſelf through, then eſpecially when I ſaw Don <hi>Maurques</hi>
expiring. They drew me away from him; the Count of <hi>Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre</hi> Father to
<hi>Bellaſire,</hi> who came out, hearing Don <hi>Mauriques,</hi> and my Name
carried me home and put me into my Fathers Hands. They would not leave me alone
by reaſon of the Fury I was in, but their care had been fruitleſs, if my
Religion had left me the liberty of killing my ſelf. The grief I knew
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> was in for the accident that hapned upon her ſcore, and
the noiſe it made in the Court, made me mad. When I conſider'd that all the
afflictions ſhe had, and all the torments I indured, befell all through my
fault, I was in a fury that cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. The Count of
<hi>Guavarre</hi> who ſtill retained a great friendſhip for me, came ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
often to ſee me, and attributed the noiſe and buſtle I had made, to the
extremity of my paſſion for his Daughter. I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by him, that
ſhe was not to be paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and that her grief exceeded the bounds of
reaſon: I was too well acquainted with her humour, and her extream
tenderneſs of <pb n="163" facs="tcp:62420:89"/>her reputation, not to know without being
told, all that ſhe could feel for ſo unhappy an accident. Some dayes after
this miſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, they told me there was a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man from
<hi>Bellaſire</hi> that deſired to ſpeak to me from her: I was
tranſported at the name of <hi>Bellaſire,</hi> who was ſo dear to me; I
bid him be call'd in, he gave me a Letter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I read theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter from <hi>Bellaſire</hi> to
<hi>Alphonſo.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>OUr ſeparation has made the world ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable to
me, that I could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger live in it with any content, and that late Accident
gave ſo deep a wound to my Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that I cannot ſtay in it without
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour. I will withdraw my ſelf unto a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, where I ſhall not be
forced to bear the ſhame of hearing the divers deſcants that ſhall be
made upon me; thoſe which you made, have occaſioned all my misfortunes, and
yet I could not reſolve to leave the world without taking my leave of you,
and without acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging to you that I love you ſtill, as Brutal as you
are; the inclination I had for you, and the remembrance of yours for me, will
be the first Sacrifice I ſhall offer up to God when I <pb n="164" facs="tcp:62420:90"/>give my ſelf to him; the Austerities of the life I am going to lead,
will ſeem eaſie to me, for nothing can be tedious to one that has felt the
ſmart of tearing her ſelf away from what paſſionately loved her, and
ſhe loved above all things. I will own further, that no other way of living
could ſecure me againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination which I have for you; and that
ſince our ſeparation, you never came to that fatal place where you
committed ſuch violence, but I was ready to ſpeak to you, and tell you that
I could not live without you; I am not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain whether <hi>I</hi> had not told
it you that very Night that you aſſaulted <hi>Don Mauriques,</hi> and
gaveſt me new Teſtimonies of thoſe ſuſpicions which cauſed all our
Misfortunes. Fare well <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> remember me ſometimes, and wiſh
for my quiet, that <hi>I</hi> may never remember you.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>There was nothing wanting to compleat my Misfortunes, but to be
aſſured that <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſire</hi> loved me ſtill, and that happily ſhe
had beſtowed her ſelf upon me again, if ſhe had not been hindered by my
own extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy; and that the ſame Accident that made me Kill my beſt
Friend, made me looſe my Miſtreſs too, and forced her to render her
ſelf unhappy all the reſt of her dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:62420:90"/>I asked him that brought me the Letter,
where <hi>Bellaſire</hi> was; he told me he had conducted her unto a Convent
of Nuns, of a very ſtrict Order, which came out of <hi>France</hi> lately;
and that as ſhe entred, ſhe gave him a Letter for her-Father, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
for me; I ran to this Monaſtery, I deſired I might ſee her, but in vain:
I met the Count of <hi>Guavarrc</hi> comeing out from thence; all his
Authority, and his Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to change her reſolution, were to no
purpoſe, ſhe took upon her the habit a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after: During her year of
probation, her Father and I uſed all our endeavours to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her to
come out, and I would not leave <hi>Navarre</hi> (as I had reſolved) untill I
loſt all hopes of ſeeing <hi>Bellaſire</hi> once more: But the day that I
knew ſhe had engaged her ſelf for ever, I came away without ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a
word to any body; my Father was dead, and there was none that could hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me;
I came into <hi>Catalonia</hi> with inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to take Shipping for
<hi>Africa,</hi> to ſpend my dayes in the Deſerts of that Country. I
happen'd by chance into this Houſe, I lik'd it, I found it retir'd and
ſolitary, and ſuch as I could wiſh for my purpoſe; I bought it: Here I
have liv'd this five years paſt, as melancholly a life as a man ought to do
that kill'd his Friend, that made the <pb n="166" facs="tcp:62420:91"/>amiableſt perſon
in the world the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, and that by his own fault, loſt the
pleaſure of ſpending his life agreeably with her. Now Sir, will you
continue ſtill in your belief, that your Misfortunes are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to
mine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſo</hi> left off here, and ſeemed to be ſo
over-charged with ſadneſs, by renewing the grief which the remembrance of
his Misfortunes paſt cauſed him, that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſeveral times
believed he was going to breath out his laſt. He ſaid all the things to him
that he thought capable of giving him eaſe; but he could not deny within
himſelf but that thoſe Misfortunes he heard related, might at leaſt come
in competition with thoſe he had ſuffer'd.</p>
               <p>In the mean time his grief for the loſs of <hi>Zayde</hi>
increaſed every day; he told <hi>Alphonſo</hi> he was reſolved to leave
<hi>Spain,</hi> and to go ſerve the Emperour in his War againſt the
<hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razens,</hi> who having gotten poſſeſſion of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily,</hi>
made daily incurſions into <hi>Italy. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo</hi> was not a little
afflicted at this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; he uſed all the arguments he could think of,
to diſſwade him, but his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours proved ineffectual.</p>
               <p>The diſquiet which Love creates, would not let
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> reſt in this ſolitude; he was prompted to leave it by a
ſecret hope, <pb n="167" facs="tcp:62420:91"/>to which he gave no great heed himſelf,
that he ſhould once more ſee <hi>Zayde.</hi> He reſolves therefore to
leave <hi>Alphonſo;</hi> never was there ſo ſad a ſeparation: They
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated over all the ſad adventures of their life; to which they added
that, of never hoping to ſee one another again; after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing mutually
to write to one another, <hi>Alphonſo</hi> remained in his ſolitude, and
<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> went to lye at <hi>Tortoſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He liv'd in a Houſe, the Garden whereof, was the greateſt
Ornament of that Town; he paſſed all the Night in walking; ſome part
whereof, he ſpent upon the Banks of of the River <hi>Elbe:</hi> Being wearied
with walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſate down at the foot of one of the Terraſſes of this
fine Garden; it was ſo low, that he cold hear ſome that were walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
there, talk: This noyſe did not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly awake him out of his Dreaming;
but at laſt he was ſtartled by the ſound of a voice like <hi>Zaydes,</hi>
which gave him (whether he would or no) both attention and curioſity; he
roſe up that he might come near to the Terraſſe: At firſt he heard
nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Alley in which they walked abutting upon this
Tarraſſe, they were fain to turn back again, and go further off from him.
He ſtood in the ſame place waiting their return; they came back as he hop'd
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:62420:92"/>they would, and he heard that ſame voyce again, which
ſurpriſed him before. <hi>There are too many Contrarieties</hi> (ſaid
ſhe) <hi>in the things that might make me happy; I cannot hope to be ſo,
but I ſhould think my grief leſs, if I could but have made him
under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand my meaning, and be aſſured of his.</hi> After theſe words,
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> could not well diſtinguiſh what they ſaid, becauſe
they that ſpoke began to go further off; they came back the ſecond time,
ſpeaking, <hi>It is true,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>that the force of our
firſt inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may excuſe that which I have ſuffered to grow in my
heart; but what a ſtrange effect of chance would it be (if it ſhould fall
out) that this inclination which ſeems to agree with my deſtiny, ſhould
ſerve one day to make me fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it with regret.</hi> This was all that
<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> could underſtand; the great reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance this voice
had with that of <hi>Zayde's</hi> amazed him, and perhaps, he had ſuſpected
her to be the ſame, if he had not heard her ſpeak Spaniſh: Though he
found that ſhe that ſpoke, had the accent of a Stranger, yet did not
reflect upon that, becauſe it was upon the borders of <hi>Spain,</hi> where
they do not ſpeak ſo exactly as in <hi>Caſtile,</hi> he pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her that
ſpoke, and her words made him judge that there was ſomething of
extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary in her Fortune. The next day he <pb n="169" facs="tcp:62420:92"/>parted from
<hi>Tortoſa,</hi> with deſign to take Shipping. He had not gone fat when he
ſaw in the middle of the River <hi>Iber</hi> a Barge ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry richly ſet out,
cover'd with a magnificent Tilt tucked up of all ſides, and in it ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Women, amongſt whom he ſaw <hi>Zayde,</hi> ſhe was ſtanding up as ioi
were to ſee the ſweetneſs of that River, and yet ſhe ſeemed to be in
a profound ſtudy. Here it were requiſite to have loſt a Miſtreſs
without all hopes of, retrieving her, to be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs what
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> felt at the ſight of <hi>Zayde:</hi> His ſurpriſe and
his joy were ſo great, that he knew not where he was, nor what he ſaw; he
looked earneſtly upon her, and knowing again all the dineaments of her face,
he was afraid to miſtake; he could not preſently imagine that ſhe (whom
he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved ſeparated from him by ſo many Seas) could be within the
breadth of one little Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of him; and yet he had preſently a mind to go to
her, and ſpeak to her; and make her take notice of him; but he was
apprehenſive of offending her, and ſo durſtſt not make himſelf to be
remark'd, or teſtifie his joy before thoſe that were with her. So
unexpected a happineſs, and ſo many different thoughts would not let him
fix up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a reſolution; but at laſt, having recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected himſelf, and
being aſſured that he <pb n="170" facs="tcp:62420:93"/>was not deceived, he decrees
within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not to diſcover himſelf to <hi>Zayde,</hi> but only to
follow her Barge to the Hort, where he hoped to find ſome opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>unity of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her in private;
he believed at leaſt to find out, what Country ſhe was, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe
was going; he fancied likewiſe by ſeeing thoſe that were in the Barge, to
be able to find out whether that Rival whom he believed like him were with her
or no; in fine, he thought himſelf now near the end of all his uncertainties,
and that at leaſt he might inform <hi>Zayd</hi> of the love he had for her.
He would gladly have wiſh'd that her eyes had been turned that way, but ſhe
was in ſuch a deep thoughtfulneſs that her looks continued ſtill fixed
upon the water. In the midſt of his Joy he remembred the perſon that he
heard ſpeak in the Garden of <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> and though ſhe ſpoke
Spaniſh, the accent of a ſtranger which he obſerved in her ſpeech, and
the ſight of <hi>Zayd</hi> ſo near the ſame place, made him Imagin it
might be ſhe her ſelf. This thought troubled the pleaſure he took in
ſeeing her again; he remembred what he had heard her ſay of a former
inclination; and notwithſtanding the Diſpoſition he might have to flatter
himſelf, he was too well perſwaded that <hi>Zayd</hi> lamented the
loſſe of a lover whom ſhe loved, who might have <pb n="171" facs="tcp:62420:93"/>a
part of that inclination; but her other following words which he ſtill
remembred gave him ſome hope; he imagin'd that it might not be
impoſſible, but that there was ſome thing writ of advantage for him; he
then began to doubt whether it was <hi>Zayd</hi> he had heard or not; and found
it very unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſhe could learn the Spaniſh Tongue in ſo ſhort a
ſpace of time.</p>
               <p>The diſquiet theſe uncertainties cauſed in him was
diſſipated by the joy he felt for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found <hi>Zayd</hi> again; and
without think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether he was beloved or not, all his mind was taken up with
the pleaſure he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped ſhortly to have of being once more ſeen by
<hi>Zayds</hi> fair Eyes; in the mean time he walked ſtill along by the River
ſide follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Barge; and though he Rid a great pace, ſome people that
followed on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back paſſed by him; he went ſome paces ont of the way
that they might not ſee his Face; but as one of them came behind the reſt
alone, the curioſity he had to learn ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>Zayde,</hi> made him
forget his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary caution, and asked him if he did not know who they were
that Sailed in that Barge. They are ſaid he, people of Quality amongſt the
<hi>Moores,</hi> that have been for ſome dayes at <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> and are
going to Ship them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a great Veſſel to go for their own 
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:62420:94"/>Country. In ſaying theſe words he looked with much
attention upon <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> and ſo Galloped to over-take his
Companions. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was ſomewhat ſurpriſed at this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
and was no longer in doubt, but that it was <hi>Zayde,</hi> whom he heard talk
in the Garden, ſince he knew that ſhe lay at <hi>Tortoſa:</hi> a turning
which the River made in that place where the way was very craggy, made him
loſe ſight of <hi>Zayde.</hi> At that very inſtant all thoſe
Horſe-men that paſſed by him, returned back to him; he found they knew
him, he endeavoured to go out of their way, but they ſo beſet him, that
there was no going from them; he knew him that was at the head of them to be
<hi>Oliban,</hi> one of the chief Commanders of the Prince of <hi>Leons</hi>
Guards; he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely troubled to be known by him: but his trouble was the
more, becauſe this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer told him, that he had been many dayes in queſt
of him, and that he had order from the Prince to bring him to Court. How! The
Prince is not ſatisfied with his Uſage to me, but he muſt more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over robb
me of my Liberty! It is the only Treaſure I have left me, and I'le periſh
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will ſuffer it to be taken from me. At theſe words he drew his
Sword, and without conſidering the number of thoſe that envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned 
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:62420:94"/>him, and flew with ſuch extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Courage upon
them, that he laid two or three of them flat, before they were able to put
themſelves in a poſture of Defence. <hi>Oliban</hi> commanded the Guards to
ſeize him only, and not to attempt any thing againſt his Life; they obeyd
him with difficulty, for <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> run at them with great Fury, that
they could no longer defend themſelves without offending him; but their
Captain amazed at <hi>Gonſalvos</hi> Wonderful Actions, and being fearful of
not being able to fulfil the Princes Orders, alighted from his Horſe; and
with one thruſt kill'd <hi>Gonſalvo's</hi> Horſe; the Horſe in his fall
ſo intangled his Rider, that it was impoſſible for him to diſengage
himſelf, his Sword alſo was broke in the fall; all his aſſailants
encompaſſed him, and <hi>Oliban</hi> with much civility repreſents to him
the impoſſibility of being able to reſiſt ſo many,
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was two ſenſible of it; but he thought it ſo great an
unhappineſs, to be conducted to <hi>Leon</hi> that he could not ſubmit to
it: <hi>Zayd</hi> but juſt found, and now going to be loſt, fill'd his Soul
with bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and deſpair; he was in ſuch a ſad ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that Don
<hi>Garcias</hi> his Officer, believed that his apprehenſion of being ill
treated made him have ſuch a repugnacy to go to Court; My Lord, ſaid he,
you muſt needs <pb n="174" facs="tcp:62420:95"/>be ignorant of what had pas'd at
<hi>Leon</hi> of late to have ſuch an apprehenſion of returning thither; I
am ignorant of all things, replyed <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> I only know that you
would do me a far greater favour, in taking away my Life, than in forcing me to
ſee the Prince of <hi>Leon.</hi> I would tell you more, replyed
<hi>Oliban,</hi> if I had not been expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Prince; let it
only ſuffice, that I aſſure you, that you need not fear any thing. I hope
the Affliction I receive by being compelled to return to <hi>Leon</hi>
againſt my will, will hinder me from being in a condition to ſatisfie Don
<hi>Garcias</hi> cruelty when I come there. As he ſaid theſe laſt words,
he ſaw <hi>Zaydes</hi> Barge again, but could not ſee her face, for ſhe
was ſate down with her Face turned from him. What a deſtiny is mine, ſaid
he within himſelf! I loſe <hi>Zayde</hi> at the very inſtant I found her;
when I ſaw her, and ſpoke to her in <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s houſe, ſhe
could not underſtand me; when I met her at <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> and might be
underſtood by her, I did not know her again; and now that I ſee her, that I
know her, and that ſhe might underſtand me, I cannot ſpeak to her, and
hope no more to ſee her, he remained for ſome time agitated betwixt theſe
various thoughts; then on a ſudden turning himſelf towards thoſe that led
him, I do not think, <pb n="175" facs="tcp:62420:95"/>ſaid he to them, you fear that I
can make my eſcape: I beg the favour of you, to let me go nearer to the
River, to ſpeak but one word or two to ſome that I ſee in that Barge; I
am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly troubled, anſwer'd <hi>Oliban,</hi> to have Orders ſo
contrary to your deſires, for I am for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to let you ſpeak to any Soul
alive, and you muſt give me your pardon if I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my Orders;
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was ſo nearly touched at this denial, that the Officer
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the violence of his Paſſion, and fearing he would call to his
aſſiſtance thoſe that were in the Barge, he commanded his men to lead
him further off from the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; which they did immediately, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Don
<hi>Gonſalvo</hi> to the next place of convenience to lodge that night; the
next day they took their journey to <hi>Leon</hi> and marched with ſo much
ſpeed that they arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there in few days. <hi>Oliban</hi> ſent one of his
people to acquaint the Prince that they were arrived, and ſtayed for his
comming back two hundred Paces from the Town; he that was ſent, brought Order
that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſhould be conducted into the Pallace by a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
and brought ſtraight into Don <hi>Garcia's</hi> Cloſet; <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>
was ſo ſad, that he let them carry him whither they would, without ſo
much as asking them whither they lead him.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the firſt Part of <hi>Zayde.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62420:96"/>
            <head>Books Printed and Sold by <hi>William Cade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> this
<hi>Michaelm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s-Term,</hi>1677.</head>
            <list>
               <item>SPaniſh Hiſtory, or a Relation of the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency that
happened in the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> between Don <hi>John</hi> of
<hi>Auſtria</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Nitard,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> Engliſh Princeſs: or, the Dutches-Queen, a Novel, being
<hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>Zayde,</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hiſtory, a Novel.
<hi>Octa.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> The Opinion of the Heathen, concerning the Immortality of
the Soul, by <hi>Ch. Blunt,</hi> Gent.</item>
               <item> Reflections on Antient and Modern Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PLAYS.</head>
               <item>The Rival Kings, or the Loves of <hi>Oroon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> and
<hi>Statira,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item> The Conſtant Nymph, or the Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Shepherdeſs: A
Paſtoral.</item>
               <item> The Counterfeit Bridegroom, or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated Widdow: A
Comedy.</item>
               <item> The French Conjurer: A Comedy.</item>
               <item> The Witts led by the Noſe: A Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:62420:96"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
